<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of popedom, containing the rise, progress, and decay thereof, &amp;c. written in High Dutch by Samuel Puffendorff ; translated into English by J.C.</title>
            <author>Pufendorf, Samuel, Freiherr von, 1632-1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 247 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 119 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56252</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4176</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5058</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12376674</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12376674</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60638</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56252)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60638)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 223:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of popedom, containing the rise, progress, and decay thereof, &amp;c. written in High Dutch by Samuel Puffendorff ; translated into English by J.C.</title>
                  <author>Pufendorf, Samuel, Freiherr von, 1632-1694.</author>
                  <author>Chamberlayne, John, 1666-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 205 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Hindmarsh ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation by J. Chamberlayne of an unidentified work possibly written in German.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: John Chamberlayne.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60638:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:60638:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
THE HISTORY OF <hi>Popedom,</hi> Containing the RISE, PROGRESS, AND DECAY Thereof, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written in High <hi>Dutch</hi> BY SAMUEL PUFFENDORFF.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>J. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Hindmarſh,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:60638:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. Alſton.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>October</hi> 2<hi>d.</hi> 1690.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60638:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Reverend Father in God HENRY Lord Biſhop of <hi>LONDON,</hi> Dean of the Chappel Royal, and one of the Lords of His Majeſties moſt Honorable Privy Council.</head>
            <p>This TREATISE is moſt humbly Dedicated
By John Chamberlayne.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:60638:3"/>
            <head>CONTENTS.</head>
            <p>Paragraph 1. <hi>POlitic Reflections on the Spiritual Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of the Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 2. Of the Blindneſs of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens in Matters of Divinity; what they propoſed to themſelves, by chooſing the Paths of Virtue; wherein their Religion conſiſted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 3. Of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion; why other Nations did not embrace the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 4. That the Chriſtian Religion is adapted to the humours of all People; that it admits no Reſpect of Perſons; that it is not contrary to Civil Government; that there is no other ſort of Religion or Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy that can equal it; why many of our Chriſtians live like Heathens.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 5. Of the External Government of Religion; what is here to be underſtood by the External Government of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion; of the Miniſtry of the Church; of the calling of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60638:3"/>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 6. The Diviſion of this Queſtion, that this neceſſity does not proceed from the nature of every Religion in general; how the External Government of Religion was tranſmitted from the Fathers of the Family to the Sovereigns of each State.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 7. That it is not inconſiſtent with the Chriſtian Religion for the Sovereign to have the direction of it as to its Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Government.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 8. The Firſt Progreſs of the Chriſtian Religion; the Divine Conduct in the Eſtabliſhment of this Religion; how the Jeſuits Preach the Goſpel to the <hi>Chineſes;</hi> why God called the Ignorant rather than the Wiſe and Learned Men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 9. The Perſecution of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church; the New Chriſtians Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and Calumniated; the <hi>Romans</hi> upon Reaſons of State oppoſe their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; the <hi>Roman</hi> Perſecution condemn'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 10. Of the Ancient Government of the Chriſtian Religion; Differences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing about Religion Terminated by Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies; why the Authority of theſe Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies ought to be permitted under Heathen Emperours.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60638:4"/>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 11. That the External Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church by being lodged in the hands of the Primitive Christians has produced ſtrange diſorders; that from hence ſome have ſuppoſed two Powers in the State; that Eccleſiaſtics ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their Call from the Sovereign of each State.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 12. That it was not in <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi>'s Power wholly to change the State of the Church; how the Biſhops and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Eccleſiaſtics came to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp the Sovereign Power; that the Sovereign may preſide in the Aſſemblies where Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies are treated of; the abuſe of Councils.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 13. The Juriſdiction of Biſhops abuſed; other Abuſes concerning Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages; Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline abuſed; the Popes miſuſe the Power of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 14. The Riſe of the Popes Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; that Ignorance and the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Age contributed much thereto; the cauſes of this Ignorance; that igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance help'd much to the Eſtabliſhing of the Popedom; the Introduction of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantry into the Schools; that the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques
<pb facs="tcp:60638:4"/>
of the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> were contrary to Monarchy; two dangerous ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the ignorance of Politiques.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 15. Why the Monarch of the Romiſh Church has choſen <hi>Rome</hi> for the place of his Reſidence; how the Pope Eſtabliſh'd his Hierarchy; of the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan Biſhops; how the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp'd the Preheminence; Reflections on the Popes Power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 16. How the Pope came to Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineer o'er all the Weſtern Part of the World; of the Confirmation of Biſhops by the Pope; Deciſions of the Pope; Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations; of the Popes Vicar in <hi>France;</hi> of the Monk <hi>Winifred;</hi> the Pope makes him his Vicar, he advances the Grandeur of the Popes; of the <hi>Annates;</hi> the Popes annul the Deciſions of Provincial Synods; they force the Biſhops to ſwear Fidelity to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 17. The Riches of the Church, and how firſt gotten; the Avarice of the Church-men, and divers effects thereof; the Inſtitution of the Cruſado a ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem of Popes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 18. Of the great number of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtics; the Original of <hi>Monks</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:60638:5"/>
other Religious Orders; of the Multitude of Monaſteries; of the Order of Begging <hi>Friars;</hi> why they choſe that ſort of Life; the Reaſons that induce men now adays to chooſe a Monaſtic Life; that Monks have been very prejudicial to other Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; that they alone hinder the Biſhops from oppoſing the Pope<hi>'s</hi> Authority; that a great many Biſhops would be glad to ſhake off the Yoke of <hi>Rome;</hi> that it is the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of Biſhops to ſubmit to the Pope.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 19. How the Church has ſhaken off all Temporal Juriſdiction; how the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> ſlipt their Neck out of the Emperours Collar.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 20. The Pope implores the <hi>French</hi> Kings Protection againſt the <hi>Lumbards;</hi> the <hi>French</hi> enter <hi>Italy;</hi> they beſtow the Exarchat on the Pope; that the Popes did heretofore hold thoſe Countries under them of the Emperour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 21. The Popes Eſtabliſh an Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Sovereignty; Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> Excommunicates the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth; the Pope endeavours to Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineer o'er the Emperour; a quarrel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King of <hi>England</hi> and his Biſhops; that ſucceeding Emperours have
<pb facs="tcp:60638:5"/>
in vain endeavoured to regain their loſt Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par</hi> 22. The Pope exalts himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all Temporal Powers; the uſe he made of his Excommunicating Power; how the Pope colour'd his uſurpations; the Pope takes upon him the cogniſance of Matrimonial Affairs; that the Pope al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lur'd the moſt knowing Men into his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; the unbounded Ambition of Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eighth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 23. The Popes find their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity oppos'd; that the great Schiſms in the Church have much weakened their Authority; the firſt Schiſm; the ſecond Schiſm; the third Schiſm; the fourth and laſt Schiſm; that the Pope has not been able to Lord it over Councils; the Confeſſion of ſeveral Popes concerning the Authority of Councils; that Popes have been Depos'd by Councils.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 24. The removal of the Popes Seat from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Avignon;</hi> that it was prejudicial to the Pope<hi>'s</hi> Authority; the Pope reduces to his Obedience the City of <hi>Rome;</hi> the Hiſtory of <hi>Caeſar Borgia</hi> natural Son of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Sixth; the Eccleſiaſtical State reunited to the Popedom.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60638:6"/>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 25. That the Papal Authority re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd a terrible blow by the Doctrine of <hi>Luther;</hi> the Virtues and Vices of <hi>Leon</hi> the Tenth; of Indulgences; <hi>Luther</hi> Preaches againſt them, and againſt the Power of the Pope.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 26. That <hi>Luther</hi>'s oppoſition met with a ſeaſonable juncture of the times; the miſerable State of Chriſtendom at that time; the ignorance of <hi>Luther</hi>'s ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries; <hi>Eraſmus</hi> favours <hi>Luther;</hi> that his ſilence alone was very prejudicial to <hi>Luther</hi>'s adverſaries; that the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> were unſatisfied with the Pope; why <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth was willing that <hi>Luther</hi>'s Doctrine ſhould make ſome progreſs; the Popes ill conduct in the Buſineſs of <hi>Luther;</hi> the imprudence of Cardinal <hi>Cajetan,</hi> the effects thereof; <hi>Luther</hi> appeals to a Council.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par</hi> 27. Why <hi>Luther</hi>'s Doctrine did not make greater advances; a Schiſm among the Proteſtants; the Proteſtants abuſe the liberty of the Goſpel; of the Academy of <hi>Paris;</hi> of <hi>Zwinglius</hi> and <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin;</hi> that <hi>Luther</hi> took a great many of the Romiſh Ceremonies; that the riches of the Church have been one cauſe of
<pb facs="tcp:60638:6"/>
the progreſs of Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 28. The Pope recovers from the fright which <hi>Luther</hi> had put him into; that he now acts more cautiouſly than heretofore; that Prieſts and Monks live more regularly at preſent; of the reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of Learning in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> the ways of enticing Proteſtants to that Church; that the Houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria</hi> has mightily contributed to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Grandeur.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 29. Of the Temporal Dominions of the Pope; of the Countries that are under his Juriſdiction; of the Popes Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia; of the Popes Intereſt in relation to <hi>Germany, France,</hi> and <hi>Spain;</hi> that the Pope need not fear the Power of the other States in <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 30. Of the Popes Spiritual Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions; that the Pope has different In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts from thoſe of other Princes; the Foundation of the Papal Monarchy; that the abſolute Power of Popes can't be prov'd from Scripture, nor from the example of the Apoſtles in General, nor from that of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in particular; how the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts Anſwer theſe Objections.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60638:7"/>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 31. Why the Sovereignty of the Roman Church could not well admit of any other Form than a Monarchical; that there could not be invented a more regular Monarchy than that of the Popes; why this Monarchy ought to be Elective; why the Popes don't Marry; of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave; why the Popes are generally <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talians;</hi> why they uſually chuſe an old Man for Pope; why they don't chuſe one of kin to the laſt Pope, nor one that is too much devoted to the <hi>French,</hi> or <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Intereſt; of the Colledg of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals; of the Dignity of Cardinals; of their Number; of their Election; that the Popes always endeavour to enrich their Kindred with the ſpoils of the Church; of the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Patroon;</hi> why the chief Miniſters of the Pope are his Nephews.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 32. Of the Celibacy of the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtics; of their great number; the ſeveral ſorts of Eccleſiaſtics.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 33. That the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> does very well ſquare with the Popes Intereſts; that it prohibits the reading the Holy Scriptures; of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; of Venial and Mortal Sins; of the Remiſſion of Sins; of Works of ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction;
<pb facs="tcp:60638:7"/>
of the merit of good Works; of Works of Superrogation; of Ceremonies and Feaſts; of forbidding the Cup; of the Sacrament of Marriage; of the forbidden Degrees; of extreme <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction; of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory; of the Adoration of Relicks; of the Invocations of Saints and of Canoniſation; other means that the Clergy uſes to drain the Purſes of ignorant People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 34. That <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities have been no ſmall means of ſupporting the Papal Authority; that the Profeſſors were the Popes Creatures; that the Philoſophers were his Slaves; of the Scholaſtic Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity and Philoſophy; that the ſame Pedantry is yet in vogue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 35. Why Jeſuits intrude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the Government of Schools and Colleges; the ſervice they render thereby to the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> that they have inſinuated themſelves into the Courts of Princes; of the Cenſuring Books; that the Romiſh Prieſts inſpire their auditors with an ill opinion againſt Proteſtants; of the falſe rumors they ſpread to their own advantage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 36. That the Excommunication of the Popes is not ſo terrible as it uſed to be.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60638:8"/>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 37. The Reaſons that oblige theſe People to ſtick to the Romiſh Religion; that a great many of them do it for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, others through ignorance; why ſome of them are guilty of Atheiſm; that there is Preferment in the Roman Church for all ſort of People; why the Princes of the Roman Religion do not abandon it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 38. Of thoſe States whoſe Intereſt it is to maintain the Authority of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> of <hi>Italy,</hi> of <hi>Poland,</hi> of <hi>Portugal,</hi> of <hi>Germany;</hi> that <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth neglected the occaſion of making a Reformation in <hi>Germany;</hi> what had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably happened if <hi>Charles</hi> had turned Proteſtant; of <hi>Spain,</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> of the Formalities that the Nuncioes are oblig'd to obſerve in <hi>France;</hi> a project of mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Patriarch</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> that the Pope has an averſion for the <hi>French</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy; of the principal ſupport of the Popes; of their conduct heretofore in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and alſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 39. How the Popes ſtand diſpos'd towards Proteſtants; why they have fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd them upon certain occaſions.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60638:8"/>
               <hi>Par.</hi> 40. If there are any hopes of an accommodation between the Pope and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants; the Reaſons of the Impoſſibility; that ſuch propoſitions are chimerical and dangerous; of the ſtrength of Proteſtants and Catholicks; of the Proteſtant States; Diviſions between the Proteſtants; other inconvenients; of the Jealouſie that reigns between the Proteſtant States; of the <hi>Huguenots</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> of <hi>Poland;</hi> how ſtrong the Proteſtants are in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> if they are able alone to defend themſelves without the aid of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Swedeland;</hi> that the ſecurity of the Proteſtant States does not depend on Treaties of the Sovereign States of the Proteſtant Religion; of the means of maintaining the Proteſtant Religion; whether the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and Reformed may be brought to any accommodation; of the Socinians and Anabaptiſts.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60638:9"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60638:9"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF <hi>Popedom.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1-90" type="pages">
               <p>THE <hi>POPEDOM</hi> may be conſider'd Two ways; Firſt, As it's Doctrine, which is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, and different from that of other Chriſtians, does fall in with the Holy Scripture, and does ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impede or promote the means of our Salvation; the conſideration there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as 'tis taken in this Sence, we leave to the Divines. And Secondly, As the <hi>Pope</hi> does not only make a very conſiderable Figure amongſt the reſt of the <hi>Italian</hi> Princes, but does alſo pretend to the Soveraignty of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom, at leaſt in all Spiritual Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; and does in effect, Exerciſe ſuch
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60638:10"/>
a Supreme Authority over all the States of <hi>Europe,</hi> that have the ſame Sentiments in Religion, with him. 'Tis this ſecond Conſideration, which particularly and immediately belongs to the Politicians, ſince ſuch a ſpiritual Soveraignty does not only bridle the Supreme Power of every State, but is altogether abſurd, and inconſiſtent with the nature of ſuch a Power. Hence is it, That Religion is ſo confounded and intangled with the politick Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of <hi>Rome,</hi> that he who will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the latter, muſt be perfectly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of the Riſe of that ſpiritual Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, and by what means it is Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd to ſo prodigious a Growth, and what Intrigues are uſed to preſerve its uſurped Greatneſs. For thereby, will likewiſe appear, what relation it has with the Controverſies ſo rife at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent among the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Chriſtians; and how far one may attribute thoſe diſagreeing Sentiments of Religion, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to different Interpretations of the Scriptures, or to the proſpect of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Intereſts: After a ſtrict Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of which, we will leave it to the Judgment of Wiſe and Impartial
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60638:10"/>
Men to determine, whether there can be any hopes of a Reconciliation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. If we will aſcend to the firſt cauſes of the thing, we ſhall find that before our Saviour's Birth, the whole World, excepting the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation, was benighted in the darkeſt Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Divine Affairs: For what they did hold forth in general, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Nature of their Gods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> conſiſted moſtly in improbable and impudent Fables. 'Tis true, ſome of the moſt Learned among the Heathens, could Diſcourſe more rationally of the Divinity, and State of the Soul; but it was ſo dubious, imperfect and ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded a Deſcription they made thereof, that they themſelves ſcarce knew what they meant. The moſt of them, were well enough convinced, that they were oblig'd to the Exerciſe and Practice of Virtue, but they knew no farther Effects thereof, than that Advantage and Honour which they enjoy'd thereby in civil Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; for as for what the Poets held forth concerning the Rewards which the juſt, and the Torments which the unjuſt, were to expect after this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60638:11"/>
Life; thoſe that would paſs for the wiſeſt Men, laugh'd at it, eſteeming it nothing more than a witty Fable, and Bug-bears, invented to frighten the unthinking <hi>Mobile,</hi> into their <hi>Devoirs.</hi> The reſt of the People, liv'd, without propoſing to themſelves any other ends, and in that which the Heathens named Religion, there was not to be found any Rules or Formularies, includ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the principal Matters of Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The greateſt part of their Divine Worſhip, conſiſted in Sacrifices, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, and certain Holy-Days, which were more ſpent in Plays, and Debauches, than any inquiry into Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine things; ſo that from ſuch a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Religion, one could neither receive any Edification in this Life, nor any hopes of a future Happineſs in the next.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. In thoſe times, the <hi>Jews</hi> were the only People to whom God vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to reveal the True Religion, and means of Eternal Salvation. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt that and the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the difference is very conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, not only in that the Redeemer of the World, and the Fountain of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60638:11"/>
was repreſented to the <hi>Jews</hi> by Types and Figures, whereas the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion comprehends the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and accompliſhment thereof; but foraſmuch as the Religion of the <hi>Jews</hi> was dreſs'd up with abundance of tedious Ceremonies, whereof the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part had reſpect to the Policy, and natural Inclinations of that People, which were great obſtacles to the growth of their Religion, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd it morally impoſſible to become Univerſal, and ſerve for all the World. 'Tis true, the other Nations were not ſo totally excluded, that through Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, they could not like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be ſaved; to which end, there were among the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſome godly and zealous men, that made it their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to convert the Heathens, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, thoſe with whom they had to do; but it did not yet pleaſe the All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe God to ſend out his Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors or Apoſtles, honour'd with eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial and extraordinary Gifts over all the Earth, to turn all Nations to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Faith; and the pains that ſome particulars took in the Converſion of the Infidels, could not produce any
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60638:12"/>
great effects, in relation to the whole World. And foraſmuch as the <hi>Jews</hi> in thoſe times, being the Select People of God, had the advantage above all others, and that the only Temple of the True God was amongſt them, they valu'd themſelves highly therefore, and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all the reſt of the World in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon with themſelves. Beſides, They were oblig'd, upon the Account of their Ceremonies, to abſtain from a too free and familiar Converſation with other Nations, which produc'd an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable and reciprocal hate betwixt them; ſo that they were ſet againſt all the World, and all the World againſt them; and conſequently, deſtroy'd all hopes of the propagation of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: Again, the Heathens could not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be perſwaded, that when they would Solemnly pay their Adorations to God Almighty, they muſt make a long Journey to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as if they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves could not build a Temple in their own Country, which ſhould enjoy the ſame privilege, as that of the <hi>Jews.</hi> To which prejudice we may add, that thoſe who were converted to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion, were not ſo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60638:12"/>
much eſteem'd as the Natives of the Country, ſo that a very few could reſolve for Religion's ſake, to expoſe themſelves to that contempt, which is uſually the fate of ſtrangers to endure.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. But the Chriſtian Religion has not only a much purer and clearer Light, and other Advantages above the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> which we leave to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Divines; but it is alſo free'd from thoſe ſtreightning Circumſtances, which render'd the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion ſo particular, and it has all the Qualities that are requiſite to the compoſition of an Univerſal Religion, upon which Account, all men are oblig'd to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the ſame, which ought eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be obſerved by one that will enquire into the Nature and Genius of the Chriſtian Religion; for in this, God has not ſet apart any particular Land or Country, where he will more peculiarly be Ador'd, nor endu'd any with a privileg'd Holineſs above the reſt; ſo that, the inconvenience and great diſtance of God's Temple, can now no longer be a pretext to this or that People; for in all Nations, the offering of an humble and contrite
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60638:13"/>
heart, is equally agreeable to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Saviour of the whole World; nor is there any one Temple, where God is more preſent, or our Prayers ſooner accepted, than in another. No Nation profeſſing the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion has ſuch Advantages above the reſt, whereupon to value its ſelf, and undervalue its Neighbour. There is no diſtinction of Jew or Greek, Bondman, or Free, but we are all in Jeſus Chriſt; there is no particular Race or Family ſelected by God for the performing Divine Service, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Jews;</hi> but all other abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties concurring, one has as much right thereto, as another. There is nothing in the Chriſtian Religion that hinders us from maintaining a good Union and Correſpondence with all men, or to render one another thoſe mutual good Offices which the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture requires from us. The Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion ſimply conſider'd, and in its natural Purity, diſpoil'd of all Worldly views and intereſts, has not the leaſt jarring or diſcord with the Laws and Civil Society, in as much as they agree with the Dictates of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60638:13"/>
right Reaſon, but rather contributes much to the cementing and corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating of the ſame, tho' that is not its principal end or deſign. There is nothing that does claſh with the ends of Civil Government, or that ſhould hinder us from living honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, quietly and ſecurely under the Protection of our Rulers; ſo that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Chriſtian may yield an exact and perfect obedience to every com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Secular Power, as long as ſuch commands do not recede from the Law of Nature, right Reaſon, and the Neceſſities of the State; as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, he may fill every charge and employ, that is neceſſary in a well govern'd Common-wealth: On the contrary, the Chriſtian Religion is moſt fit thereto, for it does require in us, a ſtrict obſervation of all the Precepts of the Law of Nature, and eſpecially, thoſe the breach whereof is not obnoxious to the puniſhment of any Civil Laws, and does recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to every one, the performance of his charge, as far as it concurs with the Laws of Nature and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, with the greateſt Zeal and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60638:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60638:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:60638:15"/>
imaginable; ſo that there is no ſort of Philoſophy in the World, nor any other Religion whatſoever, that can compare with the Chriſtian in thoſe points; as may be ſeen at firſt ſight, by any one that will take the pains to make a parallel of them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; ſo that, it is not only the obligation of every particular man, in as much as he is one day to give an account to God for his Soul, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Chriſtian Religion; but all thoſe whom God has entruſted with the Supreme Power, are particularly bound, for reaſons before mentioned, to introduce and maintain it in their States, and that by an obligation, which does neceſſarily follow the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Office. Now tho' theſe effects are not every where equally viſible among Chriſtians, and that there are found ſome, who lead as irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and diſorderly lives, as the worſt of Turks and Infidels; the blame is not to be laid upon the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but is to be imputed to the malice and perverſeneſs of mankind, who only hide their impiety under that Sacred Veil, and do little trouble
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60638:15"/>
themſelves to put in practice the moſt excellent Leſſons, which the beſtof Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions does continually ſuggeſt to 'em.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. But as all theſe things can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be doubted of by the more Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſort of Men, ſo there occurs here a very conſiderable queſtion, namely, Whether the Chriſtian Religion does indiſpenſibly require, that the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Direction of it, ſhould depend of any other than thoſe who have the Supreme Power and Adminiſtration of Affairs in every State? Or, (which is the ſame in effect) Whether the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Government thereof, ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide conjointly in the Prieſts and Clergy, or in any one of them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any dependance on the Supreme Secular Powers? Or elſe, Whether there muſt be but one Soveraign Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of the Chriſtian Religion, whom all other Chriſtian States ſhall blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obey? All which Quaeries, as ſome think, do finally terminate in this: Whether each State ought to regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late its ſelf according to its own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and Advantage? Or, Whether all other States ought to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Slaves to one, and ſeek to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it great and flouriſhing by their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60638:16"/>
own Loſs and Deſtruction?</p>
               <p>By the external Government, or Direction of the Chriſtian Religion, we underſtand ſuch a Power which exerts it ſelf in the choice it makes of certain Perſons to be employ'd in the publick exerciſe of Divine Service, reſerving to its ſelf the Juriſdiction, and free Liberty of enquiring into the Carriage and Demeanour of thoſe Perſons: The Adminiſtration and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſal of all ſuch Goods as ſhall be Conſecrated to Religion and Pious Uſes; by Enacting ſuch Laws as ſhall be thought neceſſary for the Support and Maintaining of Religion, in deciding all Differences and Diſputes that upon any occaſion may ariſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Clergy, and other things of the like nature.</p>
               <p>And we diſtinguiſh this external Direction from the Miniſter of the Church, which conſiſts in Teaching, Preaching and Adminiſtring the Holy Sacraments, which beyond all diſpute does alone belong to the Clergy: but this queſtion is to be underſtood, <hi>de Eccleſia jam plantata, &amp; constituta, non de adhuc conſtituenda &amp; plantanda,</hi> of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60638:16"/>
the Church which is already Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, and not of that which is yet to be founded. For the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Doctrine, originally proceeding from the Divine Revelation, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt, no Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Power can be admitted to the Direction thereof, before that it be manifeſted and laid open by thoſe that are immediately Authoriz'd by God for that purpoſe. So likewiſe, when our Saviour after his Reſurrection, ſent out his Diſciples as his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Embaſſadors over all the World, to promulge, and introduce the Doctrine of the Holy Goſpel, they did not receive this Commiſſion and Plenipotential right of Preaching here and there from the Supreme Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, but from God alone; to which therefore the King was as much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to ſubmit, as the meaneſt of his Subjects, they being the immediate Meſſengers of God, and to receive their Doctrine with all humility and obedience: Beſides, it would be very unreaſonable and ridiculous to aſpire to the Direction of Affairs, whereof they had not the leaſt Cognizance.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:60638:17"/>
From whence it does alſo neceſſarily follow, that this queſtion is to be underſtood of thoſe Supreme Powers, which themſelves do profeſs the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, and not of Infidels or Hereticks for to commit the Care and Direction of our Religion to ſuch, were to ſet the Wolf to keep the Sheep.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. This queſtion may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd three ſeveral ways. 1. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch a Neceſſity does ariſe from the Nature of each Religion in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral? Or, 2. Whether it be a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Effect of the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? And Laſtly, Whether it is grounded on any poſitive Command and Order of God? That ſuch ſhould proceed from the common and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Nature of every Religion we can in no wiſe perceive. Nor can a ſenſible man be eaſily brought to believe, That to ſerve God rightly, he muſt of neceſſity, make a Schiſm in the State, and introduce two jar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Powers independant of each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Such a Diviſion or Compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Soveraign Power in the ſame Republick, is the ready means
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60638:17"/>
of fomenting an unquenchable Fire of Diſtruſts, Fears, and internal Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies; whereas on the contrary, there is no abſurdity or contradiction in ſerving God, and committing the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Direction of Divine Service to the Soveraign Powers, with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction that the Soveraign will not undertake to impoſe any Falſe or He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical Opinions on us.</p>
               <p>In like manner, as every one is naturally oblig'd to ſerve God, ſo he likewiſe has the Power of Inſtituting ſuch external Signs of his Adoration, as he is perſwaded to be moſt pleaſing and agreeable to God. But ſo ſoon as Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind ſet themſelves to the forming and compoſing of civil Societies, they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon'd all their right and power to thoſe to whom belong the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and management of the whole So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety.</p>
               <p>The ancient <hi>Patres-Familias</hi> or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Family, before the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of any Republick, have this right ſolely ſeated in themſelves, and which from them was wont to deſcend to the firſt born of the Family, as <hi>Haereditas Eximia,</hi> the more Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60638:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60638:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:60638:19"/>
and Eminent Part of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance: But ſo ſoon as men with one common accord, united themſelves into civil Societies and Common-weals, this Power was transferr'd from the Head of each Family, to the Head of the Republick; and this was done upon very weighty reaſons, for if it had been left to every mans fancy and pleaſure, what ſort of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies he would obſerve in the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Adoration of God, the ſtrange and contrary varieties of ſerving God, would have produc'd nothing but Hate, Contempt, and irreconcileable Diſſentions amongſt the Subjects of the ſame State. And altho' among Gods People, the <hi>Jews,</hi> the publick Adminiſtration of Divine Service, was become hereditary, and tied to one certain Family; yet the Soveraign inſpection and care of the Prieſts, did only belong to them who had the Soveraign Authority in the Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. The ſame thing has like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe been obſerv'd by almoſt all the other Nations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. Nor can we perceive, that ſuch a Direction muſt neceſſarily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60638:19"/>
to any other than the Soveraign of each State, or the neceſſity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be prov'd from any Identity or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular quality of the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion as far as it does comprehend in its ſelf ſomething more than is ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted to us by the Light of Nature, concerning the Divine Worſhip: Whileſt we always take it for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That the Soveraign, by Virtue of that external Direction, neither can, nor will introduce any thing contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to God's Holy Word, nor hinder the Miniſters from the performance of their Office, according to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Precepts.</p>
               <p>Beſides, There can no reaſon be given, why the Supreme Powers ſhould be incapable of ever attaining thoſe Qualifications which are requir'd to this external Care and Direction of the Church; or at leaſt, that they ſhould not be able to commit this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to ſome of their Subjects, that are beyond exception qualifi'd for ſuch an employ: After the ſame manner as other parts of the Soveraignty are often Adminiſtred by the Subjects. So no body preſumes to deprive the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60638:20"/>
Soveraign of his Legiſlative Faculty, or pretends a better Right, tho' 'tis certain, that every Doctor and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of Law, ought to be infinitely better vers'd therein, than any King can be; who, as in all other Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Affairs, ought alſo herein, to make uſe of their Counſel, and profit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of the Fruits of their long Study and Experience. For a Brave and Wiſe King, far from making it his Intereſt, that his Subjects ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit themſelves ill of thoſe Offices he has entruſted 'em with, may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (conformably to his Duty) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract incredible Advantages from the good and faithful management of what he has committed to them. For the more Diligent and Zealous he is in the Maintenance and Support of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, the more capable his Subjects are of ſerving him, and the more aſſur'd is he of God's Help and Aſſiſtance. Beſides, <hi>caeteris paribus,</hi> 'tis impoſſible to give any Reaſon, why God Almighty ſhould not grant his Grace and Aſſiſtance to an Orthodox Chriſtian King, as well as to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the good and laudable Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60638:20"/>
of ſuch a Direction. Laſtly, Whileſt the Chriſtian Religion in no other point does encroach upon the Civil Laws and Ordinances, ſo far as they fall in with the Law of Nature, we ought not to believe, that it breaks its bounds in this, unleſs we had a formal and poſitive aſſurance thereof, from God himſelf. Thoſe therefore that will perſiſt in the Defence of ſuch an Abſurdity, are oblig'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, where the Holy Scripture in expreſs Terms, deprives the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Civil Magiſtrate of this Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to beſtow it on another inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, and not acknowledging any Earthly Superiour. In the mean while, we will proceed to examine, how, and by what ſteps, ſuch a Spiritual Soveraignty, has attain'd to ſo mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous a Degree in the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. When the Apoſtles, after our Saviour's Aſcention, had begun to Preach the Holy Goſpel to all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, being appointed thereto, by their Maſter's immediate Commands; they did, in a ſhort time, gain an incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble number of Proſelytes, as well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60638:21"/>
the Jews as Gentiles, and eſpecially of the common People, then oppreſs'd with a miſerable Ignorance, and leading a wretched and beaſtly Life. They therefore embraced this Doctrine with a great deal of Joy, wherein they found unſpeakable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts againſt the inconveniences, and deſperate Sorrows of this temporary Life.</p>
               <p>Beſides, The Apoſtles being them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of low Birth, and as to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance, making a very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable figure, found an eaſier Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and could better inſinuate their Opinions into the minds of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals. Whereas the great Men, and the moſt Learn'd, ſlighted this up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart Religion in the beginning, nor thought it worth their while to make any exact inquiry into the Myſteries thereof.</p>
               <p>If men may preſume to examine the Reaſons of the Divine Wiſdom, and why it was pleas'd to make uſe of ſuch means in the firſt Introduction of the Chriſtian Religion; the moſt probable ſeems to be, that God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore to make uſe of Power, or the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60638:21"/>
Authority of the Supreme Magiſtrate, leſt the Purity of the Goſpel might be miſtaken for a Politick Device, or a Philoſophical Speculation. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if a man compares the inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble beginning with the wonderful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, he will eaſily obſerve, that there is ſomething more than Humane in it; eſpecially, conſidering that the moſt Learned among the Heathens, with all their Subtilties, with all their Helps of Art and Nature, could but ſlightly and ſuperficially penetrate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Reaſon and Cauſes of Divine Things; and that the Great <hi>Socrates</hi> amongſt the reſt, tho' he clearly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd the blind Superſtition and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his Age, yet had not Power enough to introduce a better; but as a Reward for his good Deſign, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd Death as an Heretick and Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator of the Eſtabliſh'd Religion: Whereby we are given to underſtand, That the Wiſdom of the World is but Folly with God, who could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect a work, by the means of poor ignorant <hi>Fiſhermen,</hi> which all the united Wits of the greateſt Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, were not able to ſet on foot.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60638:22"/>
Beſides, The Apoſtles manner of act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſeem'd very odd to the more ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional ſort of People; they thought it ſtrange to hear a Crucified Jeſus, the greateſt Subject of their Sermons; and that they ſhould name him the Son of God, and Saviour of the World, who was born among a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple derided and deſpiſed as the ſcum of the Earth, and the abject of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; nor was this Jeſus in any great Repute in the World, nor had he ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naliz'd himſelf by any Famous He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roical Actions; or by a great many Years Preaching and Teaching, ſpread his Name abroad among the People; but on the contrary, was cut off in the Flower of his Age, by a moſt ſcandalous and ſhameful Death.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of planting the Goſpel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the cunning <hi>Chineſes,</hi> do not begin it from the Paſſions of Chriſt, but do firſt Reaſon and Diſcourſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Natural Religion, and then after a long round about, fall upon the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, which whether they can by theſe devices and politick Methods, better inſinuate into
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60638:22"/>
thoſe unbelievers, than the Apoſtles, I ſhall not now examine. One may alſo add, That it ſeem'd good to God, to deliver firſt the moſt ſimple, and the meaneſt of the People out of that Heatheniſh Blindneſs, ſince they were maintain'd and kept under in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Superſtition by the great ones, who, tho' they eaſily perceiv'd the cheat and vanity of Paganiſm, yet, with-held by their Intereſt and World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Conſiderations, did not think it worth while to ſeek after a better. Thus God by his withdrawing the <hi>Mobile</hi> from their Heatheniſh man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſerving him looſned the very Foundations of this Grand Machine, and thereby deſtroy'd the Form and Superſtructure thereof. For the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and Credulity of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People was the great Baſis by which Paganiſm was alone ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 9. After that, the Chriſtian Religion was communicated firſt to the common People, as we have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhew'd; the greateſt Oppoſition it met withal, was from the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors, for as in their Dominions,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60638:23"/>
it had taken the deepeſt Root, and made the greateſt Progreſs, ſo was it there moſt cruelly Perſecuted and Oppreſſed; to which did not a little Contribute their Ignorance of this New Religion, what its Principles, and what its Deſign was; to which Cauſe we may add the great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Proſelytes daily gain'd by the Publiſhers of the Goſpel, who all of 'em, openly contemn'd the Heatheniſh Rites and Ceremonies. Beſides, The Emperors thought it much below 'em, and a derogation from their Dignities, to enter into a more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular examination of this Doctrine. The firſt Chriſtians alſo, being for the moſt part, very unlearn'd, were not able to reduce their Religion into any Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod or Form, wherein to preſent it to thoſe that were in Authority, which was the occaſion that the moſt malicious Lyes and Calumnies of their Enemies were taken up for great Truths, even, by thoſe that caſt an indifferent Eye on that Religion. They were accus'd of practiſing all ſorts of Debauchery and Immodeſty, in their ſecret Nocturnal Aſſemblies;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60638:23"/>
nay, they did not ſtick to traduce them of holding private Cabals and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies againſt the State. There were a great many, that had an Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for all Innovations, whoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument was, That ſince the <hi>Roman</hi> Common-wealth had ſo bravely ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted with its Old Religion for ſo many Hundred Years, Why could it not make the ſame ſhift ſtill? And 'twas particularly, againſt all Rules of Policy, to ſuffer the <hi>Mobile,</hi> to begin ſo great a Revolution, as if they were wiſer than their Lords and Rulers: And that which lookt moſt ſuſpicious, was, That the Chriſtians had conſtituted among themſelves, a ſort of Eccleſiaſtical Government, which they conſider'd as a Schiſm or Faction; as if the Chriſtians had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to erect a New Common-wealth, upon the ruins of the Old one, and by dividing the Forces of the Empire, at laſt, make themſelves Maſters of the whole. Laſtly, Whileſt the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Temples began to be leſs fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented, proportionably as the number of the Chriſtians increaſed, and that in the mean time, the Grandeur of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60638:24"/>
                  <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, was ſenſibly decay'd, and weaken'd by the cruel ſhocks it had receiv'd from the <hi>Germans, Farthians,</hi> &amp;c. a great many of the People poſſeſs'd with Bigottry and Superſtition, could attribute it to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but the contempt and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect of their Gods, by whoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable Aſſiſtance, <hi>Rome</hi> had ſeen its ſelf Miſtreſs of the World. They fell therefore upon the Chriſtians, as wicked Atheiſtical Men, and ſworn Enemies to all Religions; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they refus'd to obey the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors Commands concerning the Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Images, and underwent all the Torments inflicted on them, and Death it ſelf, with an amazing Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity and Sedateneſs of mind; they interpreted that, as a malicious ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borneſs, and hardneſs of heart, and therefore raged more Tyrannically againſt them, endeavouring by all ſorts of Cruelties to maintain their Authority over theſe wretched Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: But what Reaſons ſoever can be alledg'd in Juſtification of thoſe bloody Perſecutions exercis'd againſt the Chriſtians by ſeveral <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60638:24"/>
none can be ſufficient to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them from the Title of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Tyrants, and ſhameful Abuſers of that High Power, which God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty has entruſted them with. For their Subjects had embraced this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by the expreſs Commands of God, which can neither be withſtood or ſuſpended by the Orders of any Earthly Soveraign, ſince the Soveraigns as well as their Subjects, are oblig'd to embrace this Religion; the omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion whereof, is an high Sin againſt the Divine Majeſty. Beſides, They could not excuſe themſelves with the pretext of Ignorance; for ſince it was a New Religion, they were oblig'd with greater Care and Exactneſs to inform themſelves of the Nature thereof, and not ſo blindly to ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence poor innocent People, for not obeying thoſe commands which were not in the leaſt Obligatory. For I ought not to condemn any one to Death, before I am fully inform'd of the Crimes, whereof he ſtands accuſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 10. But ſince the Chriſtian Religion did not owe its beginning to the Conſent and Authority of the Soveraign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Profeſſors thereof,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60638:25"/>
found themſelves oblig'd on their own Heads, to eſtabliſh their Religion and its external Adminiſtration after the beſt manner they could; as it uſually happens in all Societies, that are founded in any State without the knowledge or permiſſion of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Magiſtrate, where the Members of the ſame are neceſſitated to find out all the means that can beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the advantage of their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, by chuſing ſuch Officers, and making ſuch Laws as are requiſite to attain the ends they propoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. 'Tis true, according to the Rules of the beſt Policy, founded upon the Law of Nature, the Adminiſtration and External Direction of Divine Worſhip, (as we had often repeated before) does belong to the Soveraign; but ſince he then neglected to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form that Function, the Primitive Chriſtians were forc'd to conſtitute Church-Miniſters, and to maintain them by the Alms of charitable Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And when any Difference or Controverſy aroſe amongſt them, which could not be determined by one Aſſembly alone, they imparted it to another Aſſembly, with which they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60638:25"/>
kept Correſpondence, or elſe it was decided in a Convocation of the Neighbouring Miniſters. Now altho' it be againſt the Rules of Policy of all States, to permit the erecting of Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhips (eſpecially ſuch as conſiſt of any conſiderable Number of Perſons) to Subjects and Particulars; yet it does not follow from thence, that the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of the ancient Chriſtians and their Synods, were to be Interpreted ſeditious and unlawful Conventicles, ſince they had no other proſpect, than the free Exerciſe of that Religion which God had imparted to 'em, and againſt which, no humane Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were of any Efficacy. For if the Soveraign, does neglect his Duty and Care of his own Salvation, it is not neceſſary that his Subjects ſhould imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him, and reject the great Benefit that Heaven does offer to 'em; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, it is not accepted by their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, nor can his Authority extend ſo far as to oblige them thereto. And as each particular may take up Arms, and defend himſelf, when the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign either cannot, or will not afford him his Aſſiſtance and Protection; ſo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60638:26"/>
if he will not take care for my Soul, I am ſo much the more oblig'd to watch over it my ſelf, as the Soul is of greater Conſequence and Value than the Body; and that another is leſs prejudiced by my Religion, than by a violent, tho' ſelf-Defence; ſince no man by ſubmitting himſelf to any Civil Government, does renounce the Care of his Body and Soul. For other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if it had pleas'd God to have begun the propagation of his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Converſion of Kings and Emperors; without doubt, they would have ſeconded by their Edicts the Preaching of the Apoſtles, aboliſh'd the Temples of their Heatheniſh Gods, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited the Exerciſe of Paganiſm; and by the Apoſtles Advice, they would have aſſum'd and manag'd the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Direction of Religious Affairs, and forever afterward, have reſerv'd it in their own hands; as we find it put in practice in ſome Countries where the Chriſtian Religion was firſt embraced by the Princes thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 11. In the mean while, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Government and Diſpoſition of Holy Things, by the negligence
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60638:26"/>
of the Civil Magiſtrate, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd upon the Primitive Chriſtians, was found too late, to be of a very dangerous Conſequence; for from hence, ſome have pretended to infer, that the Election of fit Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and the Management of Church-Affairs, does naturally and originally belong to the common People, as they are underſtood in oppoſition to their Soveraign or Rulers. 'Tis true, one ought not to force upon the vulgar, a Miniſter whom they extreamly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, eſpecially, if they have any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable reaſon of their averſion againſt him; for ſuch a man, with all the Preaching in the World, can never Edify his unwilling Auditors; yet it does not follow from hence, that the <hi>Mob</hi> have any original right thereto, becauſe they once enjoy'd it by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, whileſt the Soveraign omitted the performance of his Duty and Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction herein: For otherwiſe, it would have been as little in their Power, to call and appoint Miniſters in their Churches, as it ever was to diſpoſe of Civil Offices and Employs in the State. Therefore, if it happens, that in this
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60638:27"/>
Country or another, the common Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have any Right or Privilege there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, 'tis to be underſtood, that they enjoy it by the permiſſion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivence of their Soveraign, whom we preſuppoſe to be an Orthodox Chriſtian. There are ſome alſo, who would from hence conclude, That the external Government of the Church, muſt neceſſarily be conſider'd as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſeparate and diſtinct from the Supreme Civil Government, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought to be Soveraignly Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred by the united Body of the Clergy, or by ſome one choſe from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them; and that ſo in every Chriſtian State, there muſt needs be two Different and Independent Bodies, of which, one was be named, the <hi>Body Politick,</hi> and t'other the <hi>Body Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick,</hi> and both Soveraign and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent of each other. But this is abſolutely falſe, and it is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that that Power and Authority, which was proviſionally uſurp'd by the People, when that negligence of the Prince, by which it was forfeited, ceaſes, does juſtly devolve again upon the lawful Soveraign; nor does it
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60638:27"/>
follow that the Power which the Apoſtles had in the eſtabliſhing the Church, can be challeng'd by the Miniſters of the Church now eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; for the Apoſtolary Function was ſomething particular, and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the ordinary Church-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, as this is from the external Direction of the Church, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as one that is choſen for a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, is not ſtrait an Apoſtle; ſo neither does a King in aſſuming the Government and Protection of the Church, immediately become a Prieſt thereof.</p>
               <p>Now, tho' the Chriſtian Religion is originally Divine, and therefore not to be comprehended by weak, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Intellects; yet that does not hinder the King, or whoſoever is Supreme, from the Direction and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration thereof, provided, that he make uſe of the Counſel and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of thoſe men who are beſt vers'd in ſuch Affairs. From what has been now ſaid, we may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe draw this concluſion, that we are not oblig'd preciſely to follow the Praxis of the Primitive Churches,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60638:28"/>
in relation to the external Direction of the Church, or to obſerve it as a general Rule for Church-Government in thoſe States where the Soveraign is an Orthodox Chriſtian. For that Praxis is wholly founded on the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of thoſe times, which can have no place in thoſe States where both the Supreme Magiſtrates and the Common People, are united in one Faith; Why therefore ſhould we make a Schiſm in the State, when there is none in the Religion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 12. Now, tho' by the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, to the Chriſtian Religion, the Church aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd a New Form; for as much as the Soveraign was then capable of Adminiſtring the Function of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Governour of the Church, yet this could not be done ſo eaſily or commodiouſly, as if the Soveraign had always from the beginning been Head of the Chriſtian Church, but there remain'd ſo many Relicks of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Proviſional-Government, that they afterwards occaſion'd innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable errours and abuſes in the <hi>Weſtern</hi> or <hi>Latin</hi> Churches. Beſides, the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60638:28"/>
could not be brought to conſent, that the Emperours, whom they as then, look'd upon to be meer Novi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Matters of Religion, ſhould immediately acquire the Supreme Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Eccleſiaſtick Affairs, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the Biſhops and Clergy, who could not ſee themſelves, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a great deal of unwillingneſs and regret, diſpoil'd of ſo conſiderable an Authority: Whereas the Emperours on the contrary (their Subjects be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſtly Chriſtians) were forced to depend on their Prieſts, and careſs them continually, if they deſir'd to have their Throne ſettled, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſecure from falling. To which Reaſon we may add, That the firſt Chriſtian Emperours having as yet in their Service a great many Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Officers, it was not reaſonable that the Government of the Church, and the Affairs thereof ſhould be taken into conſideration, or deliberated of, in the Imperial Councils, where Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans were always preſent. From thence it came, that in the Inſtitution of Biſhops and other Eccleſiaſticks, the cuſtoms and manners introduced
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60638:29"/>
in the times of the Heathen Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours were generally obſerv'd, and that not only the deciſion of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies in Matters of Faith, but alſo all Laws ſerving to the external Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and Government of the Church; as alſo all other Differences ariſing amongſt the Chiefeſt of the Clergy were deliberated of in Synods and General Aſſemblies, where the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates pretended that they alone had right to Preſide and give their Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages. Whereas the right of calling Synods or other Aſſemblies together, was the Prerogative of Soveraigns alone, and in all other times did indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputably belong to them; beſides that, that it was but reaſonable that they ſhould preſide and have the Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſuch Aſſemblies, let the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be what it would that was there Treated of, where their Conſent was abſolutely neceſſary to the ratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and paſſing into a Law of what was there determined. 'Tis true, in thoſe Conventions, neither the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, nor the whole Body of the Clergy have any Power or Right to form new Articles of our Belief, or
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60638:29"/>
to interpret the Scriptures after their own Fancy; but ſince the whole Duty of a Chriſtian, what he ought to do, and what he ought to believe, is contain'd in the Holy Bible, which God has equally given to all men, and not as the Oracles of the <hi>Sybils,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted only to the Care of the Prieſts, and that all other men, as well as the Eccleſiaſticks, can underſtand as much thereof, as is neceſſary for Salvation; it does not therefore in the leaſt, ſeem unreaſonable, that the Soveraign ſhould preſide in all ſuch Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions where they debate and diſpute about the apparent Contradictions and different Interpretations of the Holy Scriptures, where the Preſence and Authority of the Prince, might ſerve to moderate thoſe Heats and Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which uſually ariſe from diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Opinions in things of that nature, where he might hinder all Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Reflections upon Perſons, ſpightful and malicious Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Words, and finally awe them from pronouncing <hi>Anathema</hi>'s without a very juſt reaſon againſt innocent and well meaning Perſons.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60638:30"/>
But whileſt the firſt Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors neglected this their right, or could not conveniently maintain it, from hence it came, that things were very confuſedly deliberated of, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by Councils; and that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Popes uſurping a Power above all the other <hi>Weſtern</hi> Biſhops; and Councils themſelves pretended a right of determining in all Matters of Faith, and of introducing Canons or Eccleſiaſtical Laws wherein their own Profit and Advantage was their chiefeſt proſpect, and have at laſt aſſum'd the Supreme Juriſdiction in all Spiritual Matters, and thereby have withdrawn themſelves from that obedience which they ow'd to their lawful Soveraigns the <hi>Roman</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 13. Beſides, It was the Cuſtom in the ancient Churches, that the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians, according to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> would very rarely plead their cauſes before the Gentile Tribunals; but when any Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy aroſe amongſt them, they referr'd it to the deciſion of the Biſhop, leaſt the Heathens ſhould be ſcandaliz'd
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60638:30"/>
thereat, and take occaſion to revile the Name of Chriſt. Beſides, it would have a very ill grace to ſee them ſo greedily plead for temporal things which they pretended ſo much to ſlight and contemn. Now this in it ſelf, and at that time was a very laudable and uſeful deſign; but at laſt, whileſt the Chriſtian Emperors, far from abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing this Cuſtom, confirm'd it more and more, and the Tribunals were fill'd with Chriſtian Judges, the Biſhops uſurp'd a formal Juriſdiction, which did not alone encroach upon the rights of the Civil Magiſtrates, but did alſo diſtract the Biſhops themſelves from the exerciſe of that Charge, which did peculiarly belong to them.</p>
               <p>'Twas likewiſe the Cuſtom of the Primitive Chriſtians, when in their Marriages any ſcruple aroſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Proximity or nearneſs of Blood, to refer themſelves to the Prieſt, and acquieſce in his Sentiments, who alſo in all quarrels between Man and Wife, interpos'd his Authority, to which we may add his Aſſiſting always in the Celebration of Marriages, with his Prayers and Bleſſings; from all which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60638:31"/>
Cuſtoms (tho' as we ſaid before, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally innocent and good in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) very pernicious Errors and Abuſes have been deriv'd, ſince the Pope has from hence taken occaſion to draw all Affairs of Matrimony, which occur, <hi>circa ſtatum hominum, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vortia, nullitates Matrimoniorum, Suceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiones, Haereditates,</hi> and all others of the like Importance into his <hi>Forum</hi> or Tribunal, and to colour his abuſes the better, he has made a New Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Matrimony.</p>
               <p>The Primitive Chriſtians by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence and Holineſs of their Lives, endeavour'd to ſtir up a deſire in the Heathens of embracing ſo laudable a Religion, and therefore they very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely puniſhed thoſe Calumnies and Slanders which the Civil Laws of the Gentiles did not reach; ſo that in their Churches when any, by a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ill Life, had given Scandal and a bad Example to the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, there was ſome publick Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Pennance or other enjoin'd him, which never exceeded a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral or total Excluſion from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation; which Cuſtom, could not but be very profitable in the preſent
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60638:31"/>
Chriſtian States, provided that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection thereof reſided wholly in the Soveraign's hands, whoſe Duty it would be to prevent that ſuch Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures be not the effects of malice, private paſſions, and ſelf-intereſts; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when ſuch Cenſures operate ſo effectually <hi>in foro &amp; vita civ. li,</hi> as in the Eighth Century, when no man would converſe with an excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated Perſon. Now the Soveraign Exerciſe of ſuch a Power, can rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably belong to none but the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magiſtrate in every State, without making a diviſion in the Government. But how the Popes in following times have abus'd, and how far they have extended theſe Cenſures, is plainly enough laid open by all Hiſtorians; when they neither ſpar'd Emperors, Kings or Common-wealths that refus'd to Dance after their Pipes, but in excommunicating them, they forbid them to aſſiſt at Divine Service, diſpens'd their Subjects of their due Allegiance, gave away their Kingdoms to others, and finally, oblig'd them to conſent to the moſt diſadvantageous and unreaſonable things in the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60638:32"/>
In the mean while, theſe Abuſes have not ſpread themſelves ſo wide in the <hi>Eastern</hi> Churches, whileſt the Emperours of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> did at leaſt keep up their Authority ſo far, that the Clergy there durſt never incroach upon it, nor had any of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Biſhops that opportunity of lifting himſelf above his Colleagues, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming the Title of Head of the Church; for the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> himſelf had only the firſt place, and privilege of preceding all thoſe that were not of his Dioceſs, but had no Juriſdiction over them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 14. But in the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the different circumſtances of things altered quite the Scene, whileſt the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> had projected and begun to exerciſe a peculiar ſort of Government and Supremacy, and which at the laſt they have brought to its higheſt point and perfection: A Soveraignty that in all the World cannot finds its parallel, being built upon quite different Foundations, and maintained by ways extreamly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing from the policy of all other States: Therefore after having made
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60638:32"/>
an exact enquiry into its riſe and conſtitution, we will lay open its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues, and deſcribe the influences it has had, the Power it has uſurp'd and maintain'd for ſo many Ages in all the Affairs of <hi>Europe,</hi> and with what zeal and fierceneſs this up ſtart So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty has been attacked by ſome, and defended by others; to which, we will add the reaſons of that cruel blow was given to it in the laſt Age, and how it has recover'd its almoſt loſt credit in this Age, and is like to keep up it ſelf in a very good poſture.</p>
               <p>From which, the Wiſe may judge what hopes there remain of any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation or union of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants with the Papiſts. One of the Cauſes (tho' ſomething remote) which has not a little contributed to the monſtrous growth of a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſo pernicious to all the other So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigns of <hi>Europe,</hi> was the Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Ignorance of Sciences, after the decay of the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Empire; for counterfeit Wares are beſt ſold and put off by dim, weak Lights, and an ignorant man is eaſier impos'd on with bagatelles and improbabilities,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60638:33"/>
than one that has a better inſight in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the nature of things, and a freer exerciſe of his Reaſon. This igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance accompanied afterwards with ſo inſupportable a Pedantry (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the preceding Age was more Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) was promoted by different Cauſes: One of the Chiefeſt whereof, was the Invaſion of a no leſs Warlike, than ignorant People, in the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Provinces of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, which for ſome Ages during an unſetled and inconſtant Government, felt nothing but cruel Wars, terrible Diſorders, ſpoiling, ravaging and laying waſte of whole Countries; and in a Word, all the miſeries that are the neceſſary conſequences of a Barbarous Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Whereas the <hi>Muſes</hi> and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral Sciences</hi> are the Daughters of Peace and Proſperity; but in the Hurly-burlies and Tumults of War, Books are a dead Ware, and ſhall lie long enough on the hands of thoſe that have 'em; Schools and Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are then like Wilderneſſes, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quite empty, or haunted by none but wild Beaſts; and the Gentlemen of the long Robe, will rather chuſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60638:33"/>
to ſhoulder a Muſquet, than trudge to <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> with a green Bag under their Arms, ſo that in ſuch times, the poor Profeſſors, School-Maſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have nothing to do but ſhut up their Shops, pack up their Goods and begon, eſpecially when the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Enemy has no knowledge of Letters, and as little eſteem or kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for them.</p>
               <p>There are ſome that will maintain, that the Church-men themſelves did not a little Contribute to theſe dark times of Ignorance, for becauſe the Philoſophers had given them no ſmall trouble under the Pagan Emperors, and that ſtill under the Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, there were found who oppos'd their Doctrine; the Clergy upon that account, conceiv'd an irreconcileable hatred and averſion againſt the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers and againſt their Opinions, and inſpir'd the ſame Sentiments into all their Auditors, and in all places where they had any Authority or Direction of the Schools, they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad the uſe of all the Heathen Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, under pretence, that the youth might not be Debauched and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60638:34"/>
with the Errours of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and that it was a ſin for them to Study in Books fill'd with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Names of the Heathen Gods, which no good Chriſtian ought ſo much as to mention. 'Twas a very common Story too, which they ſpread abroad, that St. <hi>Jerom</hi> was whipt with Rods in a Dream by the Devil, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he read <hi>Cicero</hi> with too great an Application. And about the Year Four Hundred, the Council of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage</hi> ſtrictly prohibited the Biſhops the reading of any Heathen Book; and as in thoſe miſerable times, few applied themſelves to the Study of Letters, except thoſe that were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin'd to Divinity, ſo that the few relicks of Learning were wholly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſed by the Clergy, the Schools already ruin'd, were only us'd to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the ends which they propos'd to themſelves, that is, the propagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ignorance; and the Students were very well ſatisfi'd with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and neglect of their uſual Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as being mightily affraid of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming too Learned. That ſuch a Barbarity did not a little contribute
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60638:34"/>
to the introduction of Popery, we may learn from hence, that it would have been impoſſible in any but ſuch igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant times to have made the <hi>Epiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae Decretales</hi> (aſcrib'd to the firſt Popes) paſs for lawful, wherein they made the World believe, that it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the right of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to give Laws, at leaſt in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Matters, to all that bare the Name of Chriſtians: But after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, when the Light of Knowledge began to glimmer a little in <hi>Europe,</hi> and that it was impoſſible any long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to contain the <hi>European</hi> Nations, now their Eyes were open'd, in a ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, a groſs and blind Ignorance had given birth to; the Pope who had uſurp'd the Care and Inſpection of the Schools and Nurſeries of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, introduced therein the moſt miſerable Pedantry that ever could be imagined; and which even to this day, his Creatures teach and maintain with a great deal of zeal in all their Schools. But that which does chiefly ſeem to have powerfully contributed to this Greatneſs and Dominion of the Popes, was the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60638:35"/>
of the true Fundamental Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, wherein is contain'd the Cauſe, Nature, and Perfection of the Right and Might of Soveraigns, and wherein amongſt other things is demonſtrated that to the perfection of any State it is abſolutely neceſſary that the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority, be neither leſſened nor divided: And particularly, we find that even the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Politicians, did teach very pernicious Leſſons concerning the mixture and diviſion of the Soveraign Power, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring the common People with Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of Love and Kindneſs for a Democratical or Ariſtocratical State, but an inveterate hatred againſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, and that they were perſwaded, that the more they could bind their Princes Hands, the more happy would be the condition of the Republick. Now, theſe dangerous Maxims were not a little confirm'd by the violent and tyrannical Government of the Emperors, who were mortally hated by the moſt part of their Subjects: ſo that it is no wonder, that this Science was quite overwhelm'd and loſt in an univerſal Ignorance, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60638:35"/>
whileſt the Clergy were of an Opinion that it was quite contrary to their Profeſſion: From hence it came, that upon the firſt laying the Foundations of a Spiritual Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the World ſo little conſider'd or underſtood the conſequences of ſuch a Work, and how prejudicial it was like to be to the Supreme Secular Power, which if they had done, they would undoubtedly have oppoſed themſelves to its firſt growth, and have quaſh'd an Egg that ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſo terrible a Scorpion.</p>
               <p>And we ſee even at this Day, That in all Schools where Popiſh Prieſts bear ſway, they do intirely ſtifle the Science of the Politicks, or at leaſt they do ſo turn and wreſt the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples thereof, that it does not only not choak the Papal Authority, but does rather ſerve to eſtabliſh and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 15. The reaſons that induced the pretended Soveraign of the Church to make <hi>Rome</hi> the Seat of his Government, were chiefly the Authority of that City, which as it had been before the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60638:36"/>
the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, ſo was it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Reſidence of the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperors; for as for what the Papiſts tell of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, that's a pure Fiction, and Story invented by them, to colour the uſurpations of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> which is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt enough from hence, that the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> (when that City became the Capital of the new <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Empire) enjoy'd the ſecond place after the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> and that after the decay of the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Empire, the Priority of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> has often been diſputed by the ſucceeding Biſhops of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> After that the Perſecutions of the Heathen Emperors were quite ceaſed, and that the Chriſtian Religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to breath Liberty, and the Free Exerciſe of their Religion was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by the Statutes and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Empire; the Clergy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd inſenſibly to introduce an Hierarchy or Church-Government in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Republick, under the pretext of eſtabliſhing the Affairs of the Church, and ſetting them in good order; to which end, the Biſhops be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60638:36"/>
to Lord it over the ordinary Prieſts, and to obſerve even a kind of Subordination amongſt themſelves, and to ſuch as were Biſhops of the Capital Cities in each Province, they appointed the Care and Inſpection over the reſt of the ſame Province, and nam'd them <hi>Metropolitans,</hi> who about Eight Ages afterward, took upon themſelves the Name and Title of Arch-Biſhops; amongſt theſe there were four that had the preheminence above all the reſt; namely, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome, Conſtantinople, Antioch,</hi> and <hi>Alexandria,</hi> thoſe being the moſt conſiderable Cities of the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, to which we may add, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> Famous for its ancient Holineſs. And altho' the Emperor <hi>Phocas,</hi> out of the hatred he bore to the Biſhop of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> (who had refus'd to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of the Murder of the Emperor <hi>Maurice)</hi> had given the preheminence to <hi>Boniface</hi> the Third, Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who thereupon took the Name of Oecumenical or Univerſal Biſhop; yet this Prerogative did only conſiſt in a ſimple preference, and did not carry along with it any Power or Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60638:37"/>
which none of the other Patriarchs would ever yield to him: And we read that the Biſhops in <hi>Africa,</hi> when he of <hi>Rome</hi> would have oblig'd them to truckle to his Power, alledging to that intent, a falſifi'd Canon of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, did very vigorouſly reſiſt and baffle that his deſign. Beſides, in the whole frame of the Papal Supremacy, we find nothing Divine, but all built upon Humane Inſtitutions, and there is no more reaſon to be given, why the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> has the firſt place, than he of <hi>Antioch</hi> the third. And foraſmuch as one State has no power to preſcribe Laws to another wholly independent of it; therefore thoſe privileges which have been granted to the Popes by the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors, and the ancient Councils which were nothing elſe but a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Clergy of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, cannot oblige any other State to obedience, nor extend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves farther than the bounds of the ancient Empire. And if perhaps in ſucceeding times, ſome few Chriſtian States have given the Pope any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60638:37"/>
in Eccleſiaſtical Matters with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their Dominions, they did it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, either becauſe they knew upon what grounds that pretended Power was founded, or elſe they were ſurpriz'd and cheated into obedience.</p>
               <p>If it be the firſt, there is no other probable reaſon to be given for it, than that it originally proceeding from ſome Covenant or Agreement made betwixt thoſe States and the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> whileſt the former imagin'd that their Churches could not be well govern'd, till they aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned the Care and Direction of 'em to the latter. Now ſuch an Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment primarily depending on the free will and conſent of any Republick, according to the nature of all other obligations, is <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> void and of no effect, when it turns to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream diſadvantage of the Republick, or when the Popes abuſe that Power which is granted to them. But if this Papal Supremacy be introduc'd <hi>dolo malo,</hi> by the tricks and cheats of the knaviſh Prieſts, then the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus'd and miſs-led States as ſoon as they can diſcover how they have been impos'd on, may lawfully caſt off ſo
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60638:38"/>
unjuſt a yoke, and have right to purſue the cheater, and oblige him to refund all the Damages they have ſuſtain'd by his uſurpations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 16. But it was not all at once, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was able to lay ſo heavy a yoke on all the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches; on the contrary, he found himſelf oblig'd to inſinuate this his uſurp'd Authority by little and little, and ſteal it inſenſibly by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Slights and Artifices; and where once he happen'd to faſten his Claws, 'twas impoſſible to make him loſe his hold, till he had carried away a good ſhare of the prey. Beſides, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> never were wanting to ſerve themſelves very advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly of a good occaſion, of which the moſt advantageous to 'em (in my opinion) was the Emperours leaving <hi>Rome,</hi> and chuſing other Cities for their Reſidence; whereas if they had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways continued to have maintain'd their Authority in that place, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops thereof would have never had the confidence to have erected themſelves into Soveraigns, as we ſee that the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> (who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps had no leſs vanity and itching
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60638:38"/>
after Gevernment, than he of <hi>Rome)</hi> was never able to raiſe his Authority to ſo high a flight.</p>
               <p>The diviſion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire into ſeveral new Kingdoms founded by the Heathen and unlearn'd Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did no leſs contribute to the ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grandizing the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> for theſe People being all converted by the Prelates of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, thought themſelves therefore very much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to honour and reſpect them, and paid a deference to them, as the moſt ancient and moſt conſiderable Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of the <hi>West.</hi> It is not our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign here to deduce all circumſtances at length, 'tis enough, that we repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the moſt remarkable in haſte as it were, and <hi>en-paſſant;</hi> but one thing we can't let ſlip unobſerv'd, that the Biſhops beyond the <hi>Alps</hi> after the Fifth Century, were us'd to go in Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to <hi>Rome</hi> to viſit there the Graves of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> either out of Superſtition and Biggottry, or elſe in ſign of their approving and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe Apoſtles Doctrine; which voluntary piece of Devotion, was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards chang'd into an act of neceſſity,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60638:39"/>
ſo that as many as afterwards negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that Voyage, were excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated; from which Cuſtom, without doubt, the Popes have pretended to oblige all Biſhops to receive their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation from <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other Biſhops too, and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches had often recourſe to that of <hi>Rome,</hi> as Novices to their Superiours, in all weighty Affairs conſulting their advice in the uſe and explication of the Canons; now when the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> perceiv'd that their anſwers were receiv'd as abſolute Deciſions, they began to make Decrees and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders before e'er they were deſir'd to do it, under the pretence that <hi>Rome,</hi> being the firſt and chiefeſt Seat of Chriſtendom, it was the Right and Office of the Biſhop thereof, to ſee that the Canons and Eccleſiaſtical Laws were put in execution; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they conſtituted immediate Judges of the Differences amongſt the other Biſhops, encroached upon the Juriſdiction of the <hi>Metropolitans,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd the Biſhops, which were either not rightly Ordain'd, or that were accuſed of any great Crime, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60638:39"/>
forced them to come to <hi>Rome</hi> to plead their cauſe in perſon; after which, all ſuch as deſir'd to enjoy any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative or exemption from the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Canons, went to <hi>Rome,</hi> where they were always well receiv'd, and gratifi'd in their requeſt, that ſo the Popes might there erect a general Office of all ſort of Diſpenſations.</p>
               <p>Thoſe alſo that had loſt their Cauſe before the ordinary Magiſtrates, were wont, out of ſpite, to appeal to <hi>Rome,</hi> where they were always welcome, and ſeldom fail'd of a good <hi>exit:</hi> Thus the <hi>French</hi> Hiſtorians tell us, that when the Emperor <hi>Honorius</hi> had erected the City of <hi>Arles</hi> into a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis</hi> over ſeven Provinces, the Pope made the Arch-Biſhop thereof his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car General in <hi>France,</hi> out of fear that the ſaid Biſhop might take an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to make himſelf Patriarch of the whole Kingdom, and he was very well contented to enjoy ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carious Power over the ſeventeen Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, into which <hi>France</hi> was at that time divided, rather than have the right in himſelf, and an independent Authority over ſeven Provinces alone:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60638:40"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:60638:40"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:60638:41"/>
And to render the charge committed to him more awful and reſpected, he omitted no opportunity of enlarging and extending the Papal Juriſdiction.</p>
               <p>Afterwards in the eighth Century, when the Eccleſiaſticks and <hi>Monks</hi> were become very infamous for their exorbitant and irregular Lives, one <hi>Winefred</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monk (after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards nam'd <hi>Boniface)</hi> being mov'd with an extraordinary zeal, took up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to reform the manners of the Clergy, as alſo the introduction and plantation of the Chriſtian Religion in ſome parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> and more eſpecially in <hi>Turinge</hi> and <hi>Freezland:</hi> this man, to give a greater luſtre and credit to his Work, devoted himſelf entirely to the Seat of <hi>Rome,</hi> from whence he firſt receiv'd a Biſhop's Mantle, and afterwards was quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd with the Title of Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> and by <hi>Gregory</hi> the Third, was conſtituted his Vicar, who gave him a plenary Authority of aſſembling Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, and making Biſhops in thoſe Countries which he had converted, with Recommendations to the People, and to <hi>Charles Martel</hi> Great Maſter
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60638:41"/>
of <hi>France,</hi> that they ſhould take him under their protection, which they did with a very good will.</p>
               <p>And when <hi>Charlemain</hi> his Son ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifi'd to <hi>Boniface,</hi> that he was very deſirous of eſtabliſhing the Church-Diſcipline, he readily took that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy upon him, to the no ſmall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Chair; to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify the ſame <hi>Charlemain,</hi> he held a Council in <hi>Germany,</hi> and ſeveral Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods in <hi>France</hi> at the requeſt of King <hi>Pepin,</hi> and preſided in all thoſe Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies <hi>tanquam Legatus Sedis Romanae:</hi> And in the firſt Council, the Clergy ſign'd a Confeſſion of Faith, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they oblig'd themſelves not only to perſiſt in the Catholick Faith, but they join'd themſelves as Members to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and vow'd an eternal reſpect and obedience to St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſours. 'Twas this ſame <hi>Boniface</hi> too, that perſwaded the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Germany</hi> to accept of the <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium</hi> from the Pope, who afterwards ſent the ſame into <hi>France</hi> to bind them thereby the faſter to his Intereſts; and ſo ſoon as he had once accuſtom'd them to ſerve themſelves of that ſort
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60638:42"/>
of Robe, he afterwards made it a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary obligation, and forbad them the exerciſe of any Epiſcopal Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before they ſhould receive that Garment from <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Popes likewiſe pretended, That they only had the Power of remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Biſhop from one See to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and oblig'd all the <hi>Western</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to receive their Confirmation from them, for which they muſt pay ſome little Gratification, that was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards converted into the <hi>Annates:</hi> Beſides this, they took away the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Provincial Synods, and annull'd their Decrees, which at laſt was the occaſion that no more were call'd, when they perceiv'd that it was all in vain, whileſt the Pope abrogated all their conſtitutions, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his fancy, without hearing their Reaſons and Juſtifications. At laſt, <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh forced all the Biſhops to ſwear Allegiance and Fidelity to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Chair, and made a Decree, that no Prince or So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign ſhould preſume to condemn any man that made his Appeal to the Pope. They forgot not likewiſe to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60638:42"/>
ſend their Nuncio's or Legates in all Countries, who exercis'd in the Pope's Name that Power and Authority which they had raviſhed from the Arch-Biſhops, and Provincial Synods, and were double diligent in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of their Maſter's Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 17. This Eccleſiaſtical Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy daily increaſing, was extreamly prejudicial to the Civil Powers, whileſt the Clergy by their tricks and devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces attracted infinite Riches, and by their Riches a great number of idle <hi>Prieſts</hi> and lazy <hi>Monks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true, the Church ow'd the greateſt part of its Riches to the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and pious Intentions of Kings, Princes and others who were wheed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into a belief, That to beſtow great Largiſes and Donations on the Church, was a moſt pleaſing and acceptable Sacrifice to God; and this their libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality was afterwards much more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted when the people were perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That by good Works (amongſt which the <hi>Donationes ad pias Cauſas,</hi> held the firſt rank) Heaven and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs were to be purchaſed: And
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60638:43"/>
whereas the Avarice of the Clergy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing with their Riches, could not be ſatiated by the free and generous liberality of the people; they practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all ſort of inventions, to ſqueeze Money out of 'em; upon which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, they inſtituted a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Fopperies and unneceſſary Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, for which the Laity muſt dearly pay. 'Twas this their curſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice, that was the occaſion of Maſſes without number to be ſaid and ſung as well for the living as the dead, of <hi>Purgatory, Indulgences, Diſpenſations, Pilgrimages, Jubilees,</hi> and a thouſand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Bagatelles.</hi> Beſides, they took a ſpecial care to inſinuate themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the good wills of dying perſons, who were ſo much the leſs ſollicitous how they diſpos'd of their temporal Goods, the deſire of which did often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times make their Heirs think them too long liv'd, and<hi>—ante diem Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trios inquirere in Annos.</hi> And at laſt, if all means fail'd, they were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd to fall to down-right beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging.</p>
               <p>Amongſt other devices to get Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, the Popes ſerv'd themſelves very
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60638:43"/>
advantageouſly in the eleventh and twelfth Century of the <hi>Cruſado,</hi> when the People, mov'd with a godly itch of reconquering the Holy Land, let themſelves be mark'd with a Holy Croſs; for the Popes challeng'd to themſelves the management and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of ſuch ſort of Ghoſtly expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and receiv'd into their more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar protection the Goods and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of all thoſe Zealots that took the Croſs upon them, ſo that they could not be proceeded againſt neither Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy nor Criminally until their return from the Holy Land; whereby they had an occaſion of promoting the commerce of their Indulgences and Diſpenſations more than ever: Their Legates had the adminiſtration of all the Alms, Collections and Legacies which were given to that end, and from hence they took a pretext of obliging all the Clergy to pay them Tenths; nay, they very imperiouſly forced Kings, Princes and great Lords to take upon them the <hi>Cruſado,</hi> which Arms they afterwards turn'd againſt all ſuch as they accus'd &amp; condemn'd for Schiſm, and Hereſy, declaring their Goods
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60638:44"/>
confiſcated and void of all lawful Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors, diſtributing and dividing them to ſuch as had rendred them any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Service, and this Authority they exercis'd without asking the leave of Princes and States, under whoſe Civil Juriſdiction they were, who werel likewiſe aw'd into ſo ſlaviſh an obedience, that they durſt not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves againſt theſe Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitures, tho' they eaſily perceiv'd the injuſtice of 'em.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 18. The Riches of the Church increaſing, the number of the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticks was likewiſe proportionably augmented, whileſt there were not a few that were glad to be fed by a fat Kitchin, and make good cheer, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking any care for the proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof: and it was not enough that each Church had its ordain'd Prieſts, Chaplains, and other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Servants; but the moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable muſt have an addition of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons and Prebends, which places conſiſting of ſo great profit and ſo little pains, were ſoon fill'd by men of all ſorts and ſizes; and thus the inconveniences of a ſingle life, which
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60638:44"/>
the Popes, not without a great deal of pains and oppoſition, had intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd in the eleventh and following Centuries, were ſweetned by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and large Revenues of theſe Charges which they ſo quietly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd.</p>
               <p>Beſides, all Chriſtendom ſwarm'd with a prodigious number of <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Nuns,</hi> which ſpringing up in the times of Perſecution in the fourth and fifth Centuries, have afterwards ſtrangely increas'd. Theſe ſort of people at the firſt, were content to get their living by their own Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry: many of 'em gave all their goods to the poor without being in the leaſt oblig'd thereto, and liv'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the care and inſpection of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, according to the Diſcipline that was preſcrib'd them in the Canons. In the ſeventh Century, through all the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Empire, was the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical way of living extreamly in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, and all places were fill'd with Cloyſters, in the founding of which, the Princes and Great Men did ſeem to vie with each other; but after that, their Liberality was, as it were,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60638:45"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:60638:45"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:60638:46"/>
quite exhauſted by the Endowments and Gifts made to ſo many old Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries, and that there was not place enough for ſuch as deſir'd to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd into thoſe Orders: There was at length in the thirteenth Century form'd an Order of <hi>Mendicants</hi> or Begging Monks, which made a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhow of Holineſs, foraſmuch as they would not be thought to go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Cloyſter in hopes of a plentiful and lazy Life; but renouncing all the pleaſures of the World, they would live by Alms and the Beggars-Bas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket.</p>
               <p>The Fancy of a ſingular Merit and Supererrogative Holineſs, induced the People to this Auſterity and Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of living, or rather an unbound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Ambition and Pride ſo natural to all mankind, that not contented to live up to the Commandments of God, and barely to fulfil what he preſcribes, they had rather deſerve Heav'n than accept it as a pure Gift of their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, or purchas'd for them by the Merits of their Redeemer; and the deſire they have of Superiority, and Preference above the reſt, does even
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60638:46"/>
extend it ſelf to the other life. To the embracing of this ſingle and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Life, ſome are carried by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, others out of a proſpect of eaſe and lazineſs; others are thruſt into Cloyſters by their Parents and Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, either out of a motive of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion or Poverty, or elſe for fear of ruining their Family by the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their Goods amongſt a great many Children. From theſe <hi>Monks</hi> has the Pope form'd his <hi>Pretorian</hi> Band or Regiment of Guards, whom he has not alone quarter'd as troubleſome Companions upon the Laity, but does make uſe of 'em alſo as ſpies over the actions of the Biſhops, and reſt of the Clergy: Therefore it is that the Popes have with ſo much zeal maintain'd the privileges of the <hi>Monks,</hi> eſpecially when in the thirteenth Century they would have forc'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the Biſhops Juriſdiction, and ſubjected themſelves immediately to the Pope, and the Pope has found out the way to carry himſelf ſo evenly with them, that altho' there are great Jealouſies betwixt their Orders, as for example, betwixt the <hi>Franciſcans</hi> and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60638:47"/>
                  <hi>Dominicans,</hi> yet he holds the Balance always ſo even, and diſpenſes his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours ſo impartially, that one Order cannot be oppreſs'd by the other, nor has reaſon to complain of the Pope's injuſtice. Theſe <hi>Monks</hi> are very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to the ordinary Prieſts, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they attract to themſelves the greateſt part of the Alms, Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and Gains proceeding from the Burials of the Rich, beſides the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Conſciences, and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments, which has drawn upon them the immortal ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of the Biſhops and Secular Prieſts, which thoſe other don't much value, whileſt they are under the care and protection of the Pope; and beſides, when a Biſhop at any time oppos'd the Pope, the Monks like ſo many Blood Hounds were immediately after his heels, and by their bawlings and exclamations, ſoon made him loſe his Credit with the People, by whom their Hypocriſy and pretended Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty made them much reſpected; ſo that the Biſhops were forced to truc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle to the Pope's Authority, becauſe the People would afford them no Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60638:47"/>
or Aſſiſtance; thus the Monks were ſet as ſo many ſpies over the Conduct of the Biſhops, which when they found blamable, they did not fail immediately to ſignify to the Generals that reſided always at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo that the Pope might make a time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſition againſt their practices. In ſhort, theſe Monks were not the leaſt cauſe of the Biſhops not reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the growing Power of the Pope; for finding it always in vain, they were forced with the reſt to yield to the mighty Torrent. Tho' there were a great many of 'em likewiſe, that were well enough contented to ſubmit to this ſlavery, in hopes of ſharing the Prey with their Chief, and becauſe they were thereby freed from the Juriſdiction of their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Princes, whoſe power they more dreaded, than that of a diſtant Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal, the Judges whereof being of the ſame Trade as they, were not ſo terrible to them, for one Crow will not pick out its fellow's Eyes. In the mean while, 'tis moſt certain, that a great many Biſhops, eſpecially of this ſide the <hi>Alps,</hi> do with a great deal
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60638:48"/>
of impatience groan under the yoke of <hi>Rome;</hi> which did appear ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> where the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Biſhops did with great earneſtneſs endeavour, that it might be declar'd, <hi>quod Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia Epiſcoporum ſit Juris Divini,</hi> or, that by the Divine Appointment each Biſhop is oblig'd to reſide in his own Church, as all the <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> of <hi>France</hi> and the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> do maintain. Now the wiſeſt could eaſily penetrate what lay hid under this ſpecious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; for if God has commanded that, it muſt neceſſarily follow, that he would afford the way and means of putting it in practice, <hi>qui dat jus ad finem, dat jus ad media;</hi> and then by conſequence it is no longer need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to run to <hi>Rome,</hi> and buy the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of exerciſing their charge. And it coſt the Pope a great deal of pains and a great deal of fears, before he could oblige the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> to deſiſt from a deſign which extreamly ſhook his uſurp'd Authority, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may be aſſur'd that that ſhall be the laſt General Council, nor will the Pope ever more venture his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60638:48"/>
in ſuch like Aſſemblies, which beſides will be but very uſeleſs things as long as the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and others, teach, That the Pope is above the Councils, and, That he cannot err, and, That the Councils themſelves muſt receive their <hi>vim obligandi à confirmatione Papae.</hi> In the mean while, let a man ſay what he will, it is certainly the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of the Biſhops to truckle to that power which they at firſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Pope to exerciſe over them, for it is certain that if they ſhould withdraw themſelves from his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, they would fall into the hands of the Secular Power; eſpecially ſince they could never be able to make good their party againſt the Pope, without the Protection of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, who muſt be a very power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Prince to afford it them, therefore of two evils, 'tis beſt that they chuſe the leaſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 19. But altho' the Church had been never ſo rich and populous, yet to the erecting of a Spiritual Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, it was abſolutely neceſſary that the Pope ſhould in no wiſe be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to any temporal Juriſdictions, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60638:49"/>
that he ſhould hold his Reſidence in ſuch a place, which being free from obedience to all other Potentates, ſhould depend on, and own no other Maſter but him, as alſo to be poſſeſt of ſuch Revenues as might enable him to live honourably and ſplendidly, and not be ruin'd by the diſmembring of his State, and where his Partizans, when at any time purſued by their offended Soveraigns, might find a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and certain Refuge; but before he could compaſs all theſe advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges it has coſt him a world of pains, time, and a powerful Reſiſtance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides a thouſand ſecret Practices and Intrigues. 'Tis true, the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> whileſt the Empire of the <hi>Weſt</hi> flouriſhed, and as long as the Kingdom of the <hi>Goths</hi> laſted in <hi>Italy,</hi> had no opportunity to think of, much leſs to put in Execution theſe their am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious deſigns; but after that the <hi>Goths</hi> were driven out of <hi>Italy</hi> by the Emperor <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> with <hi>Rome</hi> reduc'd to a Province of the <hi>Graecian</hi> Empire, the Pope could not let ſlip ſo fair an opportunity of freeing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from the Juriſdiction of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60638:49"/>
to which did not a little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute the contempt of the Imperial Authority in <hi>Italy,</hi> partly caus'd by the ill Gouernment of the <hi>Exarchate</hi> or Vice-Roy of <hi>Ravenna,</hi> and partly by their weakneſs, whileſt the <hi>Lumbards</hi> were much more powerful in <hi>Italy</hi> by the continual quarrels of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors about the time of <hi>Juſtinian</hi> the ſecond; to which reaſons we may very well add the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Emperors prohibiting the adoration of Images; for <hi>Leo Iſaurus</hi> threw them out of all the Churches, whileſt the reſpect that was paid 'em did degenerate into open Idolatry, and the People began to be perſwaded that a greater Reverence was due to their Saints, than to God himſelf. Againſt this Reformation, Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſecond, violently op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd himſelf, and defended the Image-Worſhip with a great deal of zeal, partly becauſe it was one of the chiefeſt Heads of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Superſtition, and did bring in no ſmall gain to the Pope's Coffers; and partly becauſe it vex'd him extreamly, that the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors ſhould meddle with Eccleſiaſtical Affairs without his knowledge, and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60638:50"/>
againſt his conſent, whileſt he was employ'd in the Introduction of his Spiritual Monarchy: And beſides, this ſeem'd a very fit time for him to ſhake off the Authority of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors. In ſhort, it was by his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation that the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Italians,</hi> who, till then, had been very faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Emperor, refus'd to pay Tribute to him any longer; and there happening about that time a tumult at <hi>Ravenna,</hi> which was the Seat of the <hi>Exarch,</hi> he himſelf, defending the rights of the Emperors, was kill'd in the Tumult. And thus ended the Rule of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Emperors in that part of <hi>Italy,</hi> which ever ſince has been free, and in ſubjection to none.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 20. 'Twas thus the Popes ſhook off the Juriſdiction of the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> Emperors, but were in danger of falling into the clutches of a new Lord, whoſe yoke would have been much more inſupportable, than that of the far diſtant Emperors, for the Kings of the <hi>Lumbards</hi> endeavour'd to poſſeſs themſelves of thoſe Lands which were fallen off from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, and conſequently to render
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60638:50"/>
themſelves Maſters of all <hi>Italy;</hi> and in effect, they ſeiz'd upon <hi>Ravenna,</hi> and ſeveral other places, ſo that there was no body in <hi>Italy,</hi> that could withſtand their uſurpations; thereupon, the Pope knew not to what refuge he ſhould betake himſelf, unleſs to the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> who endeavour'd firſt to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt the differences amicably and by fair means, and becauſe the <hi>Lumbards</hi> refus'd to hearken to any accomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they reſolv'd to oblige them thereto by force; and they took up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them the Protection of <hi>Italy</hi> the more willingly, not only becauſe the Pope <hi>Zacharias</hi> had approv'd of <hi>Pepins</hi>'s depoſing his lawful Soveraign; and from Great Maſter, making himſelf to be declar'd King of <hi>France;</hi> but alſo becauſe they found thereby ſo good an opportunity of making New Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts in <hi>Italy,</hi> a Country which had often made the <hi>French</hi> Mouths water. Now whileſt <hi>Pepin,</hi> and after him <hi>Charlemain</hi> made War very ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully againſt the <hi>Lumbards,</hi> and had reconquer'd the whole Kingdom of <hi>Italy,</hi> they preſented the Pope with all that part of it, which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60638:51"/>
under the <hi>Exarchate;</hi> which fat Donation, That they might more peaceably retain, the Popes in after Ages gave out, that it was the gift of <hi>Constantine</hi> the Great; which ſham, paſt very eaſily upon the ignorance of thoſe barbarous times. In ſhort, the <hi>French</hi> Kings were much oblig'd to the Pope for the Reaſons already mention'd, and therefore by this gift they ſought to expreſs their Gratitude, eſpecially whileſt by a preſent of what was none of their own, they could acquire a great reputation of Charity and Holineſs; which in theſe times, was valu'd according to the Liberalities and Donations made to the Clergy; inſomuch, that the Kings themſelves endeavour'd to free their Foundations and Settlements on the Church, from all ſort of Subjection or Homage, and to aſſure to the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy the free poſſeſſion of what they had given 'em. Now theſe too ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant Donations have not been the leaſt reaſon, why the Clergy has taken ſo much pains to ſhake off the Royal Supremacy, whileſt they juſtly apprehended, that the Succeſſors of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60638:51"/>
thoſe that had been ſo liberal to them, coming to ſee their Errour ſhould recall all that had been given to them; and from hence it is, that the <hi>Politicks</hi> have made this remark: That Kings by the Conceſſion of too great Privileges and immunities have made themſelves more Enemies than Friends, whilſt the Receivers live in a continual fear and ſuſpicion of the Givers leaſt they ſhould one day recall or retrench their immoderate Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities; and therefore to prevent that Inconvenience, they are never quiet till they have tied them ſo faſt, that it ſhall not be in the King's Power, if it were in his will, to deprive them of 'em. The moſt Impartial of the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed are of the opinion that the Popes did heretofore deſign to erect into a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, thoſe Lands which were thus beſtowed on them, but that their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple oppos'd it, deſiring rather to be free: eſpecially whilſt it ſeem'd very ſtrange to them that the Pope (who was a Clergy-man) ſhould likewiſe be a Temporal Prince; 'twas upon this Account that <hi>Rome</hi> took up Arms, and drove out of their City Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60638:52"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:60638:52"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:60638:53"/>
third, who betaking himſelf to <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemain,</hi> was by him Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſh'd in his Popedom. But on the other ſide, the Pope conjointly with the People of <hi>Rome</hi> declar'd <hi>Charlemain</hi> Emperor, whereby he became Sovereign over the <hi>Exarchate</hi> of <hi>Ravenna,</hi> and other places of <hi>Italy</hi> which had rais'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into free States out of the Ruins of the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Empire, ſo that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Pope himſelf held thoſe Lands, dependently. of the Emperor who was likewiſe named <hi>Advocatus et Defenſor Eccleſiae,</hi> which laſted till the time of the Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 21. But at laſt this Advocacy or Protection of the Emperor began to ſeem tedious to the Popes, becauſe they could not be elected without the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors conſent and confirmation, who us'd likewiſe to curb them, when they grew inſolent; and proceeded even ſometimes to the depoſal of them. Now to ſhake off this heavy Yoke of the Emperor, the Popes left no ſtone unturn'd, and took a wonderful deal of pains before they could attain to their deſire. 'Twas therefore they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd ſo earneſtly to give the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60638:53"/>
their hands full of work, ſometimes in <hi>Germany,</hi> ſometimes in <hi>Italy,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to weaken their power and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. To which the <hi>German</hi> Biſhops did not a little concurr, who were not well pleas'd to be under the Subjection of the Emperor, and receive their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks at his hands. Therefore they conſpir'd with the Pope to eſtabliſh an abſolute Sovereignty in the Church. And to put this their deſign in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they found no time more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient or proper than the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, who by reaſon of his diſſolute life and Government was in perpetual diſſention with his States of <hi>Germany.</hi> Therefore when <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh, who was before nam'd <hi>Hilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand,</hi> aſcended the Papal Chair, being a proud, ambitious, and reſolute man, he began to exclaim againſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, giving out that the diſtribution of Eccleſiaſtical Benefices did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to him, becauſe he made a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Traffick of them, ſelling them to people of an ill repute, and inſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them therein before they had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Holy orders; and becauſe the Emperor undertook to defend his
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60638:54"/>
juſt Rights, the Pope thunder'd out an Excommunication, and animated the Biſhops and the other Sates of <hi>Germany</hi> againſt him, and gave him ſo much trouble and vexation, that at laſt, he was fain to abandon his Right of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing the Biſhopricks, and leave them wholly in the Pope's diſpoſal. But the Pope's main aim was not ſo much to free the Biſhops from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror's juriſdiction, as to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Supreme in <hi>Italy,</hi> and to bring all the Princes in Subjection to the Papal Chair: And ſome are of opinion that he might at laſt have effected, what he had begun, whilſt <hi>Europe</hi> at that time was divided into ſo many little Lordſhips, and moſt of 'em had weak, and inconſiderable Princes, and a great many of them, either out of devotion, or elſe for fear of being ſwallow'd up by the Great Ones, choſe freely to ſubmit themſelves to the Papal Chair, and to pay him Tribute. So that if there had but ſucceeded three or four Popes, as Couragious and cunning as <hi>Gregory,</hi> covering their deſign with the veil of Religion, and taking the ſpecious pretext of Defending the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60638:54"/>
intereſt againſt the oppreſſion of their Princes, they had made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves temporal, as well as Spiritual Monarchs. And the Pope did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pretend to ſlip his neck out of the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and free himſelf from the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror's power, but he did likewiſe endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make him take his turn, and to ſubmit him to his own Authority; for he made himſelf Judge of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror's Actions, ſummon'd him to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before his Tribunal, and anſwer to the Complaints which his Subjects made againſt him, and by reaſon of his Non-appearance, he declar'd him Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, and fallen from the Empire; and altho' his Son <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth, endeavour'd to recover what the Popes had ſqueez'd out of his Father, and ſeizing upon Pope <hi>Paſchal,</hi> obliged him to reſtore to him his right of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſting the Biſhops; yet the Clergy of <hi>Europe</hi> were ſo diſcontented therewith, and teas'd him continually till they had forced him (in the Year 1122.) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign (for ever) that Right to the Pope. Not long before, the ſame diſpute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe in <hi>England,</hi> which at laſt (in the Year 1107.) was thus adjuſted: The
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60638:55"/>
King ſhould no longer inſiſt upon his Right of inveſting the Biſhops; and they in acknowledgment of that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour ſhould do him Homage, which Article was not very pleaſing to the Pope, who had been better contented if they had refus'd to pay any ſort of ſubmiſſion to their King, as he did ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually forbid the Biſhops of <hi>France</hi> to do; but <hi>Lewis</hi> the ſixth and his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors ſtood up ſo ſtoutly in defence of this their Right, that the Pope was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with ſhame to quit his pretenſions: Beſides, fearing to draw upon his Head two Powerful Monarchs of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> he thought it better to keep in with one, whom he in time of need might oppoſe againſt the other, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially whileſt it was not ſo much his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to weaken the <hi>French</hi> King, with whom he had not ſo many Feathers to pluck, as to humble the Emperor, who was then very Powerful in <hi>Italy,</hi> and endeavoured to bring into ſubjection the City of <hi>Rome;</hi> beſides, he knew that <hi>Germany</hi> was not ſo ſtreightly United as <hi>France,</hi> and whileſt the other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were jealous and apprehenſive of the Emperor's Greatneſs, they eaſily
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60638:55"/>
agreed with the Pope to humble him a little, which deſign they palliated with the pretence of Protecting the Papal Chair and the Church's Authority. 'Tis true, <hi>Frederick</hi> the firſt and the ſecond uſed all their efforts to re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the Imperial Power o'er the Pope, but ineffectually, whileſt <hi>Italy</hi> was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into the two Factions of the <hi>Guelphs</hi> and <hi>Gihelines;</hi> the former of which held with the Pope, the latter with the Emperor, and caus'd ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate and implacable quarrels, that it was impoſſible for the Emperor to reduce <hi>Italy</hi> to a perfect Obedience. And after the death of <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, whilſt all things were in a ſtrange confuſion by reaſon of the long <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regnum</hi> that then Succeeded, the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Emperors thank'd God that they could maintain themſelves Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably in <hi>Germany,</hi> without troubling their Heads any more with the affairs of <hi>Italy;</hi> ſo that the Popes have quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exercis'd their Sovereignty as well perſonally, as in reſpect of the Goods of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 22. But this Greatneſs could not terminate the Pope's Ambition,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60638:56"/>
but was the occaſion of his ſtarting another Doctrine, which ſerv'd to extend his power far beyond that of all other Princes; for it maintain'd a ſort of an indirect Authority, right of examining and animadverting on the actions of all the temporal Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns; and tho' it was not ſaid in down-right terms, that the Princes did depend on his Holineſs in meer Worldly Affairs, yet he thought that that abſolute power which he had acquir'd in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, did ſufficiently Authorize him to judge of their Actions, whether they were good or bad, to adviſe, and correct them; and in fine, to forbid what he thought unfit, and to command what he approv'd of.</p>
               <p>Thus when at any time the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were in War with one another, the Pope made uſe of his Authority to command a Ceſſation of Arms, and that they ſhould bring their Quarrel before him, and expect his deciſion thereof, threatning the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, not only to Excommunicate their perſons, but likewiſe to Suſpend through their whole Kingdom the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60638:56"/>
exerciſe of Divine Worſhip, and uſe of the Holy Sacraments, whileſt he imagin'd that it belong'd to him only to remove all occaſions of Scandal in Chriſtendom, to ſuccour the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and in ſhort to adminiſter Judgment and Juſtice to the whole World; therefore he willingly heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to, and took upon him to redreſs the injuries of all ſuch as made their complaints to him; nay, he proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed farther, taking cognizance of thoſe injuſtices which Princes did to their own Subjects, as alſo of the new im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions that were laid on them, and forbad ſometimes their proceeding any farther, under pain of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication: Sometimes the Pope de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd confiſcated the Goods of ſuch as he had excommunicated, and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful prize for the next that ſhould lay hands on them, expoſing thereby their lives to very eminent Dangers, and diſpenſing their Subjects from all Oaths of Allegiance, under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that it was not fit to leave the Government of Chriſtian People to Princes that ſhould rebel againſt the Church; and ſuch Helliſh Maxims
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60638:57"/>
ſeveral Popes have dar'd to maintain and put in execution againſt Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Heads; and to render more plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible theſe their execrable Deſigns amongſt the ignorant people, they ſerv'd themſelves of a forg'd Decretal, whereon they began to found a new <hi>Jus Canonicum,</hi> which aſcrib'd to the Pope an unlimitted Power over all Chriſtians, and impower'd him as common Father to command or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the Faithful the exerciſe of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever had any relation to their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and good of the Religion, and to puniſh ſuch as refus'd to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey. And the reaſon why the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors of <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh, did not exerciſe ſuch a power over the Emperors, was (ſay they) either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Emperors liv'd ſo well, that there was no need of it, or that the Popes lead ſo bad a life, that they ought rather to be corrected by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, than think of correcting others.</p>
               <p>And to give the more Authority to the Pope's pretenſions, the did not fail to quote what St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> had done againſt the Emperor <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> and that the Biſhops of <hi>Spain,</hi> had
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60638:57"/>
oblig'd their King <hi>Wamba</hi> to ſubmit to ſo extraordinary a Pennance, as the renouncing of his Kingdom; as alſo, That the <hi>French</hi> Biſhops had depos'd <hi>Lewis</hi> ſurnam'd the <hi>Godly,</hi> who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards durſt not re-aſſume the Crown, without the Conſent of another Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of the Biſhops: That <hi>Fulk,</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Rhemes</hi> had threatned <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Simple,</hi> to Diſpence his Subjects of that obedience they ow'd unto him, in caſe he proceeded to make any Alliance with the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> who at that time were Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. Now, no body could doubt, but that the Pope's Authority extends it ſelf farther than all the Biſhops, ſince it had no other bounds than what the Canons of the Councils and Decrees of the Popes themſelves pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed it; which had never forbid them to depoſe Kings; but their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors could not prevent that which they could not fore-ſee, nor did they ever dream, that they ſhould arrive to ſuch a height of impudence. And ſince the Popes had taken upon 'em to beſtow the Royal Title, and that there were found Princes, who either
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60638:58"/>
out of a motive of Ambition or Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, did ſeek their Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from <hi>Rome,</hi> they imagin'd they had no leſs a right to deprive thoſe of their Crowns, whom they eſteem'd unworthy to bear them. They could not a little incommode the Princes likewiſe by their forbidding all Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages within the ſeventh Degree of Conſanguinity, and the fourth of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity, for whileſt among great Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, there can ſeldom any Match be propos'd, where one of thoſe Degrees will not occur, they were in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual fear of the Pope's troubling their Negotiation, if they did not humbly crouch to him, and implore his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation; ſo that let it happen how it would, they found themſelves ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to dance after his Pipe.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, The Popes by the great number of Affairs, to be diſpatch'd in their Courts, allur'd the greateſt and moſt learned Men of <hi>Europe</hi> to them, who came with a deſign either of procuring themſelves ſome employ, or elſe to accompliſh themſelves in this great School, to be able to ſerve their Countries at home. Now
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60638:58"/>
as moſt of theſe expected their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune from the Pope, they devoted themſelves entirely to his will, as well as all the Clergy who unanimouſly own'd him their Head and General. And this Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the eighth, did very evidently demonſtrate by the <hi>Jubilee</hi> which he publiſh'd in the year 1300. where he appear'd firſt in the Habit of an Emperor, then in his Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial Robes, ordering two Swords to be carried before him as Marks of his Authority in all Civil as well as Eccleſiaſtical Affairs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 23. In the mean while the Popes could not long enjoy this uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and intolerable power without a great deal of oppoſition; ſo that they were forced more than once to change their Notes, and to manage their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions more ſlyly and cautiouſly. 'Tis true, in the Quarrels which they had with the Emperors <hi>Henry,</hi> and <hi>Frederick,</hi> they often got the better; yet ſometimes they met with cruel rubs, and were forced to hear things which were not much to their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit; and from which the impartial may judge, That it was not the Glory
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60638:59"/>
of God, but Worldly Honor and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, that were the ends of all their Deſigns.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="90-205" type="pages">
               <p>But when <hi>Boniface</hi> the eighth would have play'd ſome of his tricks with <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Fair</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> he oppos'd himſelf ſo ſeaſonably againſt the Popes encroachments, and defended his rights ſo courageouſly, that that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute turn'd wholly to the ſhame and confuſion of the Pope. And <hi>Philip,</hi> that he might not give any occaſion of ſcandal by his proſecuting and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging himſelf on <hi>Boniface,</hi> gave out, that he did not attack him as the Vicar of Jeſus Chriſt, but as a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Prelate, who by unlawful ways had uſurp'd the Papal Chair, and therefore deſired the calling toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a General Council to deliver the Church of ſo unjuſt an oppreſſor.</p>
               <p>But the Schiſms which afterwards follow'd, made a much greater breach in the Popes Authority, when by the diviſion of the Cardinals, two Popes were at the ſame time elected, who excommunicated and anathematized one another; and, the better to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain themſelves in the Papal Chair,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60638:59"/>
they were forced to flatter and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs the Kings, and <hi>tacitly</hi> own there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that they could not ſubſiſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Support; and ſuch a Schiſm was a very evident Mark that it was not the Holy Ghoſt, but deviliſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues that preſided in thoſe Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and therefore the moſt prudent of the Clergy were of opinion, that neither of 'em ought to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Papal Authority, but that they ſhould proceed to a new Election, which afterwards was pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis'd by the Council of <hi>Conſtance.</hi> The firſt Schiſm as I take it, happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the year 1134; or as others reckon, 1130. when after the Death of <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth, two Popes, <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the ſecond, and <hi>Anacletus,</hi> were choſen both together; and tho' the firſt had gain'd the moſt partizans, yet the latter was vigorouſly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd againſt him by the King of <hi>Sicily</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Aquitain:</hi> But he dying, his Friends choſe a third in his place, nam'd <hi>Victor,</hi> whom <hi>Innocent</hi> brought to an Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, ſo that he at laſt ceas'd from his pretenſions, and freely ſubmitted
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60638:60"/>
himſelf to <hi>Innocent.</hi> But after the Death of <hi>Adrian</hi> the fourth, there were again two Popes elected, <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the third, and <hi>Victor</hi> the fourth; with the firſt held <hi>England France,</hi> and <hi>Sicily;</hi> with the latter, <hi>Frederick</hi> the firſt, all <hi>Germany,</hi> and moſt of the Clergy of <hi>Rome;</hi> and after his Death, his followers choſe three o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſucceſſively in his place, who were all out-liv'd by <hi>Alexander;</hi> now all theſe curs'd, and excommunicated one another after the moſt infamous manner in the World, and each of 'em were forc'd to ſhew more Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience than Authority to their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors.</p>
               <p>But the greateſt and moſt ſcandalous Schiſm was that which aroſe after the death of <hi>Gregory</hi> the eleventh, when in like manner two Popes were cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, one of which kept his Reſidence at <hi>Rome,</hi> and the other at <hi>Avignon,</hi> and this laſted amongſt their Succeſſors at leaſt Forty years, whileſt both Parties vomited out all the injuries imaginable againſt one another: The Pope of <hi>Avig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> was maintain'd by <hi>France, Scotland, Caſtile, Savoy</hi> and <hi>Naples,</hi> but the reſt
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60638:60"/>
of the Chriſtian States held with the Pope of <hi>Rome;</hi> both of 'em bragg'd of the Great and Holy Perſons they had of their ſide, as likewiſe the Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Miracles which Heaven in their Favour had produced, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſons were brought in the Favour of each of 'em, that there was no other way to be found than to Cite them both before the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> where they were forc'd to Renounce their Popedoms, and a new Pope was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected. The laſt Schiſm happen'd in the Year 1433, when the Council of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil</hi> depos'd <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fourth, and choſe in his place Pope <hi>Foelix</hi> the fifth. But the firſt refus'd to ſubmit to their Authority, and the Diſſention laſted till after the death of <hi>Eugenius,</hi> when <hi>Nicholas</hi> the fifth being choſen, <hi>Foelix</hi> deſirous of Peace, yielded all his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions to him on very good Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, about the Year 1438. Now 'tis eaſy to imagine how much theſe Schiſms and Quarrels expos'd the <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda Paparum,</hi> whileſt the Councils were oblig'd on theſe occaſions to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe their Authority, and Bridle the Irregularities of the Pope, to which
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:60638:61"/>
people began to appeal from the Pope, as to the Higher Powers; ſo that when the Popes began at any time to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly, there was no ſuch Bug-bears as to threaten them with a Council. 'Tis plain that the Popes could not lord it over the Councils, ſince <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh himſelf, when he had renew'd the old quarrel betwixt him and the Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, declar'd that he would call a Council, in a place of Security, where both the Friends and Enemies, Eccleſiaſtick as well as Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, might come without any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and judge whether he or the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror had violated the Peace, and to propoſe means for the re-eſtabliſhing of it. The ſame Proteſtation was made by Pope <hi>Gelaſius</hi> the ſecond, in his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel with <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth; to which he added that he was contented to ſtand to the Deciſion of his Brethren the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, whom God himſelf had made his Judges in the Church, and without whom he durſt not take in hand an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair of ſo Great Importance. <hi>Innocent</hi> the third declar'd alſo, that he durſt not undertake to judge of the Marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Philip Auguſt,</hi> and <hi>Ingeburg</hi> of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60638:61"/>
                  <hi>Denmark,</hi> without asking the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a General Council; and if he ſhould preſume to do it, he ſhould be in danger of loſing his Charge and Dignity, whereby he ſeem'd to own, that a Pope, by the abuſe of his Office, might Lawfully be depriv'd of the ſame. But when the Princes in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing times inſiſted upon thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of the Popes, all the anſwer and ſatisfaction they could have, was, that truly their Predeceſſors had us'd ſuch ſort of Expreſſions, but they were one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Complements, and bare Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous words, and that the Modeſty which they had ſhown in that matter, ought not to be prejudicial to them.</p>
               <p>Thus in the Year 1409. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Piſa</hi> depos'd the two Antipopes, <hi>Benedict</hi> the twelfth, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the twelfth, and in their place choſe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the fifth; but the Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> did not only confirm the Election of the ſaid two Popes, but alſo depos'd <hi>John</hi> the twenty fourth who ſucceded <hi>Alexander</hi> the fifth.</p>
               <p>The Council of <hi>Baſil</hi> proceeded in like manner againſt <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fourth, and made a Decree beſide, That nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60638:62"/>
at <hi>Rome,</hi> nor in any other place, ſhould there be any Expedition-Money given for Eccleſiaſtical Matters. All which Proceedings ſtruck at the very Foundations of Papal Government; and therefore 'tis no wonder that the Popes were afterwards ſo ſhy in calling the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and that they then us'd ſo many Artifices to impede its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeing any thing prejudicial to their Authority, and that, ſince that time they have bidden an Eternal adieu to all Councils.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 24. Amongſt all theſe Schiſms the Tranſlation of the Papal Chair from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Avignon,</hi> did not a little weaken their Authority; the Firſt that began it, (if I am not deceiv'd,) was <hi>Clement</hi> the fifth at the perſwaſion of <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Fair,</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> who had quarrell'd with <hi>Boniface</hi> the eighth, and was Excommunicated by him; the effects of which he deſign'd to prevent if he could but once oblige the Popes to reſide in <hi>France,</hi> eſpecially whileſt thereby moſt of the Cardinals ſhould be choſen out of the <hi>French</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and indeed the Pope, did reſide in that City more than ſeventy year,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:60638:62"/>
without reckoning the time of the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-popes,</hi> which became very prejudicial to the Papal Soveraignty; for till then, amongſt other pretences on which the Popedom was founded, one of the Chiefeſt was, That St. <hi>Peter</hi> having been Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> by his perſonal Reſidence there, had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated a particular Advantage and Holineſs to that City, which, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Popes could tranſport to <hi>Avignon,</hi> was very much doubted of; ſo that from thence, the Pope found himſelf very often oblig'd to dance after the <hi>French-man's</hi> Pipes, and to be wholly at his Devotion; tho' the <hi>French,</hi> who did then much brag of the prize they had got, do now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, that by the Reſidence of the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> they had gain'd nothing, unleſs it be the Art of Chicaning, Simony, and another abominable Crime, which it is hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lawful to pronounce; to which we may add, that the Papal Court be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus tranſlated from its natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Seat into a Foreign Country, its imperfections were the more eaſily expos'd, and conſequently the Popes
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:60638:63"/>
became more deſpicable. This ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Popes was no leſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to the Eccleſiaſtical Lands in <hi>Italy,</hi> for after that the Emperor had loſt all his Authority there, every petty Prince was for erecting himſelf into a Soveraign, and by the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the <hi>Guelphs</hi> and <hi>Gibelines,</hi> all things were brought into confuſion. The neighbouring Princes, without any ſcruple, pillag'd the Church's Patrimony, whileſt the abſence of the Pope had made them forget all the reſpect they ow'd him; the moſt of his Cities at the perſwaſion of the <hi>Florentines,</hi> drove out his Legates, and either erected themſelves into Free States, or choſe them a Prince of their own City; to which we may add, that the Emperor <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> having quarrell'd with the Pope, and gain'd the Subjects of the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical State, to his Intereſts, made himſelf Maſter of moſt of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as being a Feoff of the Empire, and inveſted therewith ſuch as took his part againſt the Pope; ſo that St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Patrimony was at that time in a very bad condition; nor have the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60638:63"/>
Popes been ſince able to reduce the better part of what was thus taken from them, into their power, but are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to leave the poſſeſſors thereof in a free enjoyment of what they have gotten.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, the City of <hi>Rome</hi> was at laſt oblig'd to ſubmit to the Pope's Soveraignty, which it had ſo long oppos'd; after that, Pope <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> the ninth, in the year 1393. had fortified the Caſtle of St. <hi>Angelo,</hi> which ſerv'd to bridle the City, and keep it in ſubjection. <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth, was chiefly the cauſe that the Patrimony of the Church fell again into the hands of the Pope: he had a natural Son, nam'd <hi>Caeſar Borgia,</hi> who, upon the account of the Dukedom of <hi>Valence,</hi> brought to him as Dowry by his Wife <hi>Charlotte d'Albret,</hi> was commonly call'd <hi>il Duca <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentino.</hi> Now whileſt the Pope uſed all his endeavours, to make his Son a powerful Prince in <hi>Italy,</hi> to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to his ends, he bethought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of this expedient: He drove out thoſe little <hi>Signiori</hi> that were poſſeſs'd of ſmall parcels of the Church's Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritory,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60638:64"/>
making himſelf Maſter of thoſe places which they held, and then gave his Son the Propriety thereof. This his deſign ſucceeded very hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily, and he made a ſhift to reduce either by force or treachery, moſt of thoſe little Lordſhips into his ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and tho' <hi>Borgia</hi> us'd a great deal of temerity in the management of this affair; yet he ſaid, he knew well enough what he did, ſince his Father, who was inſpir'd by the Holy Ghoſt, approv'd of all his actions.</p>
               <p>But when he wanted Money to pay his Souldiers, he plotted with his Father to poiſon ſeveral of the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Cardinals at a Banquet deſign'd for that purpoſe, and thereby, not only to put himſelf in poſſeſſion of their goods, but likewiſe to be rid of hateful perſons, who, he fear'd, might oppoſe themſelves to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; but in the mean time, the Servant he had employ'd in this his deviliſh deſign, by miſtake, gave the Pope and his Son the empoiſon'd drink, ſo that the Pope died immediately thereof, and the Duke very hardly eſcaped, at the expence of a terrible ſickneſs;
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60638:64"/>
nor could he afterwards with all his Authority oblige the Cardinals to chuſe a Pope that ſhould be in his Intereſts.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Borgia</hi>'s vaſt ambitious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects dwindled into nothing, for after the Death of <hi>Pius</hi> the third, who held the Chair a very few Weeks, came <hi>Julius</hi> the ſecond, the ſworn impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable enemy of <hi>Borgia,</hi> to ſucceed him, who reduced all that he had taken, and drove him at laſt out of the Country; and this Pope prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo far by his Bribes, and Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that he regain'd all that the Church had had before in its poſſeſſion, except the Dutchy of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> which like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, at the latter end of the laſt Age, the legitimate Race of all the Princes of <hi>Eſt</hi> being ended, fell into the Popes hands again; he alſo hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the <hi>French</hi> from making them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Maſters of all <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 25. But now whileſt the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſeem'd to be in its greateſt Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, and at as high a point of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection as it could ever aſpire to, all the <hi>Weſt</hi> having join'd it ſelf to the Communion and Fellowſhip of the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60638:65"/>
                  <hi>Roman</hi> Church, excepting ſome few relicks of the <hi>Vaudois</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and the <hi>Huſſites</hi> in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> which were alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether inconſiderable; and the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel betwixt Pope <hi>Julius</hi> the ſecond, and <hi>Lewis</hi> the twelfth of <hi>France,</hi> which had eaſily occaſion'd a new Schiſm, being happily compos'd after that Pope's death by <hi>Leon</hi> the Tenth; and the old complaints that were us'd to be made againſt the ambition of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> being almoſt all laid aſleep; there happen'd upon a very ſlight occaſion, ſo terrible an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection againſt the Papal Chair, that a great part of <hi>Europe</hi> did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw its ſelf from the Tyranny there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and did run the riſque of an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverable deſtruction. In which Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, as in all other, we will only obſerve, how much humane prudence and deſigns contributed thereto, and will rather adore with an humble reſpect and admiration the Counſel and Work of God Almighty, than preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly penetrate into his Holy Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; and here we may not unfitly quote that expreſſion which <hi>Tacitus</hi> uſes in his Hiſtory; <hi>Abditos Numinis</hi>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:60638:65"/>
                  <hi>ſenſus exquirere illicitum, nec ideo aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quare.</hi> Now <hi>Leon</hi> the tenth, was a peaceable, magnificent and very libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Prince to Wiſe and Learned Men, and might have paſs'd for a good Pope, had he had but an indifferent knowledge of Religion, and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Piety, for both which (on the contrary) he was very inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: He living very ſplendidly, and having exhauſted his Treaſures by the extravagant Pomp and Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of his Court, did not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Art of making Gold, but was forc'd in his neceſſities to have recourſe to the Cardinal <hi>Laurentius Puccius,</hi> who finding all the other means of getting Money quite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted, bethought himſelf of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, which the Pope diſpers'd for Money through all Chriſtendom, in the moſt ample form, for the ſervice as well of the dead as of the living, with permiſſion to eat Eggs, and Milk-Victuals on Faſt-days, with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſuch like privileges; and the Money which he hoped to collect by this infamous commerce, was already diſpos'd of, and that eſpecially, which
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60638:66"/>
was to be gather'd in <hi>Saxony,</hi> and in all that Country to the Sea, was deſtin'd for <hi>Magdalen</hi> the Pope's Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; and that they might extract greater gains from this ſort of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandice, a Commiſſion of collecting ſuch Money was given to one <hi>Arcim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldus</hi> a Biſhop in name and habit only, but a man that was incomparably well verſed in the tricks of the <hi>Genoa</hi> Merchants, and that would only deal out Commiſſions to ſuch as bad moſt for them, and whoſe only proſpect was the advantage and gain that could be made of 'em. Now 'twas anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently the Cuſtom in <hi>Saxony</hi> for the St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Hermets to preach the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, but <hi>Arcimboldus</hi> his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners knowing the great Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience they had in that ſort of work, durſt not truſt them for fear of being out-witted by 'em, therefore they made choiſe of the <hi>Dominicans;</hi> this procedure touch'd the <hi>Auſtin</hi> Monks to the quick, whileſt they ſaw it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected on their reputation, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring'd their rights and privileges.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Dominicans</hi> to ſhew their diligence in their new employ, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60638:66"/>
up their Merchandice extreamly to the great ſcandal of their Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, whileſt the Commiſſaries ſpent in riotous Debauches what the poor peaſants had ſcrap'd together, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem their ſins withal. Thereupon <hi>Luther,</hi> a Monk of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Order, took occaſion to preach againſt this impudent and ſcandalous commerce; and after that, he had throughly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin'd the whole contrivance, he propos'd Ninety Five <hi>Theſes</hi> upon that Matter at <hi>Wittenburg,</hi> in the year 1517. againſt which, <hi>John Tetſel</hi> a <hi>Dominican</hi> Fryar of <hi>Frankford</hi> on the other, propos'd as many quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; the diſpute being thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menc'd, they began both to write at large in defence of their propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but whileſt <hi>Luther</hi> had the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Reaſon on his ſide, his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary could not defend his Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by any ſtronger Arguments than the Church and Pope's Authority; this oblig'd <hi>Luther</hi> to go farther, and to ſearch into the ground and foundation of the Pope's Authority, and to examine in what condition the Church then was, whereby he more
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60638:67"/>
and more diſcover'd the errors and abuſes thereof, and ſharply repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended the ſcandalous Lives of the Popes and Monks, and prov'd that the Soveraign powers were oblig'd to reform ſuch abuſes; and to the end that he might be ſupported by them, he very advantageouſly repreſented their condition, power and grandeur, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Prieſts had before given little and contemptible Idea's, and vilifi'd them extreamly, by which means his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was receiv'd by a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of perſons, and ſpread it ſelf mightily in a ſmall time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 26. But that we may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtand how a poor inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Monk could give ſo terrible a blow to the Pope's Authority, we muſt obſerve that next to the Divine Direction and Concurrence, the fit juncture of time did not a little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the ſo ſtrange ſucceſs of this mighty Work, as likewiſe the Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of the people's minds at that very time.</p>
               <p>For firſt the Cauſe of <hi>Luther,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Indulgences, was ſo juſt and reaſonable, that ſeveral Famous
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60638:67"/>
Divines ranged themſelves on his ſide, (though they afterwards fell off from him) as well as ſome Cardinals, and <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> himſelf: And his Adverſaries were ſuch perſons, that all honeſt men were ſcandaliz'd at their ignorance and malice: Beſides, there was no body at firſt that could have been perſwaded, the buſineſs would have gone ſo far. <hi>Luther</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf did not then dream of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volting from the Pope. <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Emperor was not averſe to <hi>Luther's</hi> Doctrine; and when he heard of him, he is reported to have ſaid, <hi>They ſhould keep that Monk for him;</hi> there were only a few Monks, and the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries of the Indulgences, whoſe Trade was like to go to wrack, that oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed themſelves; and they made ſuch a-do, that by their folly and impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence they rais'd a little ſpark of fire into a mighty and dangerous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion.</p>
               <p>Now Chriſtendom at that time was in a very miſerable condition, the whole World was plung'd into unneceſſary Ceremonies, the malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Monks rul'd uncontrouledly over
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60638:68"/>
the minds and conſciences of the Laity, which they had fetter'd in undiſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luble bands. The Divinity of thoſe times, was degenerated into meer So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry and Bantering. The Prieſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd their opinions, and laid down their propoſitions without ever put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves to the trouble of prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them; and the way of living of the then Clergy from the higheſt to the loweſt, did contract the <hi>Odium</hi> and contempt of all the World; the two preceding Popes, <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth, and <hi>Julius</hi> the ſecond, had made their Memory ſtink, and left a very bad name behind 'em upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their vices, their quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſs infidelity, ambition and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch qualifications very much diſagreeing with the requiſites of a Clergy-man; the Biſhops if they were any thing worth, were nevertheleſs deeply embroil'd in worldly Affairs, and moſt of 'em lead a very ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous life, being better verſed in the hunting of Beaſts, than in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick way of catching Men; the Prieſts and Monks were plung'd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver head and ears in ignorance, and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60638:68"/>
gave a great Scandal to the common People by their Debauches and irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Lives, as they were become unſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable to all the World by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable Avarice and Thirſt after Riches.</p>
               <p>Beſides, thoſe that oppos'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves firſt againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> were miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably ignorant, and for the moſt part infamous Monks, who not being us'd to his way of diſputing, were at the firſt bout confounded, and could not tell where to lay hold on him; and tho' in the preceding times the Clergy were as bad as then, yet the univerſal ignorance of thoſe barbarous Ages did not let it appear; but afterwards, when <hi>Europe</hi> began to be enlighten'd by the blooming dawn and reſtorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Letters, their Spots and Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities were expos'd to every man's naked Eye: And therefore it was, that the Prieſts and Monks, whoſe Eyes were offended and dazled by the new-appearing Light, were ſo much incens'd againſt thoſe <hi>Inſtauratores lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum,</hi> and ſought all ways to ſuppreſs 'em; and becauſe they would do it with good grounds, they made a <hi>Work</hi>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:60638:69"/>
                  <hi>of Religion</hi> of it; which oblig'd the Men of Learning to ridicule their ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, and to labour more and more to diſcover their ſhameful ignorance.</p>
               <p>Thus the Monks began an impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Quarrel againſt <hi>Johannes Reuchli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and, right or wrong, would prove him a Heretick; where they ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully confounded themſelves, and gave occaſion to that learned Gentleman <hi>Ulrich van Hutten</hi> (as I take it) to ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly them moſt ſtrangely in his <hi>Epiſtolis obſcurorum virorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now whilſt the War was carried on with a great deal of heat and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs, between the Champions and Perſecutors of Learning, the buſineſs of <hi>Luther</hi> very opportunely fell out at the ſame time; therefore the Monks us'd all their Arts and Perſwaſions to engage the Learned to oppoſe <hi>Luther,</hi> thereby to ſuppreſs both Parties with <hi>their own</hi> Arms: Which was the occaſion that moſt of the <hi>Cultores bonarum litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> ranged themſelves on <hi>Luther</hi>'s ſide; as in effect, no man can deny, but that the learned <hi>Eraſmus</hi> of <hi>Roter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> had a great ſhare in this Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, by diſcovering and publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60638:69"/>
reprehending a great number of their Errors and Abuſes; by rejecting their Scholaſtick Divinity; by exciting the People to the reading of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and the Ancient Fathers; by tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into Ridicule the Barbarity and Ignorance both of the Prieſts and Monks; and in ſhort, by favouring in general the Cauſe of <hi>Luther</hi> at the firſt, though his hot and violent way of writing was not altogether approv'd by him.</p>
               <p>Now the bare ſilence of <hi>Eraſmus</hi> was extreamly diſadvantageous to <hi>Luther</hi>'s Oppoſers; for whilſt <hi>Eraſmus</hi> at that time was look'd upon to be one of the moſt learned Divines of <hi>Europe,</hi> it was univerſally believ'd, that he would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage himſelf in this Quarrel againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> had he not perceiv'd, that he had reaſon of his ſide; for when he afterwards put forth his Book <hi>de Libero Arbitrio,</hi> it did not meet with many Partizans; whilſt it was very remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that he writ it more at the Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of others, than as his own real Belief and Perſwaſion: Beſides, it was a thing which had but little reference to the matter in hand: And moreover,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:60638:70"/>
it was very ſolidly and pertinently an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by <hi>Luther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then again, the <hi>German</hi> Princes and States were very much diſguſted with the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> upon the account of the manifold unreaſonable Exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons laid on them; for they ſaw well, that the deſign was only to fool them out of their Money, and thereby to ſupport the Pope's extravagant Pomp and Magnificence. The imminent danger of War with the <hi>Turks</hi> did not a little contribute to the good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Luther</hi>'s Affairs: And the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions and Quarrels happening be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, and <hi>Harry</hi> the Eight, made ſo great a buſtle in the World, that no body was at leiſure to mind the petty Diſputes of the Clergy. Some are of opinion, that <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth was not ſorry to ſee the Doctrine of <hi>Luther</hi> make ſo great a Progreſs in <hi>Germany,</hi> for thereby the Empire being divided into Parties, he might the more eaſily oppreſs the States, and build an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Monarchy upon their Ruines; for otherwiſe he could not have found the leaſt difficulty or oppoſition, had
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60638:70"/>
he undertaken to ſtifle the upſtart Doctrine in its infancy, and in the year 1521, had ſeiz'd upon <hi>Luther</hi> at <hi>Worms,</hi> which might have paſt for an excellent <hi>Coup d'etat.</hi> But for all that, I can't believe that this Doctrine had been ſo eaſily ſuppreſt, though <hi>Luther</hi> had been put to death againſt the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Promiſe and ſafe Conduct which was given him. But 'tis much more probable, that the Emperor being then a young Prince, could not penetrate into the conſequence of the Affair, and beſides, did not think it conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to oppoſe the Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> who was then in great credit; and the Wars with the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>French</hi> King hindred him from attempting any thing againſt the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> whilſt <hi>Francis</hi> began to make Leagues and confederate himſelf with 'em. Though 'tis moſt certain, that he ſerv'd himſelf afterwards of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of Religion, to make War upon the Proteſtant States, that by their fall he might make himſelf a way to uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Monarchy. But tho' Fortune ſmil'd on him at the Battel of <hi>Smal-kald.</hi> he could not perfect the ſo-lucki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60638:71"/>
begun deſign, whilſt the aſſiſtance of the <hi>German</hi> Princes was ſo neceſſary to him both againſt the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> and whilſt he deſign'd to place the Imperial Crown on his Son <hi>Philip</hi>'s Head. In ſhort, the Pope himſelf <hi>(Paul</hi> the Third) did ſo much dread the Fortune of the Emperor, that he excited the <hi>French</hi> to oppoſe his grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Greatneſs, and to hinder the total ruin of the Proteſtant Party: Nor did he ſcruple to uſe the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> help thereto, ſo mightily was he afraid of a Reformation in his Court. In fine, the Pope had prejudic'd himſelf and his own Affairs by his ill Conduct; for it was a great overſight in <hi>Leon</hi> the Tenth, ſo violently to ſupport the Cauſe of the Indulgence-ſellers, as alſo his Deciſion by a Bull in the Month of <hi>November</hi> 1518. of the queſtions which were begun to be diſputed on, whereby he cut off all means of an Accommodation, and depriv'd <hi>Luther</hi> of his hopes of Pardon or Reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Whereas he had done much more prudently, had he declar'd himſelf Neuter, and impos'd in the mean time
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:60638:71"/>
Silence on both Parties, till he could have found out ſome expedient to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe <hi>Luther.</hi> So likewiſe the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Cajetan</hi> acted very imprudently at <hi>Ausburg,</hi> in the following year 1519, in handling <hi>Luther</hi> ſo roughly, and not embracing his reaſonable Propoſition of Silence, on condition that the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal would oblige his Adverſaries to do the ſame; for he forced him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to Extremities which perhaps he had never otherwiſe thought of, and to fly into an open Rebellion againſt the Papal Authority: But no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing would ſatisfie, unleſs he retra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted all his Writings; whereas they might have eaſily granted him, That there was a great Corruption of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that he might deſiſt from the Reformation of their Doctrine.</p>
               <p>Beſides, whilſt the Pope was very inſtant with the Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> that he would deliver up <hi>Luther,</hi> he found himſelf more and more engag'd into a Proof of the Pope's Injuſtice, as alſo to ſhew upon what grounds his Cauſe was founded, that ſo he might induce the Elector to ſhut his Ears to the Pope's Requeſt. But when <hi>Luther</hi>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:60638:72"/>
afterwards appeal'd to a Council, the Pope rendered himſelf very much ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, whilſt he temporiz'd and ſpun out the Affair into a great many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays; for it was very viſible, that he could never be able to defend his Cauſe, if it came once to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by impartial and unintereſted men. It happen'd likewiſe very unluckily, that the Pope embroil'd himſelf not long after with <hi>Harry</hi> the Eight, who to revenge himſelf of the Pope, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Door to the Engliſh Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: As alſo the Houſe of <hi>Navarr</hi> did mightily contribute to the introducing and eſtabliſhing of the ſame Religion in <hi>France,</hi> out of hate, as ſome think, to the Pope, who had excited <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand</hi> the Catholick, to ſeize upon and poſſeſs himſelf of that Kingdom.</p>
               <p>To all which we may add, That there were a great many honeſt men among the Papiſts, who were not ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſee the Pope a little curb'd and check'd, as <hi>Luther</hi> us'd him. Thus all things wonderfully concurr'd to the executing the Divine Will and Decree of the Almighty.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:60638:72"/>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 27. But why <hi>Luther</hi>'s Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine has not made a greater progreſs nor overthrown the whole Popedom, there may be ſeveral ſtrong and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Reaſons given thereof: For, firſt you muſt take notice, That ſo ſoon as ſeveral States had renounced the Pope's Authority, the chief direction of <hi>Eccleſiaſtick Affairs</hi> muſt neceſſarily devolve on the Supreme Magiſtrate: For though ſome of them would have aſſum'd the Authority over the reſt, that were of the ſame Belief and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, the others that thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves quite as good, and as fit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, would never give their conſent; which did much weaken their Union, and hindred them from acting ſo una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly againſt the Pope as he could do againſt them. Beſides, at the firſt they did not proceed deliberately to a Reformation, as if they would after a mature conſideration form a new ſtate, but they fell into this Change inſenſibly and unexpectedly, and the buſineſs was carried underhand, and went on very ſlowly; and though <hi>Luther</hi> was the <hi>Bell-weather</hi> of the Flock, yet his Followers would not conform
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:60638:73"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:60638:73"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:60638:74"/>
themſelves in every point to his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents, but pretended that they had likewiſe ſomething to ſay for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Hence did ariſe ſeveral Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and Diſputes among them, which whilſt there was no body whoſe Authority was ſufficient to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide 'em, and each one obſtinately perſiſted in his Opinion, quickly oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd Schiſms amongſt them, and made them, forgetting their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy, to fall foul upon one another. This gave the <hi>Papiſts</hi> a very fair occaſion to ſay, The Hereticks were confounded amongſt themſelves, not knowing what they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; and were wandring in an inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricable Labyrinth, ſince their falling away from the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to did not a little contribute thoſe, who abuſing the Name of the Holy Goſpel, led an impious and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous life; as if the Goſpel-Freedom conſiſted in the abandoning themſelves to all ſorts of Debauchery. This their ill Conduct gave occaſion to the Pope's Followers to blacken the Doctrine of <hi>Luther,</hi> becauſe he had ſo ſeverely reprehended the ſcandalous
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60638:74"/>
Lives of their Clergy, and thereby had gain'd himſelf a ſtrong Party. And it was likewiſe a great misfortune, that a very little after the preaching of <hi>Luther,</hi> there ſprung up great ſwarms of <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> as the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts,</hi> and ſuch-like; and that the Bores in <hi>Germany</hi> made a dangerous Inſurrection; all which Diſturbances were by the Pope's Creatures attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to <hi>Luther</hi>'s Doctrine; ſo that a great many Princes began to ſuſpect it, as if it were the Introducer of all ſorts of Licence and Irregular Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties amongſt the Mobile, which they eſteem'd a greater Evil than the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Clergy: So that they oppos'd themſelves with all their might againſt this new and ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeditious Doctrine of <hi>Luther.</hi> Some are of opinion, That the Academy of <hi>Paris</hi> had a great ſhare herein; for <hi>Luther</hi> imagining that the <hi>French Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> were diſcontented with <hi>Leon</hi> the Tenth, upon the account of the <hi>Prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick Sanction,</hi> concerning the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their Biſhops, and therefore would not let ſlip ſo fair an occaſion of revenging themſelves on him.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:60638:75"/>
'Twas in theſe Thoughts that <hi>Luther</hi> was ſo willing to ſubmit to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion his Diſputes with <hi>Eckius;</hi> but unfortunately for him, for they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd his Opinions in very rude and jocquant terms. <hi>Spain</hi> too found it to be her Intereſt to take into her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection the Chair of <hi>Rome,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore violently oppos'd the Proteſtant Religion, and ſo vigorouſly ſupported the ſolemn League in <hi>France,</hi> that <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, to gain the Crown, was abſolutely forced to abjure his Religion. Some have likewiſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, that the advancement of the Proteſtant Religion was not a little retarded firſt by <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by <hi>Calvin,</hi> who introducing a too great and haſty Reformation, as well in things relating to the external form of the Church, as in the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial points of Faith, fell from one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream into the other. Now <hi>Luther</hi> had chang'd very few of thoſe things to which the People had been accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed; for he left in the Church the Ornaments, Bells, Organs, and Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, and retain'd likewiſe the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of the Maſs, excepting that
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:60638:75"/>
he added thereto ſeveral Prayers in the Vulgar Tongue; ſo that he was look'd upon by the greateſt part as a Reformer only of ſome Abuſes that had ſlipt into their Religion. But juſt as it appeared that this Revolution was like to be univerſal, <hi>Zuinglius</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven'd in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> who, inſtead of obſerving <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>'s method, began immediately to preach againſt the Preſence of Chriſt's Body in the Euchariſt, aboliſht en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely all ſort of Ornaments and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, broke in pieces the Altars and Images, extirpated all ſort of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the Hierarchy, or Government of the Church, and deſpoil'd the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of all that which might ſerve to attract the Eyes and the external Senſes: Whereupon the common Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple conceiv'd a great averſion againſt them, and cleav'd with much more zeal and attachment to the Religion which they received from their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors.</p>
               <p>The Riches of the Church did alſo not a little contribute to the progreſs of <hi>Luther</hi>'s Doctrine, whilſt ſeveral laid hold on the opportunity of appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60638:76"/>
them to themſelves, and perhaps did no leſs hinder it, whileſt moſt of the great Prelates ſtuck faſt to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> who perhaps would have ventur'd to have ſhaken off the yoke, if the fear of loſing their fat Benefices, had not kept them faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to their Maſters Intereſts; as we ſee that it happen'd in <hi>France,</hi> where the Prelates themſelves, as well as the common People before the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation did mightily deſpiſe the Pope's Authority, but afterwards were great ſticklers for the Chair of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſtirr'd up the peoples hatred againſt the new Doctrine, as ſoon as they perceiv'd that if that prevail'd, they muſt out.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 28. But after that, the Pope and his Creatures were a little reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd out of the terrible conſternati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo puiſſant an oppoſition had put them in, and that his Adverſaries be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to fall out among themſelves, he eſtabliſh'd his Affairs in a much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter condition than at firſt, and ſtood ſo vigilantly upon his Guard, that the Proteſtants are not only incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of doing him any more miſchief;
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60638:76"/>
but he does proceed every day to get ſignal advantages over them; for that which <hi>Luther</hi> took an occaſion to hurt him moſt by, is now quite taken away; or at leaſt, is more pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and modeſtly practis'd by him, <hi>ſi non caſtè, ſaltem cautè:</hi> And the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons which <hi>Luther</hi> us'd againſt the Pope, are now by the ſame advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageouſly turn'd againſt their Maſter; for the Popes do no longer ſo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently inſult over Soveraign Princes as they were wont to do, but uſe them with much more civility and moderation; 'tis true, in the laſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury, <hi>Paul</hi> the fourth did handle the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſomething roughly, as <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth in the Age wherein we live, did deal with the <hi>Venetians</hi> much after the ſame rate; but their differences were quickly termined by a prudent mediation, before the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs came to be too high; and the Popes have been ſince convinced, that ſuch heats are very prejudicial to their States; as in effect, <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth was immediately brought to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, when the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador made him believe, that the <hi>Venetians</hi>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:60638:77"/>
had ſent for Miniſters from <hi>Geneva,</hi> and that he ſhould ſhortly hear they were all turn'd Proteſtants. Beſides, the Papal Chair has no more been fill'd by ſuch notorious Debauchees as <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth, or by any of ſo Martial and fighting an humor as <hi>Julius</hi> the ſecond; but on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, they endeavour to put their plots in execution with leſs noiſe, and more cunning, and by appearing outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly very zealous for the peace and quiet of Chriſtendom.</p>
               <p>The ſcandalous Merchandizing of Indulgences, and a too groſs Simony is by them ſuſpended, whileſt they endeavour to drain the Peoples pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by more honourable and plauſible means; the Biſhops likewiſe in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, are much mended, and comport themſelves with more modeſty and gravity than they did before <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>'s time, and there is now to be found amongſt their Clergy, very Wiſe and Learned Men. They have like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, made a great Reformation amongſt the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Prieſts and Friars, and that bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality and ignorance which hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:60638:77"/>
was ſo common amongſt them, is now no more to be ſeen. The brave and learned Sermons of <hi>Luther</hi> was that which at firſt procur'd him and his Diſciples ſo great a concourſe of people; they edified a great many by the excellent Books which they put out in their Mother tongue, to excite them to Meditation, Piety, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and Spiritual Exerciſes; both which the Papiſts have ſince imitated; and there are found amongſt them a great many good Preachers, and wholeſome Books of Prayer and Meditation; ſo that at preſent, the Proteſtant Clergy have no longer reaſon to reproach the <hi>Romiſh</hi> with their want of that mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and excellent conduct which they obſerve in the external Service of God. They are alſo well verſed in all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, and are ready with whole dozens of diſtinctions for every ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection made againſt them; for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, whereas there is nothing can be more ridiculouſly invented, than the Pope's diſtributing out Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for twenty or thirty Thouſand Years, they give it a colour with the diſtinction of <hi>intenſivè</hi> and <hi>extenſivè,</hi>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:60638:78"/>
                  <hi>potentialiter</hi> and <hi>actualiter,</hi> wherein the young Students take a great deal of pleaſure, and the ignorant imagine ſome great Myſteries to be invelopt therein; whereas alſo in <hi>Luther</hi>'s time, the ignorance of the Clergy, and their hatred to Learned Men was ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to the Popedom; thoſe of that Communion, and eſpecially, the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have ſince found remedies for that inconvenience; for the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have not only taken upon them the Information and Inſtruction of the youth, but in the Countries where they are eſtabliſh'd, they have as 'twere made a <hi>Monopoly</hi> thereof, ſo that learning is now ſo far from being any longer prejudicial to 'em, that it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures them great advantages: Laſtly, They deſiſted from the propagation of their Religion with Fire and Sword, and endeavour'd to allure the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of the Proteſtants, with good Words, great Promiſes, and effectual Preferments.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that will go over to 'em, if they have any parts and capacities, are ſure to make their Fortunes; to which, upon the account of their
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:60638:78"/>
Church's Riches they have the beſt opportunity in the World: Whereas on the contrary, if any one of them would turn Proteſtant, and does not bring means along with him, or is not of a more than ordinary underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he has nothing but contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble poverty to expect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> has much contributed to the raiſing up and reſtoring of the Popedom, by dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving out the Proteſtants, not only out of its hereditary Lands, but likewiſe from <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the depending Provinces, and lately out of all <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> or elſe by obliging them to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 29. From what has been ſaid before, may eaſily be underſtood, how, and by what means this Spiritual Monarchy has inſinuated it ſelf in the <hi>Weſtern</hi> part of Chriſtendom, but that you may the better conceive the ſtructure and all the reſorts of this Machine; 'twould not be amiſs, if we conſider'd the Pope two ways, firſt, as he is one of the Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> and ſecondly, as the Ghoſtly Soveraign of the <hi>Occidental</hi> Churches.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:60638:79"/>
As to the firſt, we ſay, That the Pope may very well paſs for one of the greateſt Lords in <hi>Italy,</hi> but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this conſideration, muſt he yield to moſt of the Potentates of <hi>Europe;</hi> his Territories are the City of <hi>Rome</hi> with its Dependances on both the ſides the <hi>Tyber,</hi> the Dutchy of <hi>Benevento</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> of <hi>Spoletto, Urbin</hi> and <hi>Ferrara,</hi> the <hi>Marquiſate</hi> of <hi>Ancona,</hi> ſeveral places in <hi>Hetruria,</hi> as alſo the <hi>Romaniola</hi> or <hi>Flaminia,</hi> contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Cities of <hi>Bolonia</hi> and <hi>Ravenna;</hi> in <hi>France</hi> he has the County of <hi>Avig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non; Parma</hi> is a Fee of the Church, which <hi>Paul</hi> the third inveſted his Son <hi>Peter Lewis Farneſſe</hi> with, tho' ſince that time, it has been reſolv'd, that for the future, it ſhall not be in the Pope's power to alienate the vacant Fees, nor inveſt any one with the Church-Lands, for fear of weakning the Papal State; and to the end that the Pope might have where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal to maintain his Court, if it ſhould happen that any part of his Foreign Revenues ſhould fail or come ſhort. The Kingdom of <hi>Naples</hi> is likewiſe a Fee or Copy-Hold of the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:60638:79"/>
Church, in acknowledgment of which the King of <hi>Spain</hi> does yearly preſent the Pope with a white Hackney, and five Thouſand Ducats. As for the Pope's Pretenſions upon other Lands, they are now no longer paſſable. All theſe Countries are peopled, and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile enough, and do comprehend a great many conſiderable Towns and Cities, from whence the Pope does yearly draw about two millions of Gold; and his Officers are very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that the People may not grow too rich.</p>
               <p>Though there are good Souldiers enough to be found in the Pope's Dominions, yet his Militia is not very conſiderable, whilſt the means he uſes to maintain his Countries are quite contrary to thoſe of other Princes. He keeps ready equipp'd about Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Gallies, which uſually lie at <hi>Civita Vecchia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The politick Maxims of the Pope, which he, as temporal Prince, puts in practice, do moſtly conſiſt in the maintaining of the Peace in <hi>Italy,</hi> and retaining it in the ſame poſture and condition as it is at preſent, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:60638:80"/>
in ſuppreſſing any upſtart Power that may give Laws to all the reſt. Beſides, 'tis his peculiar Intereſt to hinder the <hi>Turk</hi> from getting footing in <hi>Italy,</hi> and in caſe of any Invaſion, to unite not only all the <hi>Italian</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but likewiſe all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> againſt him, who likewiſe ought not to ſuffer that this noble Country fall into the hands of thoſe <hi>Barbarians.</hi> The Pope has now no reaſon to be alarm'd by <hi>Germany,</hi> as long as it does continue in its preſent form of Government: But if it ſhould happen to fall under an Abſolute Monarchy, it might eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly revive its old pretenſions. <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France</hi> are thoſe which can only give the Pope his hand full of buſineſs, and therefore in reſpect of thoſe it is the Pope's Intereſt to foment a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Diviſion betwixt them; or to balance them ſo equally, that neither may be able to trample upon the other. I don't doubt but the Pope wiſhes with all his Heart that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> were not ſo near a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to him in <hi>Italy,</hi> and would not be ſorry to ſee him driven out of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples;</hi> but there's no probability that
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:60638:80"/>
he could effect that himſelf; and to call in the <hi>French</hi> to drive out the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> were to leap out of the Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-pan into the Fire. Therefore the Pope muſt be contented to hinder the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> from making any greater Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs in <hi>Italy;</hi> and if at any time <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould attempt it, <hi>France</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Italian</hi> Princes would ſoon be upon their backs. Nor is it leſs the Pope's Intereſt to hinder <hi>France</hi> from getting ſo ſure footing there, as to be able to ſway the Affairs of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, according to its own will and pleaſure. The Pope has nothing to fear from the other States of <hi>Italy;</hi> for though they cheriſh a ſecret ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt him, whilſt a ſpiritual power is become very formidable to them, and ſome of them have been ſhrewdly handled by him, yet they are forced to reſpect him outwardly, and dare not undertake any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him openly: But on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, they will never ſuffer him to aggrandize himſelf by the Ruines of any one of them; whilſt that crafty Nation is very jealous of keeping the balance equal amongſt them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:60638:81"/>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 30. But if we conſider the Pope the ſecond way, that is, as the ſpiritual Monarch of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and Vicar of Jeſus Chriſt upon Earth, we ſhall find the whole <hi>baſis</hi> of that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſo artificially and ingeniou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly contriv'd, that a man may well ſay, there was never a more ſubtile Machine invented whilſt the World ſtood, than is the <hi>POPEDOM,</hi> the which to ſupport and maintain does require ſo much the more Cunning and Intrigues, as its Intereſts are dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from thoſe of all the World beſide, and the Title to ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Soveraignty more weak and impertinent. The Proſpect of other States is, to ſecure to themſelves an external as well as internal Peace and Tranquility: 'Tis to this end that each Member of the Common-wealth does contribute as much as in him lies, not ſparing Limb nor Life to put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a condition of reſiſting the Injuries and Violences of Strangers; as alſo each particular ought to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to himſelf a competent Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence by his proper Labour and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry: But the aims and deſigns of
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:60638:81"/>
the Papal Government is, that the Pope and his Clergy endeavour to make themſelves rich, powerful, and conſidered in the World, and to provide for their own eaſe and ſecurity by the Sweats of other mens Brows, which they effect by all ſort of allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and plauſible perſwaſions. And whereas other States are at exceſſive charges in the maintaining of ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Armies and a number of Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; the Pope on the contrary makes his Militia ſubſiſt, how great ſoever it be, at the Expences of others, and yet does ſerve himſelf thereof much more advantageouſly than all others.</p>
               <p>Beſides, other Princes find it to be their Intereſt not to neglect the Maxim <hi>de imperio intra terminos coercendo;</hi> or of not extending too far the limits of their Territories: But the Pope has no reaſon to obſerve the ſame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, for 'twould be neither dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous nor troubleſome to him, though his Empire ſhould reach both to the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Indies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Right of Soveraignty is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon clear and uncontroulable Reaſon, and on the Inſtitution of God
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:60638:82"/>
himſelf; ſo that without it, it were impoſſible for men to lead an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, ſafe, and orderly Life; but I am ſure, 'tis impoſſible to find ſo plain and well-grounded a Title of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Power;</hi> or to prove, That a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Soveraignty is as neceſſary to the Welfare of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> as Temporal Powers are to the Peace and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of Mankind: And he that will not believe this Poſition, let him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bring one ſolid Argument to the contrary, and we will yield with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration to the Subtleneſs of his Wit. But if the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Doctors will appeal to an expreſs and poſitive order of God, they are oblig'd to bring clear and indiſputable proofs from the Holy Scripture to demonſtrate, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, when he ſent forth his Apoſtles into all Countries to preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, gave them power not only to <hi>teach all Nations,</hi> preferrably to all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane prohibition, (which is not doubted) but alſo without the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign's Conſent, though he ſhould profeſs the ſame Chriſtian Religion, to eſtabliſh in the publick Miniſtry, who, and how many they themſelves
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:60638:82"/>
thought fit, and afterwards to reſign to them the right of augmenting their Order without number, and without meaſure, whilſt no body muſt contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict them, no, not ſo much as he whoſe Right they ſo boldly uſurped; and that in conſequence of theſe their Proceedings, ſince thoſe they had thus eſtabliſh'd, can't live by the Air, like <hi>Camelions,</hi> to impower them to ſcrape together by all ſort of Tricks and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, not only what may be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the preſervation of Life, but likewiſe to ſubminiſtrate to Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Superfluity; and that beſides all ſuch as were reſolv'd to embrace this Profeſſion, ſhould be freed from the juriſdiction of the Supreme Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; as alſo their Goods, howſoever acquir'd, nay, though they immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proceeded from the Revenue of the Republick, and were protected there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, were yet to be independent of the Higher Powers: Nor might it be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them to lay any Taxes thereon, to limit their immoderate Bounds, or to convert them to any other uſe in the greateſt caſe of neceſſity: And that the Supreme Direction of the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:60638:83"/>
of this Order, as well in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of all Offices, as of their Revenues, ſhould belong to one of the ſame Order, on whom they ſhould abſolutely depend; whilſt their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Soveraign might not pretend to a more prevalent Right, although the Multitude, or the Rebellion of ſuch a Spiritual Order, ſhould tend to the ruine of the State; or that it could not be ſaved, but by the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of their Goods, unleſs the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector of the Order gave his Conſent to it.</p>
               <p>Beſides all this, there remains clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be prov'd another <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> which conſiſts in Matter of Fact; as for example: That Jeſus Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd on St. <hi>Peter</hi> alone the ſpiritual Soveraignty over the Church, without the admiſſion of any of the other Apoſtles into the Government, and that ſuch a Prerogative was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd only to his perſon, but that by an equal right it ſhould eternally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to ſuch as ſhould ſucceed him in the place whereof he was Biſhop: As alſo that St. <hi>Peter</hi> was actually Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> did there exerciſe ſuch
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:60638:83"/>
a Soveraignty, and that he did irrevoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly communicate it to this place alone excluding all others where he <hi>afterwards</hi> preached. Now, as the proof of theſe Propoſitions is extreamly difficult, the Doctors of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church ought to take care, that they do not form them too accurately before their Auditors, but only in general terms, and to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver 'em with the Foxes Tail; for 'tis much more their Intereſt to buzz into the Peoples Ears a number of Reaſons, which are but little to the purpoſe; as for example, the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes made in Scripture, that <hi>the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt the Church;</hi> of the Greatneſs and flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eſtate of the Church; of its An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity; of the Succeſſion of the Popes; of the Fathers, Councils; of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of ſo many Nations and times; of Wonders, and ſuch-like ſtuff, very proper for a noiſy Declamation. 'Tis an Expedient likewiſe which they have found very profitable, without much Debate, to brand thoſe with the Title of Hereticks that dare to begin any Diſpute with them; for it is juſt as much as if they ſhould term them ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:60638:84"/>
and impertinent Novices, that have not yet learn'd their Trade, that don't know how to ſpeak with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour before their Maſters, but deſerve to be burned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 31. In the mean while 'tis very plain, that this Spiritual Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty was abſolutely oblig'd to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the form of Monarchy, and that it is altogether inconſiſtent with ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Aristocracy</hi> or <hi>Democracy,</hi> as well upon the account of ſeveral other inconveniences, as becauſe it would be morally impoſſible to erect any ſort of <hi>Democracy</hi> or <hi>Aristocracy</hi> (where ſo many different opinions always occurr) that could be ſo well modell'd by the moſt exact and ſevereſt Laws, as not be plagu'd with a thouſand Diviſions, Schiſms and Factions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the whole ſtructure built upon ſo weak Foundations, would ſoon fall to ruin; but amongſt the ſeveral ſorts of Monarchy, they have pitch'd upon ſo good a one, that it is impoſſible to find any other more agreeing with their Intereſts, than that they have choſen; and it is certain, that all the moſt ſubtile Speculations of poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:60638:84"/>
Writers, is nothing in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of what we ſee here actually perform'd; 'tis true, there have been Kings who have made themſelves and their Countriesvery Famous, for as much as they have given out that they were deſcended from Divine origin, or that their States were founded either by the ſpecial command of the Gods, or confirm'd by Miracles wrought in their favour, or elſe they have by their Heroick Actions procur'd their Deification, and made their Subjects adore them after their Death; but the Pope has been able to perſwade the people, that he is the true State-holder, and Vice-gerent of Jeſus Chriſt, who has all Power in Heaven and on Earth, and that too, to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in a much higher Sence, than when it is ſometimes ſaid of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Powers, that they are Earthly Gods; for he gives out, that he is the Diſpenſer of that Grace which is procur'd us by the Merits of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus Chriſt, and that he who does not acknowledge his Power, can have no hopes or pretence to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now there is nothing in the world
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:60638:85"/>
that can more attract the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found reſpect and veneration of men, than the Divine Majeſty; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, nothing more prevalent in the obliging them to obedience, and a blind ſubmiſſion to all ſort of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and charges, than the fear of God's wrath, and the damnation of their Souls; and when once the Pope can inſinuate the belief thereof into the Peoples minds, there needs no other demonſtration of all the other Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Faith, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Pope has ſaid it.</p>
               <p>Beſides, tho' moſt other Nations look upon hereditary Kingdoms to be the beſt and moſt ſecure; yet this ſort of Government does not ſquare with the Pope's Intereſts; for where the Crown deſcends from Father to Son, 'tis impoſſible but that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the <hi>minorities</hi> of Kings muſt happen, which would ſound very ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, that God's Vicar upon Earth ſhould ſometimes ride upon a Hobby-Horſe, and that the Monarch of all Chriſtendom, ſhould ſtand in need of a Tutor. Beſides, 'twould be very difficult for a young Prince to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:60638:85"/>
ſuch a Gravity as is abſolutely neceſſary in the acting of that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, nor was it to be hoped that all the Succeſſors and Poſterity of the Pope could have equal inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to ſuch an employ. In a word, the hereditary Right would have turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it into a bare temporal Kingdom, which could not have been long ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by ſo weak and unnatural a Title; not to add, that the Miniſters of State, and thoſe that enjoyed the chiefeſt Employs, would have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to turn out their Maſter, and put themſelves in his place, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they now contain themſelves in a very exact obedience, in hopes that they or theirs, may alſo by Election one day aſcend to this Supreme Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; to which, force can never give them any right. Laſtly, If this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy had been made hereditary, the extinction of the reigning Family would have caus'd horrible Debates about the Succeſſion, and perhaps at laſt, have over-turn'd the whole Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chine.</p>
               <p>They have farther found it to be the Intereſt of the Popedom, that this
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:60638:86"/>
Monarch ſhould lead a ſingle Life, which does very well agree with the Gravity of that Court, eſpecially whilſt a gawdy Attendance of young and airy Court-Ladies would have made an odd figure, and have been an ill example of a more than ordinary Piety and Devotion; 'twas likewiſe a piece of politick Hypocriſy, to ſeem to have ſo great an attachment to Heav'n as to be quite inſenſible to all fleſhly motions and deſires; nor was it eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to hoped, that a Man who had Wife and Children could defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from being debauch'd by them, and become more addicted to their particular Intereſts than to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good, ſince there is no conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or proſpect that can come in competition with that a man has for the welfare and proſperity of his Family, whereof one may find a very remarkable example in the natural Children of <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth, and <hi>Paul</hi> the third, to which we may add, that perhaps it was feared, leſt a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Prince becoming Maſter of the Eccleſiaſtick States ſhould make it hereditary in his Family, which, by
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:60638:86"/>
obliging them to celibacy, can never happen.</p>
               <p>The Conclave is likewiſe a good expedient to bridle the immoderate ambition of any Pope, and prevent thoſe Schiſms which heretofore did mightily weaken the Papal Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and to hinder the long <hi>interreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi>'s. And it is much more eaſy by the way of Election to find a perſon fit to exerciſe all the Cheats, Slights and Intrigues requir'd in ſuch a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and whom they may better perſwade the ignorant Vulgar, Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the Arts of the Conclave, to be, by an eſpecial Order of God, as the beſt and moſt capable, call'd to be his <hi>locum tenens,</hi> or Vicar on Earth. At leaſt by ſuch an Election they are able to find one that underſtands the Affairs of the World, and the Art of Governing, and who having laid aſide the Heats and Extravagancies of Youth by his Age and Experience, may ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der himſelf venerable. 'Tis alſo very politickly provided in the Election of the Pope, that two third parts of the Voices muſt concurr to the admiſſion of any one to this Dignity, to the end
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:60638:87"/>
that the Choice may not be diſpleaſing to a too great number of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals.</p>
               <p>In the Election of a Pope, the greateſt caution at preſent is, that he be not a <hi>Tranſalpine,</hi> that is, a Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigner of any Country beyond the <hi>Alps,</hi> but a Native of <hi>Italy,</hi> which does not alone happen upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their being more favourable and deſirous of transferring ſo great Honour and Profit on one of their own Country-men, rather than on a ſtranger; but chiefly, becauſe their preſervation and ſurety, depends on the keeping the balance equal betwixt <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> which <hi>equilibrium</hi> a <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Pope would quickly ruin, and by a too great partiality to his own Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, render himſelf hateful to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. They uſually chuſe an old man rather than young, that others may have ſome hopes of quickly attaining to the ſame Dignity, and that the Pope who governs, may not by a too long ſitting at the Helm, change the Maxims of State, nor transferr too much Power or Riches on his own Family, nor make ſo many Creatures
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:60638:87"/>
as to render the Popedom hereditary thereto. As to the reſt, the Vigour of youth is not in the leaſt neceſſary to the exerciſing all the Functions of this charge, for they are not requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to head an Army, or make any Campaigns, but only to ſet a grave and ſtarch'd face on the matter.</p>
               <p>The Conclave in the Election of the Pope, does likewiſe take care to chuſe ſuch a Succeſſor, that is not too nearly alli'd to him that preceded him, for fear that all the Eccleſiaſtical Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices ſhould fall into one Family; and to the end, that the ſucceeding Pope may more earneſtly redreſs thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes and grievances that have crept into the Government in his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor's time. Laſtly, They willingly make choice of ſuch a one as is not too much in the <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Intereſts, nor that is hated by either of thoſe Nations, as in effect, both thoſe Crowns do uſually propoſe him that they moſt deſire to be excluded from the Papal Dignity; but it often happens, that he who was leaſt thought on arrives to this Honour when the Cardinals are weary of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:60638:88"/>
and intriguing, and are glad with all their Heart to get out of the Conclave.</p>
               <p>It often happens alſo, that they find the ſame perſon, when poſſeſt of the Papal Chair, much different from what he was whilſt Cardinal. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, they do not preſcribe him any Conditions before he enters upon his Government, ſince it would not be handſome to tie up his Hands with Humane Laws and Ordinances, who is ſuppoſed to have ſo extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary a meaſure of the Holy Ghoſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies reſiding <hi>in ſcrinio pectoris:</hi> Yet the College of Cardinals is like a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Senate of the Eccleſiaſtical ſtate, whom the Pope conſults in all impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Affairs, though he and his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews don't alwaies follow their Counſel, but do what ſeems beſt in their own Eyes.</p>
               <p>The chiefeſt Privilege of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals is the power of chuſing a Pope, who muſt be one of them, and one that has liv'd long and is well vers'd in all the Affairs of the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> their uſual number is Seventy, tho' ſeldom compleat: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Eight
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:60638:88"/>
firſt gave them the Title of <hi>Eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimi,</hi> being only nam'd before <hi>Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſſimi,</hi> which Title grew very mean and common in <hi>Italy;</hi> but ſince the Cardinals have augmented their Titles, the Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> would ape them, and inſtead of being contented with <hi>Excellenza</hi>'s, as they were ordinarily ſtiled, they muſt now be call'd <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezza</hi>'s, or <hi>Their Highneſſes.</hi> The Election of the Cardinals is wholly in the power of the Pope, who has uſually regard therein to the Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of <hi>France, Spain,</hi> and other Potentates. The Flatterers of the Papal Chair are not aſham'd to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, That the Dignity of a Cardinal is equal to that of a King; at leaſt, they challenge the Precedence of the <hi>German Electors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Since the time of <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fourth, in the year 1471, the Popes have par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly endeavoured to enrich their Friends and Relations at the expence of the Church. As for example; <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fifth, in five years, left to his Family more than three millions of Ducats. <hi>Gregory</hi> the Fifteenth, in 27 Months time, more than three mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:60638:89"/>
of Crowns in Goods, beſides rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Money. The <hi>Barbarini,</hi> after the Death of <hi>Urban</hi> the Eighth, were left in poſſeſſion of 227 Charges and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, each amounting from three to five, eight and ten thouſand Crowns. So that the Riches of that Family were valued at about thirty millions of Crowns. And though a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were ſcandalized at this way of proceeding, yet if we rightly conſider it, 'tis not ſo blame-worthy; for ſince the whole Popedom is founded on the Riches and Authority of the Clergy, 'twould be great Imprudence in the Pope to ſtifle that natural Inclination he has to his own Family, and not to promote the Grandeur thereof, as long as it is in his power to do it; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more common, than to ſee Favourites, and ſuch as Fortune ſmiles on, envied by thoſe who are only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of the ſame condition. But for the reſt, 'tis certain that the Popes would not know what to do with their Money, without that way of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing it, ſince the Charges of their Militia is very inconſiderable. Since the time of <hi>Urban</hi> the Eighth it has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:60638:89"/>
been the Cuſtom to make one of the Pope's Nephews chief Miniſter of State under the Title of Cardinal <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troon.</hi> Amongſt the Motives that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the Pope to intruſt his Nephew with the ſole Management of his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, theſe are the moſt weighty: Firſt, becauſe nothing is more natural than to ſeek the Advantage and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment of ours, before that of any other; and ſecondly, becauſe the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Pope is thereby much more ſecure, which is otherwiſe expos'd to far greater dangers than that of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Princes is, whoſe death their Succeſſors are wont to revenge; and we may from hence gueſs how much the Popes ſtand in fear of being poiſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, foraſmuch as the Chaplain, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Pope communicates, muſt taſte both of the Bread and Wine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he gives it his Maſter.</p>
               <p>The Government of the Pope's Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews has yet this farther advantage, That the other Governours and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of State, who were us'd to heap up great Riches by an impudent and ſcandalous Sale of Offices, and by the ſupplanting of each other, were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:60638:90"/>
kept in greater awe and modeſty: Beſides, the Nephews being inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as to their number, are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more eaſily ſatisfy'd. Nor will they let the other Officers ſqueeze and oppreſs the Subject, whilſt all the Hate muſt fall upon them. They are alſo more neceſſary to the Pope, becauſe by them he is more truly and exactly inform'd of the Intereſts of the Princes, than he is by his ordinary Miniſters, who are not ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to the Pope's Service as are his Nephews, whoſe Intereſt it is likewiſe to take good care for the Government, for fear leſt they ſhould be one day call'd to an account: And 'tis upon that account that they more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly endeavour to oblige one Prince, who in caſe of need may yield them a ſecure Refuge. In a word, by their means the Pope's Secrets are better kept; and it is moſt certain, that without them he muſt be oblig'd to depend on the Cardinals, who are moſtly partial, receiving Penſions and Benefices at the hands of other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:60638:90"/>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 32. The Subjects of this Spiritual Monarchy may be divided into two Claſſes: Under the firſt we comprehend the Clergy; under the ſecond all other Chriſtians that make Profeſſion of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, whom they commonly name the Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The firſt of theſe we may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to the ſtanding Forces of any Princes, who having made great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, does thereby maintain them, and keep the conquered from ſhaking off their Yoke. The others are poor Tributary Slaves, doom'd to maintain ſo great a Militia at their own Expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The firſt are ſingular in this, That they are obliged to abſtain from Marriage, which they pretend is upon the account of a more particular Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and that they may uninterru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptedly addict themſelves to the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the Charge: But the true rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, That they may not be embaraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the care of Wife and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to the prejudice of the Church's Intereſt, or oblig'd to ſide with the Prince under whoſe Dominion they live; nor cheat the Church of its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, to ſupply the neceſſities of their
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:60638:91"/>
Families; but that they may devote themſelves wholly to the Pope, and yield him a blind Obedience, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his Orders againſt all, but more eſpecially againſt the Princes whoſe Subjects they are, whoſe Anger they dread the leſs, becauſe they are not joined or united to the Republick by ſo ſtreight Bands as the reſt are, and have but one body to take care for; whereas a Wife and Children are look'd upon to be the greateſt and deareſt Pawns of our Fidelity; but a ſingle man can eaſily get his Bread in any Country. In fine, the Pope en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours by all ſort of waies to free them from the Dependance and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of their lawful Soveraigns, to ſubject them entirely to his own.</p>
               <p>The Clergy alſo could never have ſatisfy'd their Avarice with ſo rich a Harveſt, had they been oblig'd to have ſcrap'd up for their Wives and Children; nor ſo fair a Pretext of begging for the Church, and not for themſelves: But in the mean while thoſe that firſt introduced Coelibacy or a ſingle Life among the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Clergy, were wonderfully overſeen,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:60638:91"/>
in not finding out at the ſame time a fit Receipt for the Gift of Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency, which had been very ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. We may gueſs at the multitude of the Clergy, by the computation which <hi>Paul</hi> the Fourth is ſaid to make thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> That he had under his Juriſdiction Two hundred and eighty eight thouſand Pariſhes, and forty four thouſand Cloiſters, eſpecially if that of the Convents be juſt.</p>
               <p>We may again divide the Clergy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe that are ſimply Prieſts, and thoſe that have made particular vows, as the Monks and Jeſuites, which may paſs for the Pope's Life Guard: The pay of theſe Troops conſiſts in honourable Charges, great Revenues, an eaſie Labour, idle daies, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Kitchin; but thoſe that are kept more ſtrict, have their Heads fill'd with a particular Holineſs and Merits and Advantages above the reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 33. The means which the Pope makes uſe of to keep the Laity in ſubjection, are the accuſtoming them to a belief, that he and his Ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Militia are the Promoters of their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:60638:92"/>
and the Lords of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, which is the ſtrongeſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the World to lead them into a perpetual Slavery and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to their Wills; but that it may be more ſerviceable to their Spiritual Monarchy, they have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated thereto ſome of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Chriſtian Religion, and ſince made ſome additions of others tending to the ſame end. So that if you take good notice of the Diſputes and Conteſtations which they of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion have with their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, you will alwaies find ſome Intereſt mingled therewith, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Authority, Power, or Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of the Clergy: The chiefeſt of theſe Doctrines is concerning the Power and Authority of the Pope, of his Superiority over the Councils, and of his Infallibility; which laſt point the Jeſuites have ſtretch'd as far as poſſible; for that being once granted, all the reſt is an eaſie and natural conſequence thereof. But the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Ancient Chriſtians, with whom (if I am not miſtaken) the <hi>Sorbon</hi> at preſent holds; <hi>viz.</hi> That
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:60638:92"/>
the Councils are at leaſt equal if not above the Popes, are directly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the grounds of the Papal State; for this Opinion once ſtiffly maintain'd, would deſtroy the Monarchy, and on its Ruins erect a Democracy; and in effect, to grant the Pope ſuch almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Prerogatives, and yet ſubject him to his Creatures and Vaſſals, are things incompatible, and inconſiſtent with one another: For that which the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Writings of the Fathers have attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the Church, muſt be only underſtood of the Pope, juſt as in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Diſcourſe we aſcribe that to a whole Kingdom, which is done by the King alone.</p>
               <p>The reading of the Holy Scriptures is forbid the Laity, and only permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Clergy; which does not alone contribute to the Grandeur of the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> as if they were the only perſons worthy to approach the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Oracles, but does alſo more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly hinder the Laity from finding any thing contrary to the Intereſts of the Clergy, and becoming too wiſe, and refuſing any longer blindly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Fables of their lying Prieſts.
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:60638:93"/>
So that the Laity not being permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſearch into Matters of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, nor to examin them ſeriouſly, are oblig'd to referr themſelves wholly to their <hi>Prieſts.</hi> Hence is it that they appropriate to the <hi>Pope</hi> the Right of interpreting the Scriptures, and of giving an abſolute deciſion of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted points, to the end that none may be alledg'd that are prejudicial to his Intereſts.</p>
               <p>They give out too, That the Scriptures are imperfect, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be ſupply'd by Traditions, to the end, that when they would preach up any Doctrine advantageous to the Holy Chair, of which there is not the leaſt tittle to be found in the Scripture, they may appeal to Tradition, and ſo ſpare themſelves any farther de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration.</p>
               <p>In the Doctrine of ſins they have a diſtinction betwixt venial and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſins, as alſo of particular caſes and exceptions, all which does only tend to the profit and advantage of the Prieſts; and all that infinite number of Books of Confeſſion, enough to lade a whole <hi>Eaſt-India-Fleet,</hi> are not
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:60638:93"/>
writ for the amendment of ſins; but to the end, that by the Taxes therein contain'd the Dominion of the Clergy may be confirm'd, and their avarice ſatiated.</p>
               <p>The comfortable Doctrine of the Remiſſion of Sins, is intirely accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated to their Intereſt; for whilſt it is no advantage to the Clergy, that a truly penitent ſinner ſhould obtain remiſſion of his ſins by the confidence he has in the merits of Chriſt alone; therefore they teach, that to the attainment of a full and perfect forgiveneſs of ſins, a man muſt reveal even the leaſt particulars of all and every ſin to the Prieſt, whereby they do not only make the people to be at their Devotion, and give them ſuch impreſſions as are moſt conformable to their Intereſts, but they do more particularly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, diſcover all the ſecrets and deſigns of Families, and the humor and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations of the people, and by that means, have the beſt intelligence of all that is done, tho' they are forbid to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal what is imparted to them at Confeſſions; for without that caution
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:60638:94"/>
of ſecreſy, they could never have been able to have eſtabliſh'd a thing ſo contrary, and ſo ungrateful to humane nature.</p>
               <p>They promote alſo the works of Satisfaction according as the Father-Confeſſor ſhall find convenient to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them; now theſe bring no ſmall profit to them; for tho' the impos'd pennance moſtly conſiſts in Prayers, Pilgrimages, Faſtings, Whippings and ſuch like; yet the rich are always condemned to ſome <hi>pecuniary</hi> mulct, which muſt be converted to the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Convents, Churches, and the Poor, under which they compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the <hi>Begging Friars,</hi> who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them themſelves <hi>minimos Fratrum,</hi> according to the fifteenth of St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> that their bag might be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fill'd: Now this interpretation of the Scripture, has burthened Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom with more than an hundred thouſand idle Bellies.</p>
               <p>Beſides, The firſt ſort of Penitence may eaſily be redeem'd by Money, if they on whom 'tis impos'd, ſhould find it too grievous; and in effect, What rich man is there, that would
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:60638:94"/>
not ſhew himſelf reſpectful and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral to his Holy Father, that he may be merciful to him, and make his pennance more light and eaſy? 'Tis no hard matter to gueſs, why good works are reckoned amongſt the means of obtaining Salvation, for as ſoon as they proceeded to give the definition of good works, they placed in the firſt rank, all Gifts and Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities beſtow'd on the Clergy, Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Convents, and other acts introduc'd by the Pope and his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures out of a principle of Hypocriſy, and Superſtition; to which they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this Doctrine, That the Monks and Friars could not only ſatisfy for their own ſins, but that they had alſo an inexhauſtible ſtock of Supererroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Merits remaining to be beſtow'd for the uſe and ſervice of the ſinful Laity; from which Superfluity they have erected a Magazine of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly profitable Merchandice, which coſt them nothing either to ſtow, or keep, which neither grows mouldy nor muſty by length of time, which never diminiſhes; and which in a word, cannot be reſtor'd by the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:60638:95"/>
tho' he ſhould afterwards chance to diſcover the inſignificancy and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitableneſs thereof. They have likewiſe burthen'd the exerciſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion with ſo many unneceſſary Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, Holy-Days, and ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Proceſſions, built ſo many uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Churches, Chapels and Altars, only that the ſwarming drones of the Clergy may have juſt ſomething to do, and not ſeem to be always and wholly idle, and to the end, that they may ſtill get a little by theſe and the like Fopperies.</p>
               <p>This is likewiſe the reaſon of their multiplying the Sacraments to the number of ſeven, ſince the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of each one brings in griſt to the Prieſt's Mill: They have intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd the Maſs without Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants, baptizing it a Sacrifice for the Living and for the Dead; to the end, that the Dead as well as the Living, may be put under Contributions: Beſides, nothing of Importance is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in hand by a pious Catholick, till he has made a Maſs be ſaid for his good ſucceſs. There is no Man of Quality, that dies without order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:60638:95"/>
a good number of Maſſes to be ſaid for his Soul, for which the Prieſt muſt be well greas'd in the Fiſt. It happen'd once by chance or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſs, that the Cup was not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred to the Laity, afterwards it became a Law; and tho' the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of Chriſt and the practice of the Church for ſeveral hundred Years together, was directly contrary to this encroachment; yet they obſtinately perſiſted therein, leſt it might be ſaid, the Church has err'd, and that the Clergy might enjoy a Prerogative a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Laity; nay, ſo far their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence proceeded, that as if they deſign'd to mock both GOD and Man, they give the Laity the unbleſt Cup, which in a ſcornful manner they name the Waſhing Cup, as if they had eaten ſome unclean thing, and muſt waſh their Mouths after it. Marriage muſt be turn'd into a Sacrament, tho' it ſeem never ſo abſurd and ridiculous, that the Clergy alone may take cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of all Affairs thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing, which being almoſt innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable, are very profitable to them; and of no leſs conſequence, for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:60638:96"/>
depend the Eſtates, Inheritances, and Succeſſions not only of private Perſons, but many times of Kingdoms alſo; hence it was that <hi>Mary</hi> the firſt, Queen of <hi>England,</hi> found herſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to re-eſtabliſh Popery in her Kingdom, whilſt without the Pope's Authority, ſhe could never have paſt for Legitimate; thus <hi>Philip</hi> the third, King of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſaw himſelf indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſably engag'd to eſpouſe the Pope's Intereſt, becauſe amongſt other obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, it was not the leaſt that he permitted him to be born of his Father's Siſter's Daughter, which could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have receiv'd a Diſpenſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>Now the ſame Religion that ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples not to diſpenſe with the neareſt Bonds of Conſanguinity, has intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd an endleſs Roll of forbidden De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and likewiſe forg'd a new ſort of ſpiritual Affinity. Why? To afford the Prieſts a more frequent occaſion of Diſpenſations, which brings in an ineſtimable Revenue. In the extream Unctions, the Clergy have found out a very proper expedient of giving the dying perſon a friendly admonition
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:60638:96"/>
to make ſome pious Legacies, all which tends to their profit.</p>
               <p>Nor is there any other deſign in the Fiction of Purgatory, than to wheedle thoſe that are juſt departing (and who then little value the goods they muſt leave to others) to give a good part thereof to the Clergy, to the end that by their Prayers and Maſſes they may the ſooner get out of a place ſo terribly hot and thirſty. The adoration likewiſe of Relicks, does not make the leaſt part of the Clergy's Revenue, for with an old rotten knuckle-bone, they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the greateſt Services that the Pope's moſt faithful Creatures ſhall have rendred to him. The Invocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints has furniſh'd them with a very fair and ſpecious pretext of building ſo many the more Churches, of Inſtituting more Holy-Days, of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding more Prieſts to officiate, and of extorting more Money from the Laity to maintain them. Beſides, the Canonization of Saints which depends on the Pope's breath, does contract a greater reſpect and admiration of his power, as if he could diſpoſe of
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:60638:97"/>
Charges and Offices in Heaven, and that God Almighty were oblig'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive all the Candidates the Pope ſhould preſent him, by which means he can diſpoſe of the wills of other Princes Subjects offering ſo conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a Reward to their Ambition and Credulity, on condition that they will maintain his Intereſts to the very laſt. To which we may add, That ſince Superſtition has got the upper hand, none but Eccleſiaſticks have been admitted into the number of Saints, and eſpecially ſuch of them, who by ſome rare Maſter-piece of Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy, and a falſe and affected Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, have render'd themſelves Famous o'er the World. And if this Honour has at any time been granted to a Secular Perſon, either he, or thoſe that ſollicited it for him, muſt have merited it by no common Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices.</p>
               <p>As to the reſt, I ſhall not trouble my ſelf to particularize how the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy have cheated poor ſimple people of their Money, by the invention of Miracles, Images, Apparitions, Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſms, Indulgences, <hi>Jubilee-Years,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:60638:97"/>
Meats, and a thouſand ſuch like Tricks and Devices.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 34. After theſe means the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities have not a little Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the eſtabliſhment of the Pope's Authority, which have been ſounded partly by the Pope, and partly by other Princes; yet after ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that moſt of 'em muſt receive their Confirmation from <hi>Rome;</hi> and the Pope has arrogated to himſelf the chief management of them, and the conſequences of ſuch a Polity are plain enough, whilſt the Profeſſors, who are all the Pope's Creatures do not only eſtabliſh the opinions of <hi>Rome</hi> during their Life, but do likewiſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate them, by leaving ſuch Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors as are debauch'd and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, with the ſame Doctrine.</p>
               <p>Hence is it, that the Academies and the Studies exercis'd therein have been accommodated, as much as poſſible, to the Pope's Intereſts: So that the Profeſſors of Divinity (who challenge the firſt rank in the Univerſity) were not alone the Pope's Creatures, but the Profeſſors alſo of the Canon-Law were very zealous in defence of
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:60638:98"/>
the Pope's Authority, and mingled his Decrees that he had forced upon <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> with the Chicane of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Proceſſes; for 'tis the Canon-Law that has caus'd that tediouſneſs of Law-Suits, ſince the Clergy have uſurp'd ſo great a Jurisdiction, the better to ſatiate their eternal Avarice with the Bribes and Preſents which both Parties fee their Advocates with. The moſt part of the Philoſophers were alſo the Pope's Partizans, ſo that no one of 'em durſt examine the buſineſs ſeriouſly for fear of being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd by the others: Beſides, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity and Philoſophy which was taught in the Schools, was not taught with the deſign of rendering the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors more knowing and learned, but that they might amuſe and blunt the more penetrating Wits with a parcel of ſilly, non-ſenſical terms, and by that means be hindered from acquiring a fundamental knowledge of thoſe things which might enable them clearly to diſcover the Papal Cheats. Their School-Divinity did not conſiſt in the ſearch and interpretation of the Holy Scriptures, but moſtly in the deciſion
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:60638:98"/>
of unprofitable queſtions propos'd by <hi>Peter Lombard, Thomas Aquinas, Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> and other ſuch Patriarchs of ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Pedantry. That likewiſe which they name <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> is nothing elſe but ridiculous Chymerical Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons conſiſting of barbarous Latin, and inexplicable terms, the underſtanding of which was more prejudicial than profitable to the young Students: So that all knowledge conſiſted in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing rightly.</p>
               <p>And they have had the confidence to teach theſe Bagatels and idle Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations not only in barbarous igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant times, but even at this preſent, that all Arts and Sciences are in their Meridian, is that leaven ſpread abroad, and propagated with all the induſtry and cunning imaginable: On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, good and ſolid Sciences are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd, and eſpecially ſuch as ſerve to open our Eyes in humane affairs, as chiefly the ſo neceſſary Doctrine of Morals, which is quite ſpoil'd by them, and turned into a Labyrinth, out of which it is impoſſible to diſentangle ones ſelf, which they make uſe of to enſnare People, and load their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:60638:99"/>
with ſo many doubts and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties, that being no longer able to regulate their Actions by clear and evident Principles, they muſt let them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves be guided by the Will of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted Confeſſor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 35. But becauſe it was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, that in <hi>Luther</hi>'s time the ſtudy of Letters did not a little diminiſh the Pope's Authority, the Jeſuites being the faithful Guards of the Papal Chair, did afterwards take upon them the management of all Schools and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges; but not content therewith, uſurp'd likewiſe the Inſtruction of little Children, to the end that they might ſo form their Studies, as not only not to prejudice the Kingdom of Darkneſs, but rather to promote and advance the Intereſt thereof. And indeed the Education of Children has not only enrich'd their Society, and brought it into great credit, but is alſo a mighty prop to the Papal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, to which they are more devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted than all the other Orders, for thereby they inſpire the tender and flexible Youth with Sentiments of an extraordinary reſpect and veneration
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:60638:99"/>
for the Pope, as alſo with any other Inclinations that may render them ſerviceable to their Intereſts, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore accuſtom them from their Youth to an obſtinate perſiſtance in the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions which they have once embraced, and a reſolution of never yielding to contrary Reaſons, ſo that they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of ever attaining to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth. The Jeſuites al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo learn from thence the Conſtancy and Affections of their Scholars, of which knowledge they ſerve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves very efficaciouſly, when theſe come to be employ'd in State affairs; but thoſe that are dear to them either on the account of their Wit or Riches, they moſt induſtriouſly endeavour to draw into their own Order, by which means the famous Diſcipline of their Schools only tends to the ſupporting of the Pope's Authority; and though they are fam'd for an excellent me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of teaching Children Latin, yet they are very cautious of rendering their Scholars too learned, unleſs they are deſtin'd to their Order.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:60638:100"/>
Beſides that, as the Jeſuites, by the Government of Colleges have had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to draw into their Society a great many learned men, and that in their Converſation and way of living they are extreamly civil and polite, differing much from the courſeneſs and rebutting Pedantry of the other Monks; under the pretence of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, they have inſinuated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into moſt of the Courts of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> and by cunningly arrogating to themſelves Intrigues of State, they ſway the Councils of Princes, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them to their own advantages, which as they are inſeparably annext to the Pope's, ſo is his never forgot by them. Yet nevertheleſs, in ſome places they have made themſelves ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly odious, by their inſatiable Avarice, and earneſtneſs of interpoſing in all ſort of matters. And they are no leſs envied by the old Orders of Monks, as having much encroach'd on their Rights and Authority. One of the means which are alſo us'd to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Grandeur of the Chair of <hi>Rome,</hi> is the Power which the Pope and his Creatures have attributed to
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:60638:100"/>
themſelves, of cenſuring all Books, ſo that nothing may appear in print that is contrary to their Intereſts; which Cenſure they uſe with ſo much raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and impudence, that they do not only retrench what they diſlike in old Authors when they are reprinted, but they have the confidence to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert whole paſſages, which may be ſerviceable to their deſigns.</p>
               <p>If any new piece happen to be written and printed in the Pope's Territories, 'tis preſently taken into a ſtrict examination, and whatſoever has ſlipt in that is contrary to their Intereſts, 'tis put into the <hi>Index ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgatorius,</hi> that in the ſecond Edition it may be quite omitted: But the Books that are written by their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, are abſolutely forbid to be introduced into their Country: Nor may any man read them without a ſpecial permiſſion, or ſuch alone as are ſo much prejudiced againſt them that they do not fear will be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd. So that by this means they may brand their Adverſaries, and blacken them as they pleaſe, ſince it is not allowed their people to read
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:60638:101"/>
either their Writings or Refutations. Beſides, ſome have obſerv'd, that the ſcandalous Lives of the <hi>Popes</hi> having been extreamly prejudicial to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Religion, becauſe they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to all the World by the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> they do now endeavour to retort the ſame Reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches on the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> not only by declaring the Faults and Overſights of ſome few particulars, but by char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them with the moſt ſcandalous Vices, and deſiring them afterwards to prove the contrary; whereby they prepoſſeſs their Followers with notions extreamly diſadvantageous to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They have likewiſe Impudence enough to cry up the Miracles and Exploits of their Martyrs, done in very remote Countries, by which they acquire a great credit, at leaſt with the more ſimple ſort of people: Which Trick of theirs, amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, is exactly remarked by <hi>Edwin Sands</hi> an Engliſh Gentleman, in his <hi>View of the Religions of</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:60638:101"/>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 36. But there are yet more violent ways which the Pope uſes to ſupport the Majeſty of his Character, amongſt which the chiefeſt was that terrible Ban or Excommunication, whereby whole Countries have been forbidden the exerciſe of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and Kings and Emperors have been forced to truckle to the Mitre; but now a-days theſe Arms are no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſo dreadful as they were hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, unleſs it be to ſome of the petty Princes in <hi>Italy:</hi> But in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> they have erected a ſingular Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal, which they chriſten <hi>Officium Sanctae Inquiſitionis,</hi> wherein they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire and proceed againſt ſuch as are any ways ſuſpected of Hereſie; the worſt of which is that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys the Credit, Doctrine, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the Pope: By which means the people are kept in an intolerable Slavery: And the Peſt is not ſo dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Inhabitants of thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, as is this ſort of Juſtice, which is ſo rigorouſly put in execution, that he who falls into the Inquiſitor's hands, ſhall not eſcape without the loſs of a great many Feathers.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:60638:102"/>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 37. Now, though the Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Adminiſtration of the <hi>Popiſh Religion,</hi> together with other means which we have already ſhown, are ſufficient to keep the People in the Bounds of their Duty, eſpecially ſince the <hi>Romiſh Clergy</hi> do ſo well manage the buſineſs, that they can content every one; and that moſt of thoſe that live under the Pope's Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, credulouſly ſwallow for great Truths all that their Prieſts tell them; nor have they any opportunity of knowing the contrary: Yet I really believe, that the moſt politick and learned among them plainly ſee how matters go, and would never conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue under ſo ridiculous and intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Yoke, without a great many worldly Proſpects; and if I may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce my Judgment in the caſe, I fanſie, that moſt of 'em are kept back from declaring againſt it, becauſe they are unable to oppoſe it alone; nor are they willing to ruine a good Fortune, which they enjoy amongſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and to go over to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, where they are to expect no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Poverty and Contempt,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:60638:102"/>
which is too ſharp a trial of their Faith, and therefore they think it is enough if they believe in Jeſus Chriſt and his Merits, and that thereby a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone they ſhall be ſaved. And as for the other Opinions which are the <hi>additamenta religionis,</hi> they yield an external compliance to them, but think they may believe as much of them as they pleaſe: Whether the common people and Women, who are uſually delighted with ſtrange and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible things, believe them in good earneſt, or not, is of no great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: Beſides, there are, without doubt, a great many that are not able to diſtinguiſh what there is of Divine in their Religion, and what the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy for their own Intereſts have added; therefore if they happen to diſcover the Impoſtures of the laſt, they look upon all the reſt as a meer Fable, but are forced to conceal their Atheiſm from the World, for fear of bringing themſelves into trouble. And let any wiſe man judge how eaſily an <hi>Italian</hi> or <hi>Spaniard,</hi> that has never read the Bible, nor any good Proteſtant Book, may fall into ſuch impious Thoughts
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:60638:103"/>
ſo ſoon as he begins to diſcover the Cheats of his Clergy. 'Tis likewiſe certain, that ſince <hi>Luther</hi>'s time, the Popedom has put on another face, and does proceed much more cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly than heretofore.</p>
               <p>Beſides, there are a great number of People, of all Conditions, that find their Advantage in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, either by entring into ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Orders of Knights, or but putting themſelves into Convents, which is oftentimes a great eaſe, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the aggrandizing of a whole Family; and at the leaſt, the ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Parents are very well contented therewith, and think they merit not a little, by an early dedication of their Children to God. In fine, ſuch as can't make their Fortune in the World, have no more to do, than to caſt themſelves into a Cloiſter, and there they are provided for all their life; which Advantage they could not enjoy, if the Papacy ſhould be exterminated, and the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Goods confiſcated to the State. The Popiſh Doctrin is alſo ſo <hi>deeply</hi> rooted in thoſe Countries where it
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:60638:103"/>
does at preſent reign, that if any ſhould undertake to aboliſh it, he could never attain his ends, whilſt the Prieſts would not fail to move Heaven and Earth againſt him, or find a <hi>Clement</hi> or <hi>Ravaillac</hi> to ſhorten his days; but moſt of the Princes find it their Intereſt to maintain the eſtabliſh'd Religion; or at leaſt, they find no profit, but rather a great deal of danger in beginning a change.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 38. But <hi>Italy</hi> eſpecially, has no ſmall Advantage in maintaining the Papal Dignity, becauſe that Land is become very conſiderable by the continual Reſidence of the Pope, and by that Prerogative it has, that the Pope muſt always be an <hi>Italian,</hi> and becauſe there is no Noble Family in all <hi>Italy</hi> that does not receive ſome profit from the Pope.</p>
               <p>As in <hi>Poland,</hi> the Biſhopricks and richeſt Prebendaries, are poſſeſſed by the Nobility of that Country, who there enjoy likewiſe the Soveraign Power; they have great Intereſt in the Popedom, ſince the Biſhops as Senators of the Kingdom, are there
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:60638:104"/>
in great Credit. In <hi>Portugal,</hi> the Clergy is alſo very Powerful, and would eaſily embrace the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, if their Prince ſhould go about to make any Innovation in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and therefore we have ſeen in this laſt Age, that the <hi>Portugueze</hi> have not dar'd to mutter againſt the Pope, tho' he in favour of <hi>Spain</hi> has us'd 'em very ſcurvily about the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of New Biſhopricks, and given them reaſon enough to ſlip their Necks out of ſo uneaſy a collar. In <hi>Germany,</hi> ſeveral of the States of the Empire ſtick cloſe to the exerciſe of the Popiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and amongſt the Imperial Cities, <hi>Collen,</hi> as well as ſome other of leſs Importance, ſwarms with idle Prieſts and Monks; and amongſt the Counts, and Orders of Knighthood, all ſuch as have any proſpect of attaining to Eccleſiaſtical Charges and Benefices; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the temporal Princes the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> has always perſiſted obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately in his Religion, in hopes of aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one day to the Imperial Dignity, of which he would be totally fruſtrated, if he ſhould abandon the Pope's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt;
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:60638:104"/>
and why ſome Proteſtant Princes have return'd unto the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Yoke is, I think, very well known. That the Biſhops and Prelates of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> are ſo good Catholicks is no wonder, becauſe 'tis a much ſweeter and agreeable Life, to be a rich Prince, than a poor Preacher. Beſides, they are deterred from any thoughts of change by the example of two Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of <hi>Collen,</hi> whoſe deſigns were very unhappy and fatal to them.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth's time, <hi>Spain</hi> by its Intrigues, impeded the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of the Reformation, and ſince the loſs of ſo fair an opportunity, the Emperor <hi>par raiſon d'etat,</hi> cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon the Pope's Intereſts, tho' he ſhould deſire to do it; and the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Princes are forced to hold with him, that they may have a ſupport againſt the temporal ones; but if the Emperor ſhould really deſign to leave the Pope, 'tis moſt certain, that he would firſt have all the Clergy upon his back, nor could he be aſſur'd, that the Temporal Princes would ſtand by him, eſpecially, whilſt the Princes
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:60638:105"/>
of the moſt Ancient and Noble Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, whoſe Religion is the only Bar of their Pretences to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, might then with as much right aſpire to it as any, and openly rival the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> the Pope too, would move Heaven and Earth againſt the accompliſhment of a deſign ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and pernicious to his Dignity; nor would the <hi>French</hi> King let ſlip ſo good an occaſion of advancing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Imperial Dignity, to which in ſuch a juncture the Clergy would not fail to invite him.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> would paſs for the moſt zealous Defenders of the Holy Chair, but the true reaſon is, becauſe the Pope's Favour and Protection is abſolutely neceſſary to the peaceable maintenance of their Kingdom of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> and Dutchy of <hi>Milan;</hi> and thus we ſee them uſually cloak their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes with the pretext of defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and propagating the Catholick Religion, but unſucceſsfully for the moſt part; I will not ſpeak here of the intolerable Greatneſs of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Clergy, nor of the ſtrange things
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:60638:105"/>
which they make the people believe, are contain'd in the Doctrine of the Proteſtants. <hi>France</hi> does not out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly appear ſo paſſionately to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſe the Intereſts of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor have the Popes been able to perſwade the <hi>French</hi> Church to ſo abſolute and ſlaviſh a ſubmiſſion as moſt other Churches have yielded them, ſo that when they endeavour'd to infringe or encroach upon their privileges; the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> did preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take Cognizance of the Affair, and the <hi>Sorbon</hi> has likewiſe often rejected ſeveral unreaſonable Propoſitions ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced by the Flatterers and Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants of the Pope; they likewiſe ſpy the <hi>Nuncio</hi>'s Conduct, and will not allow him too great a liberty, who when he comes out of <hi>Rome,</hi> bears his <hi>Croſier</hi> erected, but ſo ſoon as he Arrives on the <hi>French</hi> Frontiers, he carries it <hi>Reverſed,</hi> till he obtains leave from the King to exerciſe his Function, and then too, they are forced to promiſe him, that they will uſe it no longer, nor no otherwiſe than he ſhall think fit. Beſides, they are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:60638:106"/>
to make uſe of <hi>French</hi> Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, and when they go away, to leave a Roll of their Negotiations, and their Seal behind them, and to uſe ſeveral other ſuch Formalities, without which all their Proceedings would be <hi>null</hi> and void of effect; ſo that the <hi>French</hi> ſay, the Pope's <hi>Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio</hi> receives his Commiſſion as well from the King as the Pope, and that it is <hi>Precaria &amp; ad Nutum Regis revocabilis;</hi> hence it is, that the <hi>Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio</hi> lays aſide his <hi>Croſier,</hi> if he hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to come where the King is, as if his Juriſdiction were diſſolv'd by the Preſence of the King. Nay, in <hi>Richlieu</hi>'s time 'twas debated of, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no they ſhould make a Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch in <hi>France;</hi> which deſign tho', in my opinion, could not have been very advantageous for <hi>France,</hi> for the Clergy would never have been brought to conſent thereto, having reaſon enough to fear, leſt the King upon ſuch an occaſion ſhould conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably retrench their fat Revenues. Beſides, if the <hi>French</hi> King ſhould ever have any thoughts of aſpiring to
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:60638:106"/>
the Empire, his ſeparation from <hi>Rome</hi> would be very diſſerviceable to him; for ſhould ſo powerful a Prince as the <hi>French</hi> King is, become Maſter of the Empire, he would not only revive the pretences of the ancient Emperors which are now, as 'twere, buried in oblivion, of which moſt depend on <hi>Rome,</hi> but alſo the Defence of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church would be a very ſpecious pretext of claiming ſeveral rights and privileges which the Popes have ſuffer'd to be loſt. On the contrary, the Pope has a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble averſion and fear of the <hi>French</hi> Monarchy; ſince it is not to be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but upon ſuch an occaſion, <hi>France</hi> would make a great Reformation in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and bridle the Pope's Authority ſo much, that he would ſignify no more than a ſimple Patriarch; and he muſt attend the ſame fate if <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould aſpire to the Univerſal Monarchy; in the mean while, it would go very ill with the Proteſtants; and from hence we may conclude, that the greateſt Support of the Papal Chair is the Jealouſy
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:60638:107"/>
and <hi>Aequilibrium</hi> which <hi>Rome</hi> wiſely maintains between the two Crowns of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and therefore 'tis the neareſt and deareſt of the Pope's Intereſt to hinder any one of thoſe Kingdoms from trampling on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or aſpiring to the univerſal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy of <hi>Europe;</hi> which alſo is eaſy to be obſerved from the Pope's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct for ſeveral Ages; for when <hi>France</hi> was extreamly low and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned after the Death of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, the Pope was forc'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare himſelf for the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Intereſts, to which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were reſolv'd to oblige him, both by fair means and by foul. They gain'd the Pope's Nephews, who were glad to enrich themſelves during the ſhort Life of their Uncle, and willingly devoted themſelves to <hi>Spain,</hi> whilſt they could receive large Penſions, Benefices, and conſiderable Charges; and in caſe they did not render themſelves very ſerviceable to thoſe from whom they receiv'd pay, they were ſure to be cruelly perſecuted after their Unckle's Death; they alſo us'd all their efforts
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:60638:107"/>
to exclude from the Succeſſion, any Cardinal that they ſuſpected to be enclining to their Adverſaries Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts: but ſo ſoon as <hi>France</hi> began to lift up its head again, the Popes reſumed their former Indifference and Liberty, and would ſhew themſelves no more favourable to either party, than as they were ſerviceable and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to the Papal Intereſt; and therefore <hi>Guichard</hi> declar'd publickly in a Sermon at <hi>Paris,</hi> in the Month of <hi>July,</hi> 1637. that the War which <hi>France</hi> made then againſt <hi>Spain,</hi> was a Holy War, and in Defence of the Religion; for had not the <hi>French</hi> King made uſe of that means to bring <hi>Spain</hi> to reaſon, the King of <hi>Spain</hi> would certainly have placed his <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner</hi> in the Holy Chair.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 39. As for thoſe that have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted from the Pope, tho' he would not be ſorry to find them reduc'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain under his Juriſdiction, yet he does not deſire, that by their ruins any Prince ſhould become ſo great as to render himſelf formidable to all <hi>Europe,</hi> for 'tis better to give my
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:60638:108"/>
Enemy his Life, than to ſeek to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive him of it at the coſt of my own; thus we ſee how great fears and jealouſies the Victorious Progreſs of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth's Arms againſt the Proteſtants, occaſion'd at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſince it oblig'd Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the third to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call thoſe Troups which he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin'd to the Emperor's Service; and had <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond ſubdu'd <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, Sixtus</hi> the fifth would too late have repented his raſh promoting that Catholick Deſign. So <hi>Gregory</hi> the fifteenth in the War of the <hi>Valteline,</hi> ſided with the <hi>Griſons</hi> againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> tho' the firſt were of the Reform'd Religion; nor was <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth, diſpleas'd to ſee the Houſe of <hi>Austria</hi> mortifi'd by <hi>Guſtavus Adol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> King of <hi>Suedeland,</hi> becauſe the Emperor in the buſineſs of <hi>Mantua,</hi> had ſhown as little mercy to the Catholicks, as before to the Proteſtants; and 'tis ſaid, that when <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond deſir'd a ſum of Money, which the ſame Pope had promiſed him, inſtead thereof, he ſent him and his Army a plenary Indulgence
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:60638:108"/>
at the hour of Death, that they might with greater confidence expoſe themſelves to all dangers.</p>
               <p>Nor was the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> leſs apprehenſive ſome years ago, when the <hi>French</hi> King made ſo great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſes in the United Provinces, that the ruin of the Republick, ſeem'd inevitable. But tho' the Pope does not deſire the weakning of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant party by which rough means, yet it cannot be denied that he uſes all ſort of ſlights and devices to allure them from their Religion; amongſt which, the principal are, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a diſcord amongſt the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, to flatter the Princes of that perſwaſion, and by giving them Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Wives, to place a Serpent in their boſom, to entice the <hi>cadets</hi> or younger Brothers of great Families by Spiritual Dignities and fat Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, by making all thoſe extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly welcome that go over to 'em, and inſtead of amuſing themſelves unſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully to write Books againſt the Proteſtant Divines, to cheriſh thoſe diſputes and quarrels that are amongſt
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:60638:109"/>
them; and it is viſibly certain, that the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Clergy have made very great progreſſes in this laſt Age, and are in a condition of making grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, comforting themſelves with a malicious joy, to ſee that their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, by internal Schiſms, weaken and deſtroy each other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 40. From what has been here ſaid, may eaſily be judged, Whether ever any Accommodation can be expected between the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants and Papiſts, whilſt each Party abandoning ſome of their Tenents, ſhall make ſuch Advances, as at laſt to agree in one common Confeſſion of their Faith, and leave the reſt, as obſcure and uſeleſs, to be diſputed of in the Schools; or elſe, that both might keep their Opinions, and that notwithſtanding the difference of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions, they might live with one another as Brethren in Chriſt, and Members of one and the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. Yet if we rightly examine the ſtate of affairs, and the Principles of the Popiſh Religion, we muſt own, that all ſuch Accommodations are
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:60638:109"/>
morally impoſſible; for we do not only diſcover an extream jarring and contradiction of Doctrines, but the Intereſts of each are quite oppoſite and contrary one to another: For, firſt, the Pope would willingly re-enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the poſſeſſion of the Church-Goods, but he will find it hard to get ſo ſweet a Morſel out of the Proteſtants Clutches.</p>
               <p>Then again, the Pope would fain be acknowledged the Head of <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> but the Proteſtants will never part with the <hi>jus circa ſacra,</hi> the choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt Jewel of their Soveraignty; and it is a <hi>contradictio in adjecto</hi> to live in good intelligence and friendſhip with the Pope, and not own him at the ſame time the ſupreme Monarch of the Church: Juſt as if any Stranger ſhould deſire to be naturaliz'd, and made a free Deniſon of <hi>England,</hi> and yet refuſe to acknowledge the King his Soveraign Lord.</p>
               <p>The Infallibility of the Pope is likewiſe the Corner-ſtone of the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which if once taken away, the whole Structure will fall to the
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:60638:110"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="189" facs="tcp:60638:110"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="190" facs="tcp:60638:111"/>
Ground; and therefore the Pope <hi>par raiſon d'etat,</hi> cannot yield the leaſt of thoſe points which occaſion the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion betwixt the Proteſtants and Papiſts; for if the Pope ſhould own that any the leaſt part of that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which he has hitherto main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, is falſe, he muſt grant at the ſame time that he is not infallible: Can he therefore err in one point? He may eaſily err in another: But if the Proteſtants grant that one Article of the Pope's Infallibility, they muſt alſo give him all the other contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted points. Now 'tis non-ſence to imagine that the Proteſtants will ever retract all that they have written againſt the Pope; and ſhould the Laity be brought to do it, what will the Clergy do? Where will they diſpoſe of their Wives and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore how good and how pious ſoever their Intention may have been, who have propos'd any means of an Accommodation, between the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants and Papiſts, which they call by the name of <hi>Syncretiſm,</hi> yet they
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:60638:111"/>
are in reality nothing but pure Whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and ſerve only to furniſh mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Raillery, and Diverſion to the Papiſts, who are alſo very well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, that the Proteſtant Divines ſhould amuſe themſelves with ſuch <hi>Chimaera's,</hi> ſince they are ſure to get by it, but never loſe any thing, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as the Proteſtants do not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall foul upon one another, on the account of this pretended <hi>Syncretiſm,</hi> but the common and united zeal which they heretofore bare againſt the Papiſts, is thereby extreamly weakened; for any one that does not underſtand the matter to the botom, when he hears them talk of an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation, will eaſily be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the Difference betwixt us is not ſo great or capital as has been repreſented. Now he that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits ſuch thoughts, will at the ſame time be apt to revolve in his mind the benefits and advantages he may find in the Roman Communion, and then he'll make no great ſcruple to bid adieu to the Proteſtant Religion; for 'tis with their Religion as with a
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:60638:112"/>
Maiden-head, or Town beſieg'd, which run a great riſque of being loſt, when once they begin to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 41. 'Tis a <hi>quaere</hi> whether the <hi>Pope,</hi> with the united help of all of his Perſwaſion, can bring the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants by force under his Juriſdiction? We anſwer, That the Papiſts do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably excel the Proteſtants in number; for on the Pope's ſide is all <hi>Italy, Spain, Portugal, France,</hi> and the greateſt part of <hi>Poland,</hi> as well as the weakeſt <hi>Cantons</hi> of <hi>Switzerland.</hi> In <hi>Germany</hi> are all the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, the Kingdom of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all <hi>Upper Hungary,</hi> the Biſhops and Prelates, the Houſe of <hi>Bavaria</hi> and <hi>Newburg,</hi> the Marqueſate of <hi>Baden,</hi> and ſome other Princes of leſs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; a great number of Counts, Lords, Free Knighthoods, and Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Cities, beſides a great many in Proteſtant Countries, which all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, according to my Eſtimate, will amount to two thirds of <hi>Germany.</hi> In <hi>Holland</hi> we find a great many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and there were a great many
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:60638:112"/>
of the ſame leaven in <hi>England, though (God be thanked) ſince the Happy Coming of Their Preſent Majeſties to the Crown, the Land is pretty well ſcowr'd of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the other ſide, we reckon among the Proteſtants the Kingdoms of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> with all their dependences, <hi>Suedeland, Denmark, Holland,</hi> the moſt of the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Electors and Princes, together with the Imperial Cities of <hi>Germany.</hi> The Proteſtants of <hi>France</hi> are at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſarm'd; thoſe of <hi>Poland</hi> are not in a condition to undertake any thing; the Cities of <hi>Pruſſia</hi> and <hi>Curland</hi> have enough to do to maintain the free exerciſe of their Religion; <hi>Tranſylva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> can do but little: And the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts have beſides, this advantage above the Proteſtants, That they all of 'em own the Pope for Supreme Head of their Church, and do, at leaſt with their Mouth, and externally, profeſs one and the ſame Faith. But on the contrary, the Proteſtants have no viſible Spiritual Head, but are miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably divided amongſt themſelves;
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:60638:113"/>
for, not to mention thoſe little Sects of <hi>Arminians, Socinians, Anabaptiſts,</hi> and the reſt, their Body is divided into almoſt two equal parts of <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> amongſt which a great many are as much imbitter'd againſt one another, as they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Common Enemy, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts: Beſides, there is no general Policy or Government in the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amongſt them, but in every ſtate the particular Soveraign regulates the Affairs thereof according to his own will and pleaſure<hi>:</hi> Nor can it be denied that (commonly ſpeaking) the Papiſts do with more Zeal, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and Induſtry promote the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement and propagation of their Religion, than do the Proteſtants, who have moſtly in view how they may conveniently ſubſiſt by their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, as the chiefeſt proſpect of Handicrafts-men is, how to get their Living by the Trade to which they apply themſelves: So that the ſearch of the Kingdom of God is as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and the laſt thing they take care for. Whereas the Monks and
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:60638:113"/>
Jeſuites, on the contrary, have brought themſelves into great repute by their Miſſions, both into the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt Indies;</hi> and though in the relations they give us thereof, they intermit a thouſand fabulous reports, yet the thing in it ſelf is extreamly lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>In fine, there is ſuch an irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable Jealouſie among the chiefeſt of the Proteſtant States, that it is morally impoſſible ever to perſwade them to ſubmit to one Head: As for example; Betwixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Suedeland</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> not to mention the reſt. Though again it muſt be owned too, that there are no leſs Jealouſies between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> which will ſcarcely permit them to act unanimouſly againſt the Proteſtants. So that notwithſtanding the great inequality in ſtrength that there is between the Proteſtants and Papiſts, the former need never appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the Oppreſſion of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="196" facs="tcp:60638:114"/>
In the mean while there is a great difference between the Proteſtants that form an Independent State, and thoſe that are under the Yoke of <hi>Popiſh Lords,</hi> for theſe are not half ſo well aſſur'd of the maintenance of their Religion as are the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus the Security of the</hi> French <hi>Proteſtants depends on the bare word of the King, and the Edict of</hi> Nan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes; <hi>ſo that they would be in a ſad condition, if the</hi> French <hi>King ſhould at any time be poſſeſt with a</hi> Spaniſh <hi>or</hi> Auſtrian <hi>Zeal: Yet I don't believe he will ever undertake to force them in the matter of Religion, as long as they live peaceably and contented with that Liberty he allows them; eſpecially if he conſiders the good Service they rendered to his Grandfather</hi> Henry <hi>the Fourth, and that he himſelf, without their aſſiſtance, had never arrived to the Crown of</hi> France.</p>
               <p>Nor can <hi>Poland</hi> eaſily ſuppreſs the exerciſe of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in <hi>Curland</hi> and <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> as long as <hi>Dantzick</hi> enjoys its Liberty. In
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:60638:114"/>
                  <hi>Germany</hi> the Proteſtants are ſtrong enough: So that if they were united under one Head, they would make a formidable Kingdom; but the great number of their Chiefs, the diverſity of their Intereſts, and their diſtance from one another, diminiſhes their Strength very conſiderably; ſo that the Emperor, in the ſpace of an hundred years, had twice reduc'd them to ſuch a condition, that their <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> (which are ſo inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly annex'd, that the loſs of one would have been a neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the other's loſs) had both been ruin'd without the aſſiſtance of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Suedeland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true, of late years ſome have pretended to hold forth this new Maxim, <q>That the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> are able to ſubſiſt and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their Liberties without the help of thoſe two Crowns, and that <hi>Brandenburg</hi> is very fit to have the management and direction in Chief of all their Affairs.</q> And 'tis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the real Intereſt of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> that ſuch an Opinion
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:60638:115"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="197" facs="tcp:60638:115"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="198" facs="tcp:60638:116"/>
ſhould prevail among the Proteſtants. 'Tis with this Pretext that the <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburger</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Lunen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> cover the deſire they have of putting themſelves in poſſeſſion of thoſe Lands which the King of <hi>Suedeland</hi> has in <hi>Germany;</hi> whilſt they give out, They are as well able to maintain them in the enjoyment of their Liberty and Religion, as the other Proteſtant States. Yet it is moſt certain, that if theſe two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhould attain their ends, their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Grandeur would render them leſs formidable to the Emperor, than they are at preſent, whilſt back'd and ſupported by the King of <hi>Suede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And they are no leſs decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, if they think to find as ſure a Support from <hi>Denmark</hi> or <hi>Holland,</hi> as they have received from <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Suedeland.</hi> And thirdly, Should the Emperor once attain to his deſire, and diſpoſſeſſing thoſe two Crowns of what they have at preſent in <hi>Germany,</hi> introduce again the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Faction, and mortifie the States by the maintenance of a ſtanding Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:60638:116"/>
and other Inconveniences of War, who at ſuch a time could oblige the Emperor to disband his Victorious Troops? And if, for example, the Emperor could find no Pretext to keep his Army together, and to oblige the Proteſtants to maintain it at their coſt, will <hi>Brandenburg</hi> and <hi>Lunenburg</hi> make head againſt him? And fourthly, If in caſe the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant States ſhould not find themſelves equal to ſo vaſt a Work, Whether thoſe two Crowns would at their Call come and help them? And whether their own Affairs would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to undertake ſo important a deſign? Or, laſtly, Whether there would fall down from Heaven ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus,</hi> to redeem them from the very brink of Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and make as great a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs as that mighty Conqueror once did?</p>
               <p>And as for ſuch as believe, that the Security of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion can conſiſt alone in Parchment and Seals; or that the Emperor will not attempt the Soveraignty of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi>
                  <pb n="200" facs="tcp:60638:117"/>
if ever a fair occaſion preſents it ſelf; whilſt he can pretext ſo ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Cauſes as is the reſtauration of the Catholick Religion, and Goods of the Eccleſiaſticks, they muſt have quite loſt all knowledge of preceding times; beſides, the Treaty of <hi>Nimmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> has ſhewn how vain and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs all ſuch Projects are.</p>
               <p>The Independent Proteſtant States need not fear being oblig'd to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don their Religion by any violent means; for as the uniformity of Religion cannot remove the Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies of State, which is notoriouſly evident from <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> and <hi>Holland;</hi> ſo neither can the difference of <hi>Religion</hi> produce this effect, that in caſe any potent State of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Perſwaſion ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to oppreſs a neighbouring Proteſtant, all the Papiſts ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the one, and immediately join with the other, eſpecially if they had any Intereſt in the preſervation of the State, that ſhould be in danger of ruine.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="201" facs="tcp:60638:117"/>
The laſtingneſs and conſervation of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> in thoſe States where it is profeſs'd, does chiefly conſiſt in the care that is taken to maintain it within the Country; whereto they have no need of ſuch ſubtile and artificial Devices, as are us'd in the ſupport of the Popedom, but the moſt ſimple and ordinary means are ſufficient; for it moſtly conſiſts herein, That the Schools and Churches be provided of learned and pious Teachers; That the Clergy, by a ſound Doctrine and virtuous Life, give a good Example to their Flocks; That every one be eaſily grounded in the true Fundamentals of their <hi>Religion,</hi> and eſpecially ſuch as are to be employed in Affairs of State, that they may be able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves againſt the Artifices of the Papiſts, chiefly when they happen to travel in <hi>Popiſh Countries.</hi> And laſtly, That the Clergy qualifie themſelves ſo as to be able to baffle their Adverſaries, and refute all their Quirks and Sophiſtical Arguments.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="202" facs="tcp:60638:118"/>
Some are of opinion, that it would be no ſmall advantage to us, if the two head Parties of the Proteſtants (which only differ in ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar opinions, whilſt the Intereſts of their Religions is one and the ſame) could be brought to an accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and union under one head; the which they imagine to be very fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, if we would lay aſide all Hate, Animoſities, Self-Love, Pride, Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niatrety, and unreaſonable Preventions.</p>
               <p>But if we examine well the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> and Humor of moſt of the World, we ſhall find this <hi>poſtulatum</hi> to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant; for if a man ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Controverſies written on the ſubject of Religion impartially, and unprevented, he would ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maz'd to ſee how the writers turn and wind themſelves on all ſides, to maintain the opinion they have once laid down, without having the leaſt regard to its Agreement or Repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to the Scriptures; And how often they renew Diſputes and Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions which have been refuted a thouſand times. Beſides, It can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:60638:118"/>
happen that one opinion ſhould be thought as good as the other; for ſuch an indifference in any one point, would ſhew that they did not much matter all the reſt. Furthermore, 'twould be very dangerous to make thoſe Articles, wherein we cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, <hi>problematick;</hi> nor can I tell by what Authority we preſume of our own Heads to make any Article Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental or <hi>Problematick.</hi> Some are likewiſe of the mind, that we ſhould draw up a Scheme of all the points, in which both parties agree, and try if from thence may be form'd a perfect <hi>Syſtem</hi> of Divinity, which from the beginning to the end, ſhould be compos'd, <hi>ad formam juſtae Artis.</hi> So that if this project could ſucceed, altho' there ſhould remain ſome different opinions, yet if they did not diſſolve the union and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuity of the whole body, we ſhould in the main, agree concerning the means of attaining Eternal Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and all the reſt would not be ſufficient to hinder us from uniting in one Church. But to judge right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:60638:119"/>
of this opinion, one ought firſt to ſee a model of ſuch a projected <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem.</hi> For my part, I know no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter means, than to commit the matter wholly to Divine Providence, which in its own time, will perhaps furniſh expedients, that the Wit of Man could not have imagin'd. For 'tis certain, that unſeaſonable means will only ſerve to create new Schiſms and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions: In the mean while, both parties, notwithſtanding the diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their Sentiments, ought to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite againſt the common Enemies, and to be really perſwaded, that the Pope is no better a Friend to the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theran,</hi> than to the <hi>Calviniſt.</hi> As for what belongs to thoſe little Sects of <hi>Socinians, Anabaptiſt,</hi> and ſuch like, 'tis impoſſible to hope for any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with them, whilſt thoſe believe that the Chriſtian Religion is nothing but a Philoſophy purely Moral, and theſe know not what to believe themſelves; to which we may add, That theſe laſt, have filled their Heads with a ſort of a new Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, which would render them very
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:60638:119"/>
dangerous to a State where they had the upper hand; but whether the <hi>Socinians</hi> have the ſame Sentiments, I cannot well determine, ſince they are not as yet become ſo powerful in any Republick, as to be able to oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion any Troubles or Revolutions.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
